Last time, on Tuesday this
week, we had a lecture on GPUs
and how to train,
how to use them,
and how to use multiple GPUs
for training, larger scaling,
your trainings, and so on.
An exciting, a new
topic that we've
added to this class
this year, which
is, I think, timely
and very important
with the increase of model
sizes and applications
that you see the AI
models have these days.
And before that, we talked about
we covered all of the key tasks
in computer vision,
from classification,
semantic segmentation,
object detection, instance
segmentation, and so on.
And we're going to revisit
some of these topics, some
of the results of the
models we talk about today.
So those tasks are
still quite important.
And then we talked about
visualizing and understanding
the models and seeing what
the models are learning.
One of the things
that we've discussed
was, for example, using
just in the early sessions,
we talked about nearest
neighbor and in the pixel space
and how we can actually do
find the class of images
based on only
pixels-based distances,
and we discussed how it's
actually not efficient.
And one of the things
that we talked about
was if we use the embedding
layers or the feature
space, feature layers, one of
those fully connected layers
in the feature maps there, from
a convolutional neural network
or any other network
architecture that we
use there, that could actually
be a good representation
of images.
And we talked about
the L2 distance,
if we use that as the
metric for nearest neighbor
in the feature space, feature
of these models, right?
So this means that
these features
are quite meaningful
for the specific task
that we had at hand.
And this means that
specifically, OK,
if we run a neural network,
a CNN, a ResNet, or even
the transformer models, and
look at the representations,
the learned representations,
in different contexts,
you may see these as referred
to with different names.
Learned large
representations, features,
embeddings, latent
space, and so on.
But these learned
representations or features
are very good representatives
of the images.
And if we have a way
to extract those,
we can always get the class
labels out of those features
as well by a simple linear
model, as you can see at the end
here.
But the major
challenge that exists
is training or
building these networks
at larger scale is
always challenging.
And can you tell me why
there is a challenge here?
So the thing is that
at larger scale,
we need a lot of labeled data
because this network is trained
starting from an image, and at
the end, we have class labels.
If we train this network,
yes, these features
are going to be very useful for
getting those class labels out,
right?
But at scale, we need a lot
of manual labeling efforts
to sit down and label
the images one by one.
If the task is
segmentation, you have
to label the pixels one
by one in every image,
and that is going to
be very challenging.
So the question
is is there a way
we can train neural networks
without the need for huge
manually labeled data sets?
So these manual labels
are the challenge,
and we want to see
if we can bypass them
in a way to train a
neural network that
gets us very good features.
And with that, the topic
of self-supervised learning
comes in light.
And that's what we are
going to cover today.
So having a large data set of,
say, images without any labels,
our hypothesis is that we
can train a neural network
using an objective function, a
pretext task that gets us good
features from images.
And then when it comes to
learning on a specific data set
with a smaller set of data
points, which have labels,
we can basically train, we can
transfer this trained encoder
and use that to extract
features for a downstream task
or downstream objective.
So here, we want to define
a pretext task, a task that
is general enough
to be able to learn
some good features
from the images
and then use that encoder,
let's call it encoder,
to solve another
problem, what we call
downstream task,
downstream objective, which
is the application
that you care about.
Like for example, we have a lot
of natural images downloaded
from the internet.
We can train
something out of it.
And then we have a small
data set of, for example,
one of these
industrial applications
or medical applications that
we have few labeled images on.
And we can now use that
transferred knowledge
to extract features and then
classify or perform the task
that we are interested in.
So we want to delve
into this topic
and go a little bit
deeper in understanding
the different components.
In a nutshell, what
self-supervised learning is,
as I said, defining this
pretext task on the data
set with no labels.
Encoder often gets us some
learned representations.
And then another module
of the same neural network
generates or does transfer
the learned representations
into the output
space, which could
be labels or outputs
that automatically
are generated from the data.
They are not manual annotations.
So if we can do this, then we
have an objective function,
a loss function,
and a neural network
to be trained with
loss function.
As you can see here, we call the
second part sometimes decoder,
a classifier, a regressor,
depending on how
we define our pretext task.
I will give you some
examples, but these
could be any form of framework.
But when it's encoder
and then a decoder,
this is more of an
autoencoding framework
that I'll talk briefly about.
So after we do this training
with the pretext task,
now we can use the encoder
and the learn representations
for a downstream
task, which we just
need to add one layer or even a
fully connected neural network,
a linear function, or a fully
connected neural network that
predicts the labels, and
these labels are coming now
from the data set.
So that's the major,
that's the main concept
of self-supervised learning,
that the pretext version of it,
a portion of it doesn't
require any labeled data to do
the training.
But how to define
the pretext task
itself is not that
straightforward.
There are many different
ways of defining those.
For example, just
keep in mind that we
want to define the
pretext task in a way
that it's, first, general enough
that can get us good features
and doesn't require
manual labeling.
So the labels should come
from the data itself, right?
So one example would be image
completion, where we half
of the image or
parts of the image.
And we define a task to given
the parts that are unmasked,
predict the parts
that are masked.
Or for example, we rotate the
image with a specific angle,
and the task is to
take the image as input
and predict what's the rotation
angle that it's gone through.
And the other one could
be a jigsaw puzzle,
where we have patches of the
image that are not ordered,
but the task is to output the
correct order of these patches.
And colorization is
one of the popular ones
that these are the
four that we'll
be covering very quickly today.
But given the black and
white version of the image,
predict the colors for
each of the pixels.
So solving the pretext
task allows the model
to learn good features.
That's what we wanted.
And we can
automatically generate
labels for the pretext tasks.
So the two points
that I mentioned
we need for a task that could
be qualified as a good pretext
task for self-supervised
learning.
Some other quick
considerations to always
keep in mind, how to evaluate
a self-supervised learning
framework.
There are many different pieces
and areas that you can actually
look into the
pretext task itself
because we are generating
the labels and so on.
It gives us the power
to do some evaluation
of how good the model is able
to solve that pretext task.
So that's one of the factors.
Then representation
quality itself
is sometimes very important.
Looking at, for example,
only representations
without any fine
tuning or anything
that I'll be talking
about or even
clustering the
representations to see,
do we see a pattern in
the representations?
And sometimes, there are some
good dimensionality reduction
algorithms.
I'm referring to t-SNE here,
which we didn't very much talk
about, but this is a
dimensionality reduction
framework that you can
reduce the dimensionality
of the learned representations
and then visualize it in 2D
or 3D and see if there is
a pattern that you can find
in your representations.
So robustness, generalization,
and computational efficiency,
these are all quite important.
But the most important thing,
the most important aspect
that we are after
is the performance
on the downstream task.
Because we are doing the
entire self-supervised learning
and define the
tasks, pretext tasks,
and so on to be able
to improve results
for a task of interest or
something that we care about.
Let's see some quick examples
of how this could be done.
This is an example of
let's rotate the images
and then predict the degree
of rotation as the output.
So we can train this in
a self-supervised manner
without the need for labels
of the objects in the image.
And we have a bunch of
convolutional layers
in this example and then a
fully connected neural network
at the end to do this either
regression or classification
task.
And this means that
this is giving us
a set of good features, a
good feature extractor, which
we can at the end remove
these tasks, pretext
task, specific parts, the FC
layers, and put one layer,
or in some cases,
multiple layers
to classify the features
into the object label.
So this time, we use the object
labels to do the prediction
and train this linear
function itself.
So we often look for
a shallow network
because if the features
are good enough, then
we don't need to do
a lot of training
on getting the class labels out.
So this is self-supervised
learning in general.
And although we are talking
about the computer vision
applications.
But this paradigm of
self-supervised learning
was actually what enabled all
of these large language models.
GPT-4 and all of
these frameworks
are trained with mostly raw data
without any manual labeling.
And not just in language
models, in speech,
and these days,
quite a lot in robot
and robotics and
reinforcement learning.
Because when we don't
need any me labeling data,
we can start capturing data,
raw data without any manual
labeling and use
those for training.
And that's why you see so many
self-driving cars in the Bay
Area collecting data because
that's getting them the data,
and they don't have to
really annotate the data,
but they can still
train models based on.
So with that, today's agenda
will cover some of these pretext
tasks from image
transformations,
and then I will
talk a little bit
about a set of
algorithms that are
around contrastive
representation learning that
are slightly different from
these image transformation based
pretext tasks but
have shown promise.
So let's start with
the first part.
And there we will cover
the tasks one by one.
So I talked quite a lot about
rotation, predicting rotations.
Let's see if we can
actually rotate the images
with random or arbitrary
degrees and predict the rotation
angle with a model.
And our hypothesis here
is that the model, a model
could recognize the correct
rotation of an object
only if it has the common
sense visual common
sense of what the object
should look like unperturbed.
So these models mostly are
designed around this concept
of visual common sense.
And then if the model
is able to capture
that it means that it is
also able to summarize
the image, the entire image,
into a useful set of features,
good features.
This paper published in
2018 implemented this
with just exploring four
different angles of 0,
19, 90, 180, and 270, these
rotating images with one
of these angles and then using
a convolutional neural network
to basically predict
what each of these
rotations the output is.
And because they only created
four different outputs,
this is a classification
task because it only
has four different cases.
It doesn't have to
predict the exact value
of the angle, the degrees.
But it's actually
just predicting
one of these four
classes of 0, 1, 2, or 3.
y0, 1, 2, or 3.
So with that, the authors
were able to learn
good representations.
And with those
representations, they
started training
the neural network
at a downstream
application, basically fine
tuning the neural network based
on fine tuning the encoders
and also the classifier.
Actually, in this case, they
froze first and second layers,
and then they fine tuned
the last convolution
layer and the linear layer.
So it's not entirely fine
tuning the entire network,
but they were able to
get very good results.
This is on CIFAR10 data
set, one of the data
sets that we've
talked about earlier.
You see that when the
model is pre-trained,
it starts with a good
accuracy to start with.
So it means that it
already is in a good shape,
and it's having a good
understanding of the objects,
even in the very
first iterations.
But if the task
is simple enough,
CIFAR10 is actually not too
hard to train a model for.
If the task is simple enough,
the supervised version,
the fully supervised
version, and the one that
starts with pre-training, often
converge to the same number,
same accuracy.
But again, if the
task is simple enough,
in very hard application, in
much harder to applications,
often the supervised learning
frameworks, if we don't
do any pre-training,
large scale pre-training,
we don't get as good results.
OK.
So they've done also
some applications,
some experiments on this
PASCAL VOC 2017 data
sets which involves
a number of tasks,
including classification,
detection, and segmentation.
And of these three
sets of tasks,
they've used different
setups of just training
a few fully connected
layers or all
of the layers for the
classification, detection,
and segmentation tasks.
If you look at the
ImageNet labels,
like if we have a
huge labeled data set,
and we pre-train
on that data set.
We already get a
very high accuracy.
But again, have this
in mind that this
is ImageNet with all
of the labels involved
for the pre-training.
But if we don't do any
supervised pre-training,
and the pre-training is all
based on self-supervised,
it's showing that this
rotation framework is
doing a much better job than
many of the other counterparts,
any of the other methods
that we don't actually
go into many of the
detail of many of those,
but it's showing efficacy for
this rotation pretext task.
And see how it's different,
how much better it
is if you start with a random
initialization of the weights.
So the random initialization
versus this pretraining
with rotation, pretext task.
The difference is huge, and this
rotation pretext task is not
equal, but it's
close to pre-training
on the entire ImageNet.
So one other thing
that they've looked
into in this paper was
looking at the features
and how the learned
features are meaningful.
I mentioned earlier that one
of the ways of evaluating
the pretext tasks,
generally self-supervised
learning frameworks, is
to look at the features.
And you can always
go from the features
from the fully connected layers.
We talked about grad cam and all
of those other attention-based
frameworks, how we can
go from the features
back to the image space.
So this evaluation
involves projecting those
into the image space and seeing
what the model is looking at.
If you look at the attention
maps for the supervised model,
often the supervised
model has more
focused maps because
it's only trying
to solve one single
task of classification.
So if it captures the eye
and the shape around it,
it doesn't care about the
other parts very much.
But in cases of
self-supervised learning,
often, more features,
more areas are
covered because it has to have
a more holistic understanding
of the image because
we don't know what
the downstream task
is, but the goal
is to perform equally
well in many of those.
So that's one of the tasks.
If you do have any
questions, keep it.
I'll stop after going
over some of the tasks.
And if your question
was not answered,
then I would be
happy to answer that.
OK.
Another one, another
popular pretext task
was to basically
create this 3 by 3 grid
and then use networks to
predict the location of each
of the given patches with
respect to the sensor patch.
So for this patch,
which is from here,
the output should be 3
because we only have 8--
This is 3 by 3, and the
center patch is the reference.
So this also turns out to be an
eight-way classification task.
It's getting any
of these patches,
and it's trying to output what
the location of that given patch
is with respect to
the center patch.
So this was another example.
But this other follow-up
paper, paper publication,
which turned this into a
jigsaw puzzle framework,
was instead of asking
the model to just predict
which of these
eight patches it is,
it tried to predict
the exact permutation,
the right permutation.
So what they've done was they
used the same three by three
grid, took all of the patches,
shuffled them randomly, and then
ask the neural network
to say which one should
be the correct permutation.
So they basically predict
the correct permutations.
Can you tell me what is
the number of permutations
you can have for this setup?
Say again?
9 factorial.
Yes, exactly.
So it's a huge number, right?
300,000 something, I think.
But what they've
done was they've
created this lookup table with
only 64 plausible, possible
permutations.
And then only they
consider 64 permutations.
And then they're shuffling
that, they do the shuffling
based on one of these 64.
And then the output will also
be just the 60, 64 sized vector.
So again, this turns out to be
just a simple classification
task with 64 output classes.
And they've shown this
is also a great idea
for solving to define
as a pretext task,
and on the same data set
with similar type of tasks
that I talked about and how
the supervision is done.
They've shown their
method was outperforming
some of the more previous
models, previous frameworks.
And again, remember that
this was published in 2016.
So next pretext task
is just inpainting
predicting what is missing.
So what they have done here
was a simple masking strategy,
you mask parts of the
image and then you
ask the model to inpaint
those parts that are masked.
So how it was done, simple
masking on the input image.
But because we have
all of the images,
we actually have
the desired output.
So an encoder turns this
into a feature space,
and then that feature
space is also,
there are some fully connected
layers in the middle,
and then there is a
decoder that decodes
the parts that is missing.
And the loss function
is comparing the output
with what the ground truth was.
And this is basically learning
to reconstruct the missing
pixels.
Again, we've talked about
autoencoders a couple of times
before, and this is also some
form of an autoencoder that
encodes the input image
into a representation
that you want to
decode the output.
But this autoencoder is trained
with a masking strategy, masking
objective.
So just to show
you some examples,
the inpainting evaluations
are a little bit
interesting and tricky because
when you want to inpaint,
there are so many different ways
of inpainting this image, right?
And we can say there is just one
output to do in this case here.
Reconstruction-based
frameworks, earlier
reconstruction-based
frameworks were actually
creating a lot of fuzzy
and very smooth outputs.
And that's why this paper
that I'm referring to here
was actually using an
additional adversarial objective
function, which I'm not going
to go into details because this
is a topic of discussion for the
next lecture, generative models.
But generally, how
these frameworks work,
we have a reconstruction loss.
And reconstruction
loss is basically
calculating the difference
between the patch,
between the image x and
the image after it's
passed through the encoder.
And then this is element
wise multiplication.
And we also have this
mask here because we
want to only calculate
the loss function,
the objective function,
only on the masked area.
So we do element wise
multiplication with the mask
as well.
And this basically gives
us the reconstruction loss
for that part of the
mask that we had.
So as I said, it's
also supplemented
with an adversarial objective
adversarial learning loss
function, which ensures the
images that are generated
are real looking.
So with that, they have
been able to improve
the parts that are reconstructed
to look a little bit better.
But again, details will be
discussed in the next lecture.
So this reconstruction
framework was actually
able to again
provide, and this ours
is the same, provide
additional benefit when
it's run on the same
classification, detection,
and segmentation task on
same set of data sets.
I will come back to this
reconstruction-based frameworks
and masking in a
bit because it's
one of the most used models or
pretext tasks that these days
are used for pre-training.
So I'll come back to this.
But before that, let me
introduce this other pretext
task of image coloring.
And this is another very
simple framework setup
that we turn a colored image
because our data set is mostly
colored images, right?
We turn that colored image
into its components or channels
that separate the lightness,
the illumination from the color
itself.
There are several
color spaces if you've
taken courses like
computer graphics
or CS-131, other
computer vision class.
You know that there are so
many different color spaces.
Mostly, in computer
vision, we use RGB.
But if you want to separate
lightness, illumination
from color, there are
some other color spaces.
For example, LAB
color space, LAB,
is one of those color spaces
that separates lightness
from color.
So we have one channel for
lightness and two channels
for defining the actual color.
And if we add these two
all together L, A, and B,
all three channels
together, we can actually
get the colored image.
So the pretext task
here is simple.
Given the L channel, predict
the A and B channels, right?
So again, we don't need to
do any manual annotation.
It's already in the data.
And this was extended
into other frameworks.
Why should we only look at
like given L, predict A and B.
We can also do the
reverse, right?
And that led us to
split, something
that we call a split
brain autoencoder, where
the input image is split, is
basically turned into one.
The L channel, lightness
channel, and the color channels.
These two images,
this is one channel.
This is two channels of color.
And we train two functions,
two neural networks,
sets of layers to
predict the other one.
And then at the end, in order
to calculate the loss function
and backprop, we
just merge these two
to generate the actual
image and a loss an L2 loss.
Any distance function
can help with training
this neural network.
In a more generic
framework or formulation,
the idea is given one
channel or a set of channels,
predict the others,
and do the same for X2.
So sets of channels X1,
sets of channels X2.
So given one we can predict
the other one, and these
are the neural
networks for those.
Merging them we'll get
the value the image
and then loss function
would be simple.
So if we have such
a framework we
can run it on everything, not
just color and illumination.
We can have data from some
of these RGBD sensors, those
that have RGB channels
and depth channels,
like for example,
connect and other sensors
that they use in robotics.
And given the RGB channel,
predict the depth and vice
versa.
And this was a very
successful downstream task
that was used for
different applications.
And as you can see this
model and this paper
that I just the split brain and
the papers that the model that
predicts colorizes the images
is those features themselves.
They do have actually
a very good level
of accuracy for predicting
the class labels.
And you can see, there are
many different other frameworks
that are used also in
terms of comparisons.
Again, this is not as good
as supervised learning
because there is no
label involved here
and it's just based on
the learned features
with concatenated
features out of F1 and F2.
OK, so the image
coloring pretext task
was actually very interesting
because now we could not only
use it for pre-training
neural networks,
but it was also
itself useful somehow,
because now we could
colorize images that we
don't have a colored version.
So we could colorize
images and videos
that we don't have a
colored version of those.
And not only that, one of
the other interesting results
that they've shown
in the paper was
this image of Yosemite and the
Half Dome that they colorized.
The interesting thing
that is seen in this image
is the consistency
between the actual object,
the Half Dome or trees, or
the bridge and its reflection
in the water.
So the model was also
able to understand
that this reflection
should also somehow
preserve the color based
on how it was trained
on vast amounts of data.
Again, keep in mind
that these models
are all pre-large language,
large vision models.
And they have been
trained on specific tasks.
So they're not trained
for solving everything.
So this could be actually
extended into video settings.
Because now if we have a video,
we can have a reference frame
that has the color and do the
coloring for the follow-up
frames and how this is done.
This is very simple
because with--
this is also very useful because
with colorizing future frames
in the video, what
we are doing is
we basically try to track
pixels and objects in the video,
and the model
implicitly learns how
these tracks should be formed.
So the hypothesis is learning
to color video frames
should allow a model to
learn to track regions
or objects without labels.
And learning to color
videos because there
are a lot of correspondences is
an interesting task by itself.
I would suggest taking
a look at the details.
I'll very briefly
to talk about them.
So if you have a
reference frame, what
we need to do is for
coloring the input frame,
we need to find the
pointers of where that's
a specific object or pixel is.
And then based on that
see what the color
is and copy what the
color is as the color
for that pixel as the
output, as the target color.
And how this is done
is very much similar
to the same topic of attention
that we talked about.
So it's about forming
attention for each
of the pixels for each
input frame, sorry reference
frame and target frame.
We often run a CNN to see what
features around those pixels
should be used.
And using those features,
now we can calculate,
for each of the
target pixels, we
can calculate the
attention or the distance
to all of the frames, all of the
pixels in the reference frame.
And then after defining
this attention with respect
to the pixel of
interest in the target
frame with all of the pixels
in the reference frame.
Now we can do an average
color of all of based
on those attention modules.
So attention is basically just
similarity between the two.
So anyways with
that, what we can do
is we can just get
the output color
as an average with that tension
and then ultimately calculate
the loss function because we
have the values of the colors,
the right colors of
those pixels in our data.
And this was able to,
with this reference frame,
colorize the images.
You see how consistent this
becomes in terms of coloring.
If we color them separately
without this consistency
over time, you often see, for
example, the person's shirt
or clothing changes color
because there is no constraint
to keep it consistent.
And then there has been
also some very interesting
applications, because now that
you are calculating attention
to a reference frame,
you're actually
able to track objects,
track segments in videos,
and even identify key
points in the videos.
That's a good question.
You're asking your question
is about this slide basically,
and how the encoder knows
about the data to begin with
and gets us good
learned representations.
So all of these tasks that
I presented and defined
are trying to do something here
at either decoding, classifying,
or using regression to
generate some outputs to be
able to train this encoder.
So if your original
images, if these
are all natural images taken
off of internet or ImageNet
or whatever, then you
are learning an encoder
that can extract features
from those types of images
with the pretext task.
And then when you
remove the decoder
and add this
classifier to the end,
you only need to
train this part,
because this encoder was
already trained with all
of these pre-training tasks
that I just talked about.
You're asking if the
labels are coming
from the decoder for
pre-training the encoder,
and the answer to that is, yes.
That's why we define
the pretext tasks,
because we want to have
some labels, some outputs.
And then based on
those outputs we try
to train this entire network.
And on the way of
predicting the right labels,
this encoder is also trained.
Good question.
You're asking if encoder and
decoder are one big neural
network or there is differences.
In different papers,
in different works,
it has been
completely different.
In some cases, your encoder
and not just decoder,
that's why I'm
calling it classifier.
In the example that I showed
you about predicting the degree,
this is just a simple
neural network.
The decoder is these FC layers.
So this could be
one entire network.
And then you're replacing
it with something
for your downstream task.
But in some cases, for example,
when I talked about auto
encoding an image and then
decoding another image,
you often have two
neural networks
that are trained
end-to-end because you
want to make use of that
representation space
in the middle.
And in the next thing
that I want to talk about,
masked autoencoders, even there
is no symmetry between encoders
and decoders.
They can be just two
different frameworks,
two different neural networks,
even without any symmetry
to train the task.
So this is very
much task dependent,
pretext task dependent.
But there could be belonging
to the same architecture
that we know about,
say, CNN or ResNet,
or there could be two
different architectures, even
without any symmetry.
Remember that these are
the very first methods
for self-supervised learning.
So they're not supposed
to be solving everything.
That's just a quick
disclaimer, but the idea
is, the hypothesis here
is, if the model is
able to say this is
90 degree rotated,
it means that implicitly,
it's understanding
the right rotation, sorry,
right orientation and direction.
And then it will
be able to if given
a right an unrotated image,
it's able to recognize
what it is in it.
But this is a limited task
by itself, I agree with that.
The question that you have
is why here they use 64.
That's a good question.
But that's also an arbitrary
choice, almost arbitrary choice.
As I said, there are
many different types
of different number of
permutations here 9 factorial.
So it's a very big number.
It doesn't make sense for us
to be predicting all of those.
What the authors did
here, they decided
to select a few of
those perturbations
that there is enough
variation because many
of those perturbations is just
like one patch switched only.
So they selected 64 of those
that they have the largest
difference distance
between them,
and they just selected
64 because they wanted
to solve the classification
problem instead
of other types of tasks.
OK.
So I've been talking about
these frameworks that
often do some transformation
on the image or the videos
and so on.
And this brings us to
this newer framework,
which is published in 2021.
And then there has been so
many follow-ups on this,
and it's been a great framework
for pre-training for many tasks,
even if these days when
we want to pre-train
on a data set on raw data sets,
we often use this MAE framework.
It's called Masked
Auto Encoders.
It is also reconstruction
based framework
similar to that masking strategy
in painting that I mentioned,
but this is far more detailed.
And as you can
see, this framework
is not just selecting one mask.
There are so many different
patches and places
that they do masking with
even more aggressive sampling
rates, 50% masking or 75
masking rates and ratios.
And through training
in larger scale,
they have shown
that not only they
are able to reconstruct
all of those masked areas,
they are also getting very good
encoders that can summarize
the images into good features.
And how this was done
was through defining
a encoder and a decoder.
And that's one of
the examples that I
said these are not symmetric.
And encoders and decoder,
so a large portion
of the input masks.
Input patches are masked and
the ones that are not masked,
they are given to the encoder
to encode in two features that
are then passed through decoder
to generate the complete image.
But let's go a little bit into
details of what this means.
I do have some of
the details on how
these models are trained here.
But I very briefly
just explained to you
how these models often work.
The encoder here is very
much similar to ViTs.
All of them are based on
transformers, the ViTs
that we've talked about.
Similar to the ViTs, the
images are split into patches.
The patches are then
sampled, so uniform sampling
is what they've done
and they've shown 75%
sampling was quite efficient
in the experiments.
And they use a
high masking ratio,
and then this makes the
prediction task very challenging
and challenging in
the set of pretext
for pretext tasks in
self-supervised learning
means the task is meaningful.
The task is very good
because the model
has to learn good features
to be able to reconstruct it.
So with that high
sampling, high ratio
of sampling, what it can
do is they can actually
augment the data by a lot
too, because each time you
mask 75% of the data, so
you can reuse the same image
multiple and multiple
times during training.
So you will have so much of
data to train this encoder with.
And then that's why they use
a huge encoder, a large ViT
in as their encoder.
So this encoder itself only
sees 25% of the samples.
The patches embeds those two
with first linear projection
to some embedding spaces.
Then positional embeddings
are added exactly same
as what we mentioned for ViTs.
And all of these are
transformer blocks.
And the encoder is very large,
that's what I just mentioned.
And then when it comes
to the decoding part,
so we have the embeddings
of all of those patches
that were present for the
patches that were masked
or were missing.
For those, there is a
trainable parameter,
very much similar to that
class token that we had.
A shared masked masked
token that is basically
in some sort of average.
We can consider that
as an average patch,
an average representation
that is put for the ones that
are missing are masked, and then
the decoder has to transfer them
to the image patches
of the entire image,
and then the entire image is
the output target is the output.
So how we train this,
this is a simple MSE
based mean squared error loss
function for between the image
and the reconstructed
image, the loss function
is only computed for
the masked patches
similar to the previous one
that I just talked about.
And then what it has is--
When we do the training,
they've shown in the paper
that you can do either linear
probing or full fine tuning
to use it for your
downstream tasks,
for any of the applications
that you have in mind.
And in linear
probing, what happens
is you often have your
encoder frozen and then use
the learned representations and
only learn a linear function
for the final task.
And this mark, it means
that it's being trained,
but in full fine
tuning, in fine tuning,
the pre-trained
encoders are also
fine tuned, either all of them
or just few transformer blocks.
And that's the fine
tuning framework.
The linear probing
provides a measure
of representation quality,
how those representations
features are, and fine
tuning always exploits models
near to potential to
adapt for new tasks.
OK, so if you're
interested in this topic
and if you're planning
to use this paper,
I highly advise looking at
the paper in its follow-ups.
There are so many discussions
around different aspects
model choices,
hyperparameters, masking ratio
is one thing they've shown with
the masking ratio that the 75%
is actually giving them
a very high accuracy.
So 75% that's the reason
that it was chosen.
Decoder depth, decoder width,
mask tokens, reconstruction
targets, data augmentation
how it's helpful
and mask sampling method I'm
showing the results here again.
Mask sampling method
is mostly around
should they use some random
masking blocks or grid
type of masking.
You see the examples here, and
they've came to the conclusion
that this random masking
was the best choice.
And finally they've
been able to show
that MAE is doing a
much better job compared
to many of the other
methods that were used.
So some of the other
state of the art methods
were actually Dino and Moco V3.
If you have time, I will
briefly go over them.
But this framework was
actually outperforming
those that are more at the
time, advanced frameworks
of contrastive learning.
So I'll stop for a few
questions if you have any.
Let me just summarize
what we've talked about.
Pretext tasks were
actually very important.
And as I said their
focus is on understanding
the visual common sense.
And one of the things
that also related
to some of the questions
that were asked, we can see
is coming up with an individual
pretext task is often
challenging because the
learned representations may not
be general enough because of the
type of tasks that you define.
For example, if you're using
completion, rotation prediction,
or jigsaw puzzle
or colorization,
you learned representations
are good for solving
those specific tasks,
and they may not
be very good for
general pretext tasks.
So the question is in
split brain autoencoder,
how does the model know how to
predict the other channel given
for example L channel,
the illumination channel,
lightness channel.
So let me answer your
question with a question.
When you're training a model
to predict classes of objects
in the image, how
does the encoder
know what features to extract
to predict the class of models?
Labeled data, because what
you're doing is you're
back propagating a
loss value that is
calculated around those labels.
It's the same story here.
We define the network that
takes one of the channels
and outputs the other channel.
How this was trained
was by back propagating
what the output should be.
The output was
the other channel.
We do have the other
channel in the data.
So instead of defining the
task being a classification
of predicting the
class of the objects,
here we define the
task to be predicting
the color of the pixels.
And the color of the
pixels, we already
have them in the data set,
so the loss function still
can be calculated
and back propagated.
So the question is
how these outputs are
used as input to the decoder.
So this is, again, a VIT
transformer style framework
encoder that turns every input
to a token as the output that
is representation of that
specific input patch.
So we've talked about this.
But then we know that this is
not the list of all patches,
there are some of the
patches that are masked.
For those that are
masked, we also
train this encoder
outputs a shared mask
token, a token that is basically
an average token, for example.
It's a learnable parameter.
We can't necessarily
interpret it,
but we can say it's
probably something
that is similar to a mask
like an average token.
So that's shared mask token
is put in the place of those
that are missing.
And then this long vector,
long sequence is created.
Decoder, another
transformer framework
takes this long set of
tokens and outputs those
that are projected as
the output pixel value.
Perfect, so we only have 15
minutes and a lot of things
to cover.
But I think what I wanted
to get out of this session,
was for you to understand
what pretext tasks are,
and how we define them.
And one of the most
used frameworks
right now is the masked
autoencoder, which we actually
covered to some extent.
But anyways, I was
here that we did look
at these transformations,
and then we
know that all of
these transformations
are actually the same object
as the original image,
just in a different form.
But then we also have the
knowledge that in the data set,
we have other objects that
look completely different.
So if I define a
task that can say
these that belong to the
same object, same pixel,
try to bring them close in
the representation space,
basically attract them to each
other in the representation
space, and those that are not--
that they do not belong
to the same object,
try to maximize the
distance between them
in the latent space, basically
repel the representation
of these two images.
Then this is another
task that is often
referred to as contrastive
learning, contrastive
representation
learning, and there
are quite a number of very
interesting methods to look at.
We have sampled there are so
many papers in this space,
especially around
2019's to 2020's, and so
on around those years.
Sinclair McCaw, CBC, and
then ultimately dyno,
which actually borrows concepts
from contrastive learning
but is not necessarily
contrastive learning framework.
And what we do there is in order
to define, attract and repel
functions, characteristics
or regularize the model based
on those, we define the
reference image as x, and then
all of those that
are transformations
of the same as positive
samples and all
of the other objects
in the data set,
or in the batch as
negative samples.
And these positive
and negative samples
will basically
define a way for us
to calculate the loss function.
How can we do that?
Assume we have a
scoring function.
We want to get a
scoring function that
says the score for the
reference image encoded version,
features of the reference
image and the features
of a positive sample should be
larger than the score that is,
comparing the reference image
and the negative samples.
So with this type of
scoring function, if we--
so basically to define this
type of scoring function,
we define a loss
function based on that.
After training the
scoring function S,
you can see this S is
the same as the score
in the previous slide.
So if we have that
scoring function,
now in order to
attract and repel,
we can use this
framework of turn
them a softmax setup with
exp that turn those scores
into probability values.
And then in the
denominator, you see
all of the other negative
samples that are used
are considered.
In order to
implement actually we
use this we use the
batch learning framework.
All of the other
negative samples
that belong to other
objects in the batch
are taken as negative samples,
and one of the transform
is as the positive sample.
So we define the loss
function like this.
And a score for
the positive pair,
score for all of the
other negative pairs.
And this function is very
similar to what we've actually
discussed before.
Any ideas?
This is the cross entropy
for multi classes.
So if we have n samples--
sorry n samples, yes, then in
this case, we have n samples.
So the softmax is if you
have multiple classes,
if you have 10
classes as the output,
it wants to maximize the
score for one of those 10,
and minimize for the rest of it.
It's the same story here.
We want to maximize
this score, but minimize
the score between a
negative and reference.
So it's the same concept
that we discussed
about multi-class
classification,
but put it in the
form of formulation
of contrastive for
this loss function
as contrastive learning.
This function is called info
NCE or the information Noise
Contrastive
Estimation loss, which
was proposed in this paper.
And there are a lot of
theoretical discussions
in the paper that this
objective, this loss function
measures the dependencies,
sorry that it's a lower bound
on mutual information.
And what mutual information
is, when you have two images
and you calculate the mutual
information between them,
it's basically measuring
the dependencies
or shared information
between these two images.
So what we want
to do is, we want
to maximize shared information
between x and x plus,
but minimize the shared
information for x and x minuses.
So the paper says and
again, this will itself
take half an hour to go into.
So you should definitely
take a look at the paper
if you're interested, that the
negative of this loss function
info NCE, is a lower bound on
mutual information between x
and x plus.
So a lower bound on
mutual information
if the negative of it is a lower
bound on mutual information.
If I minimize the info
NCE, I'm basically
maximizing the
mutual information
between x and x plus.
So this is what I really want.
So that's why we take
this as the loss function
and start minimizing that value.
There is also another
theoretical aspect
in the info NCE paper
that says the larger
the number of negative
samples the tighter the bound.
So it tightens the bound
based on the number
of negative samples.
So that's why for training and
loss function a neural network
with this type of loss function,
we need a huge batch size.
With a larger number
of negative samples,
we'll get better and much
faster training convergence.
And then this loss function
was used in a number
of different frameworks.
And in the next few
minutes, I'm just
going to tell you what
those frameworks are.
For example, Sinclair
is a simple framework
for contrastive learning, is
basically taking each image,
do the two transformations
of the same image,
transfer it into the
representation space.
And what it does
is it calculates
the cosine similarity between
embeddings representations.
But before doing that, it does a
linear or non-linear projection
into a set of features z,
that calculates the distance
between those in this space.
And this is the way
that they do this,
generating this
positive samples.
And for generating
positive samples,
all sorts of transformations
would make sense.
The details are
basically covered here.
Generate a positive pair by
sampling data augmentation
functions.
So we sample a few of those
then we calculate the inverse
and see loss on the pairs.
And this is what we iterate
because each sample has 2n
multiplied by n samples
that we have created.
So what happens is we
take a list of images
in the mini batch, in
the batch that we have,
and pass them through
encoder for both variations
of the same image.
So each of the images basically
will have a transformed version
of it.
And next, so we have sub 2n
samples in the batch now.
And then this
means that for each
of the samples the next one,
these two are positive samples,
and everything else is negative.
So for the first one, the
second image is positive.
Everything else is negative.
For the second one
the first is positive
and everything else is negative.
And this repeats for all
of the samples there.
So this is a high level
definition of SimCLR.
Please note that we have
in assignment 3, a question
related to SimCLR that you will
be exploring this framework
a little bit more.
But be careful that the
definition is slightly
different from what the
standard definition that I
presented here.
And make sure you follow the
instructions in the assignment.
So SimCLR was actually
very successful.
It was able to without
the use of labels or--
and then a training
a linear classifier
on top of the features,
it was able to surpass
all of the previous works
and even basically generate
results comparable to
the supervised learning,
fully supervised
learning frameworks.
Although we need a larger
neural network because now
we are learning more
generic features.
But in terms of
accuracy, this was
not as it was comparable to what
we had for supervised learning.
So the interesting
thing with SimCLR
and some of the
results around it
was that there
are a few choices.
Actually, let me spend
time on the main choices.
You may have this question of
why did we project the features
into a new variable instead of
using the same representations?
So this was a design choice
that they made in SimCLR,
because they rightly
so assume that when
we have an objective
function that
does this contrast
between samples,
you often lose some
more information,
some extra information
that do not
help with the contrastive
learning framework.
So in order to preserve all
of those extra features,
representations
are defined as h,
but then there is this linear
or non-linear projection--
in their paper they use
non-linear projection,
to get the z values that they
can calculate influencer.
So that's one important
design choice.
And the other one is I mentioned
earlier large batch sizes.
You need huge batch
sizes, larger batch sizes
to be able to get better
SimCLR performance.
And we talked about it, how
and why this is the case.
But we can't always
do large batch sizes
for many of the
tasks that we have
at hand because of constraints
in memory and so on.
And that was why a
number of follow ups,
for example, mocha was proposed
momentum contrastive learning.
Instead of using the samples,
all of the negative samples
in the batch, what it
does is it creates a queue
and keeps a history of
the negative samples
across batches over
time in the model.
So it doesn't only depend on the
negative samples in the batch,
it has a separate
queue that is defined
and keeps a number of negative
samples and changes it,
updates it over time to train,
to do the inference loss,
the contrastive loss here.
But because we have this
queue, we cannot back propagate
because those samples are
not in the batch anymore.
So we cannot back propagate
for the negative samples,
and that's why it had
to separate the encoder
for positive samples,
which are now called query.
And the negative
samples which are now
called key in this architecture.
So the training only impacts
encoder and over time
the Q encoder, using a momentum
m, it updates the key encoder,
the momentum encoder.
So this is a framework
that has actually
been very successful in
terms of implementation,
and follow up versions of it.
There is a lot of
interesting results,
but then what they've
done was basically
tried hybrid versions of using
some non-linear projection heads
and data augmentation
from SimCLR
and using this mini batch style,
the decoupling of the mini batch
and negative samples
from MoCo, and they've
shown that actually if you do
this together, MoCo version 2,
it improves the
performance by a lot.
So I will stop here, but
there was some notions
of CPC, the Contrastive
Predictive Coding,
as another example, that you
can look at in the slides.
And then a better version of
MoCo, MoCo version 3 and DINO
is also one of the widely
used frameworks which actually
has a similar type of
architecture as MoCo,
but it's not
necessarily contrastive
learning because now we have
students and teacher networks.
So I'll leave that for
a separate discussion,
and if you're interested,
we can discuss maybe
in the future slides,
in future lectures.
But anyways, this is also one
of the widely used frameworks
for extracting features
from images and also videos
sometimes.