Hi, everyone.
My name is Zain.
I realized I actually
didn't introduce myself
on the first lecture I gave,
which was lecture three,
but I'm one of the
co-instructors for the course.
My name is Zain Durante.
I'm co-advised by
Ehsan and Fei-Fei.
I'm a fourth year PhD student
at Stanford and in this lecture
today, lecture six,
we'll be talking
about training convolutional
neural networks
and also CNN architectures.
So I would say this
lecture is really broken up
into two different components.
The first one is
just telling you
how to piece together all of
the different building blocks
that we've learned like
convolutional layers,
linear layers or
fully connected layers
together to create
a CNN architecture.
We'll go through some
examples and then
also we'll talk about
how you actually
train these and all the
steps involved there.
So as I mentioned
before, we'll have
basically two different topics.
The first one is
how to build CNNs
and by this I mean how
do you actually define
your CNN architecture to
set it up to be trained.
And then the second
set of topics
today is how do you train CNNs?
So starting with the
first set of topics here,
we'll go through the layers in
convolutional neural networks.
And if you recall
from last lecture,
we learned about the key
layer in these models,
which is the convolution layer.
And the way that these layers
work is they have these filters.
You have a predefined
number of filters per one
of these convolution
layers, in this case six.
They match the depth of
your input data here.
So in this case, we have
a 32 by 32 RGB image
so we three depth channels.
Each of these filters
slides across the image
and calculates a
score at each point.
At that location
in the image, you
take the dot product of
the values in the filter
with the values in the image.
So you multiply all these values
together, you sum them together
and then you add a bias term.
And this is how you calculate
each value in your output
activation map on the right.
So you have these
sliding windows
that go across the image.
They calculate a
score at each position
and that's how you get
these activation maps.
And you have one
per each filter.
Normally, we'll
do a sort of ReLU
or a non-linearity activation
function at the end here.
So this is from last lecture.
I won't spend too
much time on it.
The question is,
for images the depth
is equal to the number
of channels RGB,
but here the depth is
6 for the output here.
So if we had a second
convolution layer afterwards
they would need
to be filters that
go across all six of
these activation maps
so the next layer
would be a depth of 6.
OK, and then the second
layer we talked about,
which is much simpler than
the convolution layer,
is this idea of a pooling layer.
So here it's still
this filter that we're
sliding across the image, 2
by 2 filter with stride 2.
So we're skipping over.
We're not doing every
single location.
And here is a max pooling.
So we're just taking the
max of each of these areas
and that's the
value we get here.
Or you could do an
average pooling.
These are both commonly
used, I would say.
And depending on
the architecture,
you would probably
just, if you're
creating new architecture,
you would try both of them
and see what
performs better here.
But the basic idea
is to consolidate
among the height and width
dimensions for your image.
OK, so we've basically
gone over at this point
in the course all the
top row here, which
is convolution layers,
pooling layers and also
the fully connected layers.
These are the first
layers that we
talked about in the
neural networks lecture
where it's basically one
matrix multiply followed
by an activation function.
And for the rest
of this lecture,
I'll talk about the
remaining layers
that you see in CNNs, at least
the commonly used ones, which
include normalization layers,
which I'll go into those,
and then also dropout,
which is a regularization
technique that's used
actually in the model
architecture itself.
And then finally, we'll revisit
the activation functions
and I'll tell you about here
are the most commonly used
ones both historically and in
the modern era of deep learning.
So starting out with
normalization layers,
the basic idea
here is we're going
to be calculating statistics
like the mean and standard
deviation for our input
data and then using
those to normalize the data.
And then we'll
basically learn what
is the optimal
distribution for the model
to learn at that point.
So very concretely
we learn parameters
that will scale
and shift our input
data by a learned mean and a
learned standard deviation.
So how all of these
normalization layers work is
there's two steps.
The first is to normalize
the data coming in
to be a unit Gaussian, so mean
0, our standard deviation 1.
And then we will
scale and shift it.
So multiply by some value
to increase or decrease
the standard deviation
and then shift
it to change where the mean is.
And all normalization
layers do this technique,
but the way that
they differ is how
they calculate the statistics.
So how are you calculating the
mean and standard deviation
and which values
are you applying
these calculated statistics to,
but all normalization layers are
doing this high level process.
So I'll talk about
layer norm, which
is the most commonly used
normalization layer I would
say today in deep learning.
And it's really commonly used
in transformers specifically.
And so you can imagine you
have some data coming in,
x, which is a batch size of n.
So we have n samples
coming into our model.
And each of these are
vectors of dimension D.
So what LayerNorm
does is we calculate
a mean and standard deviation
for each of our samples
separately.
So we're calculating
what is the mean
along the depth or
the dimension D here
and what is the
standard deviation.
Then we learn parameters.
And so these are
learnable parameters
learned via gradient
descent in our model
to then apply to each sample.
So after we calculate
our statistics
in this way, treating
each sample separately
to calculate the mean
and standard deviation,
we then apply these learned
scale and shift or parameters
here.
So we subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation
within our input
data to normalize it
and then we apply the scale
here with multiplication
and the shift.
So this is the idea
behind LayerNorm.
And at a high level idea all of
these different normalization
layers are all computing
very similar things,
but the main difference
is how are they
computing the mean and
standard deviation.
So this is a really
nice visualization
from a paper called Group
Normalization that introduces
a new way to normalize.
Its I would say not so
commonly used these days,
but this is actually
a really great way
to gain intuition about how
these different normalization
layers are different.
So for LayerNorm I described
the really simple case
where we just have vectors
that were normalizing,
but in the case for
convolutional neural networks,
we have a channel
dimension or the depth
and the height and the width
or the spatial dimensions
of the image.
So what LayerNorm does
is for each sample,
we're still processing
it separately
and we're calculating
the mean across all
of the channels, all of the
heights and all the widths.
So if we look back
into this diagram here,
you would basically
be calculating
one mean and one
standard deviation
over all of these values.
So for each of our
input data points
we're calculating one mean
and one standard deviation
across all of the channels,
all of the height and width
dimensions.
So this is what
LayerNorm is doing.
But you could imagine feasibly
that you could calculate
these statistics differently.
BatchNorm, you're
taking each channel
so each channel is being
calculated as one mean and one
standard deviation.
And you're applying it
just to that channel
and so you're averaging across
all the data in your batch.
InstanceNorm is even more
granular and then a GroupNorm.
So I just want to point
out all these layers
are kind of trying to do
the same thing where you're
basically normalizing
your data and then
having these learnable scaling
and shifting parameters,
but the way they do it is
different because they're
calculating the statistics using
different subsets of your input
data.
Yeah, so the question
is for LayerNorm,
are we calculating one mean
and one standard deviation
for each image or input data?
Yes, they're all
calculated separately,
but for BatchNorm
it would not be
the case in this example here.
Yeah.
For BatchNorm it's actually
within the mini batch for when
you're doing gradient descent.
You have a small batch of
data you're looking at.
You feed it into your model.
You're calculating
the per channel
mean and standard
deviation based on all
of the data in your batch.
Yeah, I think this is a good--
if you can understand this
diagram, I think you understand
what all the different
normalization layers are doing,
so it might be worthwhile after
lecture if you still
don't fully understand it,
just to go through and make
sure you understand what--
and shaded in blue,
these are the values
we're both calculating our
statistics over and then
applying the mean and
standard deviations to.
Yeah, one final question
and then we'll go on.
For channel, same
has the layers?
So channel here
is the depth here.
So the number of values you
have at each spatial location.
OK, cool.
So we talked about
normalization layers.
The key idea is you're
calculating the statistics,
applying them to your input
data and then learning
a scale and shift parameter
that you then apply.
So the next type of layer we'll
talk about is called dropout.
And this is a regularization
layer in CNN's.
And this is the final
layer that you'll
need to learn in
order to-- basically,
we can start going through
all these different CNN
architectures that people
have created over the years.
So with dropout,
the basic idea is
to add randomization
during the training process
that we then take
away at test time.
And the goal is to make
it harder for the model
to learn the training data, but
then it will generalize better.
So this is a form
of regularization.
The way we do it concretely
is that in each forward pass
of our layer, we'll
actually randomly zero out
some of the outputs or
activations from that layer.
And the main parameter you
have for this dropout layer,
which is just a
fixed hyperparameter,
is the probability of
dropping out the values.
And 0.5 is probably
the most common or 0.25
is also commonly used here.
So you're just dropping out a
fixed percentage of the values
here.
And so going forward to the
next layer these would be 0.
And so you don't really need
to calculate the values here.
So I mean, basically all the
outputs here are 0 at this point
so there's some tricks you can
do with masking so you don't
even need to calculate
the values because 0
times any value will be 0.
So I think in general you
might ask, why does this work?
And I would say this is more of
an empirical thing than a well
studied from a
theoretical standpoint,
but there are
actually some ways you
can view what dropout is
doing to gain intuition
of why this might be useful.
So it basically forces
your network to--
you can imagine it forces it to
have redundant representations.
So if we have a list of features
that we're learning at a given
layer, say the layer right
before the output of our model,
and we have a CNN that is
basically extracting each
of these features so it
can detect if there's
ears in the image or if
there's a tail, if it's furry,
it has claws and
you want your model
to output the probability
of a cat score.
So one of the things
that's useful about this
is because some of these
values might randomly
be dropped out during training.
Your model can't over
rely on certain features
being present in
some of the classes
and actually needs to
learn a more broad set
of correspondences between
your features and your output
classes.
So the model can't just
hard focus on, OK, well,
if it has an ear and is
furry, it just so happens
that these are always cats
or something like this
or if it has claws
and it has an ear,
it'll almost always be
a cat on your data set.
So it'll actually
help you generalize
better to new features, despite
the fact that in your data
set there might actually be
really strong correlations
between the codependency of
certain features and your output
class.
By having dropout,
you're essentially
making it so the
model can't rely
on these during
the training phase
because it won't always see
the pairs of features together.
So this is an example for cat.
And the question is if we had
something like tree instead
how would you determine
which features to drop out?
So the dropping out part is
actually completely random
so we're not making
any choices about this.
It's just in this case 50% of
your features at any given step
will be dropped
out and set to 0.
So yeah, you don't
have to make choices
about it, which is kind of nice,
but it is completely random.
How would the model
know if you're only
seeing a subset of the features
like tail and claw here?
The point is you will actually
do worse on the training data
because you're only seeing
a subset of the features.
So it does make the
model worse by not having
all the information,
but then it does better
at test time, this idea.
So worst training
time and better
and test time
because at test time
you're basically no longer
having this drop out.
So the final component
here, which maybe I
should have explained first
before fielding questions,
is the idea at test time
you're no longer dropping out
any of the values.
So this is randomness that we're
adding during the training phase
only.
Then at test time
we're never masking
any of the output activations
and we're removing this dropout
idea altogether.
Now one thing we need to note is
that because if we were dropping
out 50% of the activations
during training time,
at test time, you're
basically having
50% more values that are being
input to each of your layers.
And so this can cause issues
if you don't scale it.
So what you need to do is
multiply by the probability
of dropout so that the
magnitude of the values coming
into each layer is preserved
during training and test time.
Otherwise, if you're
dropping 50% of the values
and then at test time, you
just include all of them,
you'll get really weird
behavior because you'll
be seeing much larger magnitude
of inputs than before.
Yeah, so what about
for backward prop?
So for back prop when you
have these zeroed values,
yeah, it's like you don't
need to traverse that path
of your directed graph anymore.
It's very similar to ReLU.
If you have a zeroed
value at that point
the gradient becomes 0.
So anything further back in
your computational graph,
there's no gradients
calculated at that point.
If you're dropping out
certain values or activations,
the weights associated with
those specific activations
will not be updated
during gradient descent
if you're dropping them out.
So the question is--
maybe I'll reframe it.
What are we doing at test time?
So at test time, we are using
all of the output activations.
We're not dropping
them out anymore,
but we need to scale by the
probability of drop out.
So we multiply each of
our output activations
by this p value because now
we're using all of them.
So otherwise you
can imagine you have
each node is seeing a
significantly higher number
of inputs than it did during
training at test time.
So you need to multiply
by this p value
to maintain the same magnitude
of your inputs coming in.
And the variance
stays the same in all
these different properties.
It works very nicely
if you do it like this.
So the question is, can you just
add noise to the image instead?
The answer is yes
and we'll go over how
to do that in future slides.
Yes, that's a great idea
to add noise to your image
OK, some specific code here.
I won't go over this because
we already mentioned this,
but you're dropping a p
percentage of your activations
here and then you multiply
here at test time.
The next topic I'll talk
about is activation functions.
So you all have basically
learned all of the key layers
now in CNNs.
And now we're going to be
talking about these activation
functions.
If you remember, the whole point
of these activation functions
is to introduce
nonlinearities to our model.
So right now with these
convolution operators,
the kernel sliding
across the image
and the fully connected
layers without activations,
they're all just
linear operations
because they're
multiplications and additions.
And the whole point of
the activation function
is to add non-linearity.
So historically, sigmoid was a
really commonly used activation
function, but there's actually
a key problem with sigmoid
that is the reason why
it's no longer used today.
And so sigmoid, if you
graph it, looks like this.
You can see the equation in the
top right of the slide here.
And the main issue is that
empirically what happened
was after many
layers of sigmoids,
you would get smaller
and smaller gradients
as you're computing backprop.
So starting from the
end, the gradients
are fairly large in magnitude.
And as you undergo multiple
layers of backpropagation,
go to the initial early
layers of your model,
you would get smaller
and smaller gradients
as you do this process.
So I'll actually open this
question up to the class.
This isn't a phenomenon we
see that occurs with sigmoid.
And so in what
regions in our graph
does sigmoid have a
really small gradient?
Yeah, so very negative and very
positive values is correct.
And this is actually
a huge issue.
I mean, you can
visually see here
in the graph the
gradient is very flat.
You're taking the
derivative here.
It's very small.
And so basically for
almost all of our input
space from negative infinity
to positive infinity
you have very small gradients.
And it's only this narrow
range in the middle
where you have something
that's non-zero
so it basically
approaches 0 very quickly
on both ends of the extremes.
And so this means that if the
values coming into sigmoid
are very large or
very small, then
your gradient will
be very small.
So this is one of
the main reasons
why ReLU became super
popular because now
in the positive region we don't
have any of this behavior.
It's just derivative of 1 here,
but in practice, you still
have this flat portion
here on the left
where your gradient is 0.
So now we basically have
half of our input domain.
Here we get a gradient
of 1 and the other half
is 0, which is better
than almost all
of it being 0 or very close
to 0 except for a small region
in the middle.
So in practice
these work better.
Also, it's much
cheaper to just compute
a max operation between 0
and your input value then
the sigmoid function.
So for those two reasons,
ReLU became super popular.
But you still have this issue
where for any negative input
you get a 0 gradient and
so more recently there's
been popular activation
functions that avoid this
by basically having a non-flat
section of the activation
function in the nearby
neighborhood to near 0.
So this is GELU, And
there's also SELU,
which I'll show in a slide, but
I won't go over the formula.
They look very similar.
The basic idea is to smoothen
out this non-smooth jump here
in the derivative from
0 to 1 at 0.0 for ReLU.
So this is a very sharp and
non-smooth function with ReLU,
but the nice part about
GELU is we actually
have non-zero gradients here.
And in the limit as x approaches
infinity or negative infinity,
it does converge
to ReLU as well,
but you get more smooth
behavior in the middle here.
And specifically
what GELU calculates
is this Gaussian
error linear unit.
So this is the cumulative
distribution function
of a Gaussian normal.
So if you imagine the area
under the curve of a Gaussian,
that's what this phi
of x is at any point x.
So if you have a
really negative value
here you'll have a
value close to 0,
which is why it
converges to ReLU 0 here.
And at a very high
positive value
it gets very close to 1,
the area under the curve
so it converges to x here.
So this is GELU.
It has these nice properties
and it converges to ReLU
at the extremes too.
And this is the main activation
function used in transformers
today.
If you look at all of them
and you squint, a lot of these
look the same.
The basic idea is
something relatively flat.
And then in the limit, it
approaches f of x equals x
and it becomes a linear line.
So SELU is actually
x times sigmoid
of x, which also
has this property
of for very negative value,
you have something close to 0
and for very positive
value it's close to 1.
So it's actually similar to
the cumulative distribution
function for the unit
Gaussian that is phi here.
So that's why the
shapes are actually
really similar looking too.
So you might ask where are
these activations used in CNNs
and the general
answer is that they're
placed after linear operators.
So almost any time we have a
feedforward or a linear layer
or a fully connected
layer, these
are all words for
the same layer,
so matrix multiply followed
by a activation function.
Or if we have a convolutional
layer, pretty much after these
is where we place the--
so after the
convolutional layer,
after these linear layers, we'll
put the activation function.
OK, so you've learned
everything now
about all the
components of CNNs.
And I'll now go
through some examples
of how we put them
together and how people
have created state of the art
convolutional neural network
architectures.
I think this is a really
neat slide because it
plots two different values.
So on one hand, we
have the error rate,
which is these blue bars.
And this is over time so these
are different models people have
trained on ImageNet.
And then you have
these orange triangles
which represent the number
of layers that models have.
And you can see
at the same point
that we have a significant
drop in error where we actually
surpass human performance
for the first time,
we see a huge increase
in the number of layers.
So we'll go over
in class today how
they were able to
achieve this, and what
were the design challenges and
goals for how they did this.
Historically, AlexNet
was the first CNN
based paper that worked
really well on ImageNet.
And they were able to
train it by using GPUs.
We talked about this
earlier in lecture,
so I won't spend too much
details around AlexNet from
a historical lens, but I do
want to compare it to another
architecture called VGG,
which was a really standard
and commonly used
architecture in the 2010s.
And I think I can plot the
two CNN architectures together
side by side here.
So in general in AI, we like
to plot our model architectures
using block diagrams,
where each block represents
a different layer
or a group of layers
that are stacked together.
And it also helps
you gain intuition
about what are the
general differences just
at an initial glance.
So these orange blocks, which
are the common ones here,
are 3 by 3 convolution layers.
So these are
convolution layers that
have filters that are sliding
across that are size 3 by 3.
Their stride is 1
so they're visiting
every location in the image,
not skipping over anything.
And they add padding
of 1 around the outside
so that we're not shrinking as
we do these convolution layers.
And so they also add these max
pooling layers throughout here
too.
And you'll notice that for all
of these after a pooling layer
they'll start doing two sets
of fully connected layers
of dimension 4,096 followed
by a dimension of 1,000.
And the reason we have 1,000 at
the end is because ImageNet was
1,000 different
image categories.
So we need to have scores
for each of these categories.
So the final layer is
always equal to the number
of classes you have for an
image classification problem.
And so you can see it actually
looks extremely similar.
It's just like a scaled
up version of AlexNet
with more layers here.
And also they're now doing some
three groups of convolutions
at a time, followed by
pooling rather than two layers
in a pooling or even one.
So it's actually
pretty remarkable
that there's only basically
three different types of layers
in these models, but they
perform extremely well
compared to anything people
had tried before at this point.
So these are, I would
say, the simplest models
we're going to
discuss today, but you
might ask why are they
doing 3 by 3 convolutions.
How do they pick this value?
And there is actually
some intuition
behind how they chose 3
by 3 and specifically they
have groups of three
or even four of these.
So I'll ask you all a question.
What is the effective
receptive field?
So we looked at receptive
field last time,
but it's basically the idea of
the parts of your input image
that a particular value in your
activation map has seen before.
So what values have been used
to compute the final activation
map after many
layers of your model?
So you have three
of these layers that
are all 3 by 3 convolutions
with the sliding filter
with stride of 1.
What is the effective
receptive field
of each value in our
activation map A3 here?
So this is after
the third layer.
So I'm showing one
of the layers here.
You can see for each value in A3
it's computed by looking at a 3
by 3 grid of values in A2.
And then conceivably for
each one in A2 it's a 3
by 3 grid in A1.
And for each of those it's
a 3 by 3 grid in our input.
So I'll let you all think
about this for a little bit.
Maybe it will help to
see the next layer here.
So it is actually really
helpful to visualize this.
So at A1 each of
the corners here,
we're calculating from
a new 3 by 3 grid here.
So from our input, how large
is this overall square?
7 by 7.
Yeah, exactly.
So this first one is 3 by 3.
This next one is 5 by 5 And?
Then the next one is 7 by 7.
And we can visualize
it here pretty easily.
So the nice thing about the 3
by 3 convolution with stride one
is that you're basically
always adding 2
to your receptive
field at each layer
because each point here,
you're looking to the left
and to the right and
above and below it.
So after you have
many blocks of those,
you're just adding
two each time.
So we basically just
showed that a stack
of three of these 3 by 3
convolution and stride 1 layers
has the same effective
field as one 7 by 7 layer.
Yeah, so the question
is how much of this
is justification after the
fact versus how much of this
is intuition that they then use
to, say, design the experiments?
I think it actually probably
depends on the architecture.
So for some of them it's
more intuition focused.
And actually the one we're going
to cover next I think really
was--
the whole research direction was
spawned by an empirical finding
that there was a thought
experiment about.
So that's ResNets and
I think for there,
there's actually a
pretty good intuition
that led the whole investigation
into what will work well.
But then for this one, I mean,
I can't speak for the authors
whether it's justification
after the fact
or based on empirical
findings or if it
was involved in
the design choices
because I haven't seen them
speak publicly about that yet.
But for ResNets, I do know
it was the hypothesis that
led to the creation, but this is
actually a really nice property.
So three of these 3 by 3s have
the same effective receptive
field as one 7 by 7 layer.
And it actually has
fewer parameters too.
So if you imagine our channel
dimension is staying the same,
you have these 3 by 3
grids where you have
your input number of channels.
So 3 times 3 times C would
be the number of values
in each of these filters.
And if we have C of these
filters it's 3 times 3 times
C times C or 3
squared C squared.
And we have three layers total.
So if we look at it
through this lens,
it's actually fewer parameters.
And we're having a more
complex and more nonlinear
model that we're building here.
So fewer parameters and it can
model more complex relationships
among your input data.
So this is maybe why
stacking these 3 by 3 layers
together could be better than
having just a larger filter
that you're sliding across.
So fewer parameters
and then also
you can model more
complex relationships.
OK, I'll now talk
about ResNets, which
I guess I'll very much
bring up the thought
experiment that someone
just asked a question about.
So there was actually
an empirical finding
that spawned a lot
of the conversation
and thought around
designing ResNets.
And the idea was actually shown
that if you keep stacking deeper
layers on a plain CNN
network, something like this
and you just keep
adding layers to it,
you build it larger and
larger, what happens?
So what we found
and what they found
is that the 20 layer model
will actually have a lower test
error than a 56 layer model.
And you might think that this
is because of overfitting,
but it's actually not because if
we look at the training error,
the training error of this
20 layer model is also lower.
So it has a lower training and
a lower test error basically
means that the model is
doing better on all accounts.
So why is this 56 layer
model performing worse
than a 20 layer model?
It might be confusing.
And we know as I
mentioned before, it's not
caused by overfitting.
So these deeper models have
more representational power,
and theoretically they
should be able to represent
any model that a more
shallow network can model.
So the set of possible
mappings between your inputs
and different values
for your larger networks
is a superset for
your smaller networks
because theoretically you could
imagine that you basically
are just setting
some of these layers
to be the identity
function where
the layer is doing nothing.
And then if you set half
your layers to do nothing,
you have exactly the
same representation power
as a model one half the size.
So the idea is not
that these models
are worse in terms of the
representational power,
but they're actually
harder to optimize
because the set of possible
models for your deeper networks
is larger and it contains
all of the possible models
that your more shallow
networks could learn.
So I hinted at it before,
but how specifically could
the deeper model learn
to be at least as
good as a shallow model?
It's by setting.
So if we have a two layer model
versus a one layer, so one layer
here and two layer on the right,
if we set one of the layers
to just essentially be an
identity matrix or this
is just an identity
function, The?
Model should be at least as
good as the shallow model.
It should be at least as
So how do we actually build
this intuition into our models?
We want them to be
able to be just as
good as a shallower
model if they
want to be during optimization.
So the way that we
do this is actually
by fitting what's called
a residual mapping instead
of directly trying to fit a
desired underlying mapping.
And what this looks like is
we basically take the value x
and we copy it over past
our convolution layers
so that the value at
this point is already
receiving x, our original input,
as well as the output of our two
convolution stacks.
So basically at
this point this F
of x, which is called
the residual map here,
it could just learn zero values
for all the conv filters.
And the output would be 0 here.
And then we would just add x
along here and we would get x.
So it allows a very
simple way for the model
to bypass these layers if it
doesn't need to learn anything
for the layers.
And what this means is you
can really easily now learn
basically this identity function
that we talked about earlier
by just learning zero filters.
So your filters all are
filled with zero values,
for example or in this
case more practically
what happens is they
just need to learn
very small values because
instead of learning
this entire mapping from
x to h of x, they just
need to learn this
difference, which is F of x.
So you're now just
learning this sort
of difference between
your desired output
here and the copied over block.
This is called a residual
block or residual connection
when you copy over values
from an earlier layer
into a later layer in
your model and then
you just add it to the
values at that point.
So I talked a bit
about the intuition,
which was this observed
phenomenon that these larger
networks were achieving worse
training and worse test error
because they were
harder to optimize.
So the intuition was we need to
build a model that can really
easily model the
shallower networks so it
can be at least as good
as a shallower model.
The way they did this was by
adding a residual connection so
that you can just copy
over the values easily,
build that into the
architecture itself,
rather than trying to
learn some identity mapping
among the convolutional layers.
And empirically, this showed
to work extremely well too.
Yeah, so what is the
residual block carry?
So we have our input x.
We pass it through two
different convolutional layers
and we get our output F of x.
x is just copied over here.
So this is exactly the
same as x and we add it
to the output of these two
blocks which is F of x.
Yeah, x is the output of
one of the previous layers
or if it's the very first
layer of the model it
would be the image.
Yeah, so the question
is if maybe you just
don't have enough data and
if you added enough data,
then maybe you could train a
model without these blocks.
I think these blocks actually
do extremely help you
with learning from more data.
I think the issue, it was
really an optimization problem.
So transformers
used residual blocks
for exactly the same
reason because--
and I think it
actually helps you
model these more complex
models and it actually
enables you to use more data.
So I think it's very good.
Residual blocks help
you use more data
more efficiently because you're
able to model a greater number--
you're able to more easily model
a greater number of functions.
Yeah, so the question
is that maybe if we just
trained for longer, the
performance would eventually
converge to the value
of the smaller network.
And maybe it's just harder
to optimize because it takes
longer to train a larger model.
And I think the answer
is no, that they were not
converging to the performance
of the smaller model,
regardless of how
long you trained it.
And the reason is
because it's being stuck
in essentially local minimum.
And when you add these
residual connections,
you're avoiding these.
This is the actual explanation
why this is the case is still,
I would say, being a more
active area of research.
It's really hard to
understand exactly what causes
these models to avoid
a global or, sorry,
to avoid local minimum and
not get an optimal solution
or what causes them to not
train and find better solutions.
And oftentimes this is
really an empirical finding,
but there's some
intuition behind it.
And in this case,
the intuition was
that we want to enable our
models to do at least as
well as the shallower models,
which we know were performing
better at the time.
So it's not that you could
just train it for longer
and it would do better.
It was actually a
limitation it was just
completely unable to achieve as
good as the shallower models.
OK, so here's the overall
ResNet architecture.
We have these stacks
of residual blocks now.
So that's what these two
blocks here together mean.
It's a residual block.
So we have a 3 by 3 convolution
with a ReLU followed
by another 3 by 3 convolution.
And we're copying over
this x value here.
We're adding it to
the outputs here
and then we're having
a ReLU afterwards.
So each of these pairs of
blocks is one of these residual.
And that's why you see this
line skipping over here
because the value is
getting added forward.
The cool thing
about ResNets also
is that they basically had a
lot of these different depths
that they created.
So they created a
whole family of models,
some smaller and some larger.
And they showed that as they
increased the number of layers,
their performance
was increasing,
albeit the difference
in performance
as you got to the larger and
larger models became smaller.
So it was reaching a point
of, given the data set,
they weren't able to scale any
significant amount by adding
more layers further
than that, but they
saw significant improvements
in performance among especially
the earlier models.
And then 101 to 152 is
where the performance,
it wasn't really changing.
It was marginally better,
but performance changes maybe
only 1% at that point.
Yeah, how did they
get the number of 152?
I actually don't know how
they got the number of 152.
I think they wanted to
try different values here.
And you can see that--
I mean, they're not
exactly doubling,
but there's a significant
increase in each time.
I don't know how
they picked 152.
That's a good question.
Maybe they showed it somehow
worked better than other.
I actually don't though.
So generally when you're trying
multiple different number
of layers for your
model, given that
say these are the number
of layers you want to try,
what you'll do is you'll first
train the smallest model,
see performance and
then add more layers,
see if your performance
increases and go on so forth.
So that's probably why
they stopped at 152
is because performance wasn't
increased as much anymore.
And also there's GPU
memory limitations
so as you get larger
and larger models,
it becomes harder to train
from a hardware perspective
because you need to fit more
parameters into your GPU memory.
So there is a limit for, given
your compute setup, how large
of a model you can train.
I think you need to train
these models separately though,
so you have one model
run for 18 layers and one
for 34, et cetera.
So the question is how to think
of intuition of CNN blocks,
given we're using these
residual connections because you
can still think of it as
higher levels of abstraction.
And this is shown to
be true in the layers.
So instead of learning--
within the block itself, instead
of just learning the higher
level features, you're
learning the delta
from the original image to
get the higher level features.
That's what you're
learning in the block.
So you're learning the
delta, but you're still
achieving these higher level
representations at each step.
So that part is the same,
but the actual functional way
of doing it is you learn
this F of x that you
add your previous input to.
So it's like you're
learning the delta.
The question is,
if you do addition,
does that require you to
have the same tensor size?
The answer is yes.
And it's part of the
reason why it's really
the nice property
that all of these ones
have this 3 by 3 convolution
with stride 1 and 1 padding
so that you maintain the same
size at every layer going
forward.
So after you had, say,
a pooling layer, I mean,
you could maybe
come up with a way
to do it where you
unspool the values,
but after pooling
layer, for example,
you couldn't do a
naive addition anymore
because the size of your
tensors are different.
So these are done before a
pool, at least the regular one.
I mean, you could
get around it by just
having each value be spread
out into multiple values,
for example.
OK, so these are basically the
main takeaways for ResNets.
One other neat trick
they do is they basically
periodically after a certain
number of these blocks,
they'll double the
number of filters
and downsample the
spatial dimension.
So basically you
can imagine if you
start with a really flat
image, as the activations get
pushed through the network,
it becomes smaller spatially,
but then the depth is larger.
So this is how to think of it.
And then at the
very end, it just
becomes a vector that you
then use for classification.
So that's how you should
be visualizing what's
happening to the values
in the network itself
and the shape of them.
And then one other
sort of thing that's
somewhat unique to ResNets,
other architectures do this too,
but before all these layers
with the residual blocks,
they have this relatively
larger convolutional layer.
And here is just
empirically shown
that it did better if
they added this here.
So this one is purely
empirical finding.
OK, I think basically
to highlight,
it did extremely well,
these larger models.
It was the first time they were
able to train 100 plus layer
models successfully so
it was a really big deal.
And basically ResNets were used
in a huge variety of computer
vision tasks afterwards.
Almost every task
in computer vision
was using a ResNet at
the time because they
performed so well because of
these residual connections.
So we talked about some CNN
architectures, the main one
being ResNet and then
also VGG historically.
So we talked about why the
smaller filter size is useful
and having many layers
of these is useful.
So the final thing I'll
talk about in terms
of how we actually
construct the CNNs
and prime them to be ready for
training is how do you actually
initialize the weight values
of the individual layers?
So depending on what
values you choose,
you could either put values
that are too small or too large,
which would cause significant
issues for your model
during training.
So here it's basically a six
layer network where we have
4,096 dimensional features.
And this is just six layers
of fully connected model
and we initialize them.
Here this is getting
a unit Gaussian random
and then we
multiplying it by 0.01
to get very small
values close to 0
and we have ReLU
at each layer too.
So if you plot the forward
pass of this model,
you would actually see
that at the beginning
you get a relatively
high-- because there's ReLU
so all the means are
going to be positive,
but you'll have a mean
and standard deviation
that is relatively high.
But as each layer
progresses, because we
had a really small
weight initialization,
it becomes smaller and smaller
mean and standard deviation.
And really ideally we
would want basically
all of these to be the
same for each layer
because it makes our
optimization problem much
nicer to solve.
So if we say use
0.05 instead of 0.01,
can anyone imagine what might
be the issue here if we set it
to too large of a value?
So when it's too small,
it goes to 0, basically.
What happens if it's too large?
Yeah, basically the activations
get larger and larger
at each layer.
So if you plot it here,
you can see that by the end
there's some massive mean
and standard deviation.
And if you're training
152 layer ResNet and you
can imagine that this becomes
quite an issue very quickly.
So how do you actually do this?
So in this case maybe
the optimal value I think
is 0.022 or something, but how
would you actually know that
and how would you do this more
generally across any layer?
There are a few different ways
you can initialize weights.
And I'll go over the
most commonly used one
today in class, but no,
there are other ones.
And generally what
they're a function of
is the dimension of
your values here.
So you'll have a different value
for a 4,096 dimension fully
connected layer versus a 2048.
And the specific
formula we'll go through
is called Kaiming
Initialization.
It's actually the same
person who created ResNets.
So Kaiming, he was very famous.
I mean, he still is a very
famous computer vision
researcher.
I think he's one of the
most widely cited computer
scientists of the last 10
or 15 years, maybe the most.
So he's extremely well known in
the computer vision community.
And he also came
up with this idea
of initializing the values
to the square root of 2
over your input dimension size.
And I won't go over
all the details
for how they derived this
and showed that with a ReLU
activation, this will cause
the standard deviation
and mean to be relatively
constant throughout the layers.
But if you do plot it, you
see this does have the effect
so you can almost think
of this as a magic formula
where if you plug it in
get the desired properties.
And if you want to
know the derivation,
you can actually-- we
link the paper here so
feel free to look into that,
but you can just take our word.
I won't go through
the details here,
but it does this desired effect
where the mean and standard
deviation is unchanging.
And you can also imagine
that for any given setup,
you could also, just
through testing,
try to find what
is the value here.
OK, so these are
how you we discuss
how you initialize
weights, how you
combine these different
layers together
to form a CNN architecture,
which activation functions
people use, and then all the
different layers in CNNs.
So I think already we
covered quite a few topics.
So I think I'll
pause very briefly
to see if there's any
questions about these.
And the second part
of the lecture, it's
actually much less dense
than the first part.
So we'll be mainly
going over a lot
of nice practical tips for when
you're training these models.
So the question is, how do
you do weight initialization
for CNNs?
So you still use the
same initialization,
but your dimension n here
is the size of your kernel.
So if you have a 3 by
3 kernel with channels
say 6 would be 3 times 3 times
6, but it's the same idea.
It's just you calculate
your dimensions differently
depending on the layer,
the type of layer.
You can think of it as the
number of values roughly
in each operation, but it
does depend on the layer.
And some layers use different
weight initializations,
but this is
specifically for CNNs
how this initialization
applies to it.
Yeah, so the question is,
why do your activations
explode if you have too large
of an initialization value?
So you imagine at each layer
of your initialized network
you have a set of randomly
initialized values.
And if they're very large,
then when you do your--
you have a ReLU
activation afterwards.
And that doesn't actually cap
the outputs of your layer.
You can go to
infinity with ReLU.
So if you have too
large of a set of values
that you're essentially
repeating the same operation on
because you're initializing
all the weights
to the same set of random
values, then at each layer,
you'll be multiplying
one set of large values
by a set that's been
initialized to large so
that it becomes larger at
each iteration afterwards.
I mean, you could think of it as
it's like a recurrence relation
where because they're
all initialized randomly
at the start where it's
being multiplied by a value
and you would want in a
simple recurrence relation,
you'd want it to be one.
But because we have
a vector of values
that are being
multiplied by our matrix,
it depends on the dimension
of the vector, what
your average output would be
and after the ReLU because you
have basically a standard
deviation for what
is your activations.
Then you remove all
the negative ones
and you're left with what are
your outputs at that point
and if you have a
really large values,
you have a really large
standard deviation.
So when you remove
the bottom half of it,
your mean starts moving more
positive and more positive.
Did that make sense to--
I didn't have slides
to show it, but OK.
Mostly, sorry.
Yeah, you can see more
details in the paper.
It's actually not too
bad to read I think.
So the conclusion
of the discussion
here is that normalization would
solve this activation issue
where they're blowing
up, but it still
might be harder to optimize.
Maybe we should
probably do a follow up
post explaining
this in more detail,
but I think it's a really
good question actually, yeah.
It would solve, I think,
this particular issue,
but maybe it's still hard to
optimize this in the discussion.
Yeah, it's a good question.
OK.
Cool.
So I'll talk about
these steps now.
So how do you actually
train your model?
And the nice thing for
data pre-processing
is it's really easy for images.
So if you have your
giant image data set,
the standard way to do it is
you calculate the average red,
the average green, and
the average blue pixel
along with the
standard deviations.
And you take your input
image, you subtract the mean
and you divide by the
standard deviation.
And this is how you do data
normalization for images.
Is actually very
straightforward.
So it does require
you to pre-compute
the means and standard deviation
for each pixel channel.
So sometimes what
people will do is
they'll use means that have
already been calculated.
A very common one is
to use the ImageNet
means and standard
deviations and apply those
to your input images, even if
you're training a model not
on ImageNet.
So it is very data set dependent
is the way to think of this.
And different models will
use different values here
depending on their data set,
but the most commonly used one
is just use the mean
and standard deviation
from ImageNet.
Yeah, so any input image,
you apply this operation
before the model sees it.
So yeah, that one
was really quick.
And then in terms of
data augmentation,
so someone had a suggestion
earlier in the class
why don't we just add
noise to our image.
And that's a great idea.
And we'll talk about the
different ways you can add noise
to your image here.
This helps with regularization
and helps prevent your model
from overfitting.
So we talked about it before,
but this is a common pattern
with regularization,
where during training time
you add some kind of randomness.
And then at testing time you
then average out the randomness.
So sometimes this
is approximate,
but for example, for dropout,
we saw that during training time
we'll randomly drop, say,
50% of the activations.
And then at testing time
we'll use all the activations,
but then we'll need
to scale it down
by this probability
of dropout p.
So this is a really
common pattern.
And it's also used
for data augmentation.
So you can imagine this
being this cylinder here
is like your data set.
You load an image and a label.
So we have a cat label and
we have our original image
from our data set.
Before we actually pass it into
our model, it's extremely common
and basically always in
modern deep learning,
people will always use data
augmentation for training
computer vision models.
But the basic idea is to
apply some transformations
to the image to make it
look different but still
recognizable for
the category class
and then pass that to
your model and you're
computing the loss here.
So one of the nice
benefits of this
is you can effectively increase
the size of your data set
because instead of seeing
each image multiple times,
it will be seeing different
versions of the image
with different
transformations that all still
are the same category label.
So you can basically
get more data
and therefore it increases your
generalization capabilities,
but your training loss will be
higher because you're not just
seeing the same example
over and over again.
So it makes it harder for
the model to just memorize.
So how do we know the weight
initialization is just right?
So we know it's
right in this case,
because the means and
the standard deviations
are relatively constant
throughout the layers
of the network.
And we're not seeing--
in this case, we saw
mode collapse to 0.
In this case, it was
blowing up to infinity as we
increased the number of layers.
So the way you can
ensure it always happens
is by using the formula.
This will always
initialize them well.
So in practice that's
how people do it.
If you were creating
a new layer that
maybe does some different
kind of operation
that no one's done
before, then you probably
would need to try a bunch of
different weight initialization
schemes and see what works best.
But generally for
these linear layers
or the convolutional layers,
you can use this formula here,
which is called the
timing initialization.
OK.
So back to data
augmentation, so what
are the different augmentations
you can do specifically?
So one of them is
horizontal flipping.
This depends on the problem.
So if you want to
have a model that
reads text this would be
a very bad augmentation
to use because the
text is now-- it's
like you're looking
through a mirror
and you can't read it properly.
So this is sometimes useful
for everyday objects.
It's usually pretty good
because most objects
are symmetrical so this property
actually works pretty well.
And then you could also
imagine if you're looking maybe
at images from a
microscope or overhead
that you could also
do a vertical flip
and that would make sense.
But for everyday objects,
vertical flipping actually
doesn't really make sense
because a cat is almost
always seen in this
position, but maybe
if you had a data
set where cats were
in all different
orientations, you
could imagine that flipping or
rotating or all these things
would make sense
for your data set.
Another type of augmentation is
this resizing and cropping idea.
So what ResNets and
many different image
models in deep learning
do is they basically take
a random crop of the
image and then resize
that to be your image size.
They might even take
another crop afterwards.
So the most common
strategy is you
pick the length of
what is basically
the short side of your image.
So if you have a input image
size to your model of 224
by 224 pixels, you would pick
a value larger than this first
and find some crop of your image
that contains this larger scale
L and these are
commonly used values.
You crop the image.
Sorry, you don't crop.
You resize the image
to be that scale.
So instead say this
is a 800 by 600 image,
if we use 256 here we resize
the short side, so 600 to be 256
and then 800 would be
scaled correspondingly.
So we scale it to this L.
We scale the short side to L
and then we crop a
random patch of 224
by 224 pixels from that image.
So you're scaling the
image by first preserving--
you've preserved the
relative resolution,
but you make it smaller
or larger to fit this L
and then you take a
random crop of that.
And this is by far the
most commonly used--
random resized crop is what
it's called in most libraries.
So this is used in most problems
because it works pretty well
and it reserves the relative
resolution of your images.
And then there's
another neat trick
you can do with augmentation
called test time augmentation.
So if you really just want
to get the best performance
possible, you can basically get
a bunch of these different crops
and resizes and run them
all through your model
and then average your
predictions at the end.
And for ResNets,
people will often
try a bunch of different scales,
a bunch of different crop
locations and
maybe even flip it.
And usually you'll start
getting diminishing returns,
but you can get actually
pretty good 1% to 2%
performance boost by using this
sort of test time augmentation.
So if you're in a setting
where it really matters,
you're trying to eke out every
last bit of percentage points,
then this is actually
a really great trick
that you can use for almost
any computer vision problem.
OK, so a final
few augmentations.
One is color jitter, so
here we're specifically
randomizing the
contrast and brightness
and scaling the image
correspondingly.
So maybe images
look more muted or I
say the colors look more
muted or more brighter,
but these are very traditional
image processing techniques.
And usually with all these
different augmentations,
you'll try different
values and see
which ones make your images
still look in distribution
and look normal
to you as a human.
And that's a pretty
good way to judge
what values you should
pick for how much jitter
you should have, how much
brightness, variance, et cetera.
So normally when I'm
starting a problem,
I'll try a bunch of these
different augmentations.
I'll see what is
making the data look
different from
the original data,
but then still recognizable
to me and still very easy
to recognize.
And that's generally a good
set of augmentations to use.
Final one is you
can imagine just
like cropping out
parts of the image
where you just are
basically putting
a black or a gray box over it.
And I think this one's
maybe less commonly used,
but it kind of shows
you how you can
get creative with
the augmentations
depending on your problem.
Say you're in a setting
where things will get covered
like the camera will be occluded
so it won't be able to see
the objects fully, this
could be a really neat trick
you do to make your model
more resilient to stuff
blocking parts of your objects.
So you could almost imagine
for your given setting,
what augmentations make sense.
What ways can you
transform your input data
so that it's still
recognizable to you as a human,
but it makes it harder for the
model to memorize the training
examples?
OK, so the final
set of topics here
are basically
extremely practical.
So when you're,
say, doing a project
or training a model, so say
for your course project,
I think you should basically
do the exact things we're
going to be describing
in the coming slides,
but this also applies
outside the course
to any computer vision domain
you could be practicing in.
So in practice in many
times we don't actually
have so much data.
ImageNet, the original
version had a million images.
Maybe you don't have a million
images for your problem,
which almost none of
us do unless you've
been collecting vast amount
of data with a huge team.
So if you don't have a lot of
data, can you still train CNNs?
And the short answer
is yes, you can,
but you need to be a little
bit smart with how you do it.
So I think in one of the--
I think maybe it
was last lecture,
we showed how the different
filters in your CNN
are extracting different
types of features.
So this goes back
to someone asked
about the hierarchy of features
in convolutional neural
networks.
So at the beginning, it's
more of just edges or patterns
or really small shapes.
And then at the
highest level, you
can imagine if we put
an image into our CNN
and we get this final vector
right before we get our class
scores, and we compare that to
other images in our data set,
you'll actually see
that these values
of the vector of our image
are actually really close.
So you can think of this as the
nearest neighbors thing we did
before, but instead of it being
the pixels of the image where
we're looking at the vector at
the very end of your CNN right
before you have the
classification layer,
so this would be like the
4,096 or the 2048 layer.
And if we look at the difference
here, it's the L2 distance.
You'll find that
for a given image,
if you put it into
your model and you
look at the other
images that are
close to the model
in this vector space
right here after you go
through all the layers
except the last one, that you'll
find the images are extremely
close to each other when the
items are in the same category.
So intuitively, what
this basically means
is that these features here
are actually really good at--
you could build a linear
classifier on top of them
or a K nearest
neighbor classifier
and be able to classify
objects extremely well.
So how could you use
this in practice?
So what you would do
is you would first
train your model on
ImageNet or you would just
grab a model someone else
is trained on ImageNet
or one of these really large
web internet scale data sets.
And you can just freeze
all of these layers
so you don't train any of them.
You keep them exactly the same
as before and you replace this
final layer instead of it being
in the case of ImageNet 1,000
classes, you replace it with
the number of classes you have
in your data set.
And then when you're
training the model,
you only train this layer here.
So if we think about
we talked about how
in the old paradigm
of computer vision
you had feature
extractors, which
was a predefined
set of operations
to get stuff like
color histograms
and other predefined features.
You could almost think of the
frozen model as doing this.
It's a predefined
feature extractor
that we're not
changing in any way,
but we're using it to
calculate features that we then
train a model on top of.
It's actually extremely
similar under that paradigm
because you're not
training it here.
And if you have a
larger data set, what
tends to work best
in practice is
to actually train
the whole model,
but you're initializing
it from these values that
were pre-trained on ImageNet or
some other really large internet
scale data set.
So I think pretty much for
all of the problems I ever
work on, I'm doing this step
three here because I have maybe
a million or 10 million
training examples.
So I'll start it with a model
that was trained on billions
that I don't have
the compute for
and then I'll fine tune
the model on my relatively
smaller data set.
And I'll get better
performance than if I just
tried to train a model myself.
Because the model is
basically seen more data.
It's created a better
feature extractor.
And then when I fine
tune the whole thing,
it can still be specific
enough to my problem.
You're basically
taking-- say let's
use a very concrete
case where we're
training a model on ImageNet.
We're taking this model and
we're replacing the final layer
so that it's no longer
outputting 1,000 classes.
It's outputting the number
of classes in your data set.
And we're initializing this
randomly using the Kaiming
Initialization we
talked about before,
but the rest of these layers
are maintaining their values
that they had before.
So we're not
changing these values
and during gradient
descent we're
never changing these values.
So these values are unchanged.
We basically take our image.
We pass it through our model.
And now it's just like we have
a-- it's almost like you're just
training a linear classifier
where your input are these 4,096
vectors for each image that we
calculate by passing it through
the whole model.
Then we have our
vector of 4,096.
And we're just mapping that
to the number of classes.
And we're only training
this mapping at the end.
Yeah, so the question is, will
you have some bias in your model
because it was
trained on ImageNet?
The answer is definitely.
So the model if you
do this number two,
this way of training, then
it will do best on data sets
that look very
similar to ImageNet.
So these would be pictures of
everyday things like laptops
or maybe a classroom or a
person, things like this where
ImageNet is everyday objects.
But if it was, say, photos of
Mars, it would do a lot worse.
So there's definitely
bias based on the training
data of the pre-trained model.
And you want to
get something that
is in the same type
of distribution
where you're seeing the same
kinds of objects or locations
or things like that.
So the question is, what do you
do when your data set is out
of distribution?
I actually have a slide
here to cover some of that.
So it's a great question.
So if you have a very similar
data set but very little data,
you can use the
linear classifier
strategy we just mentioned.
If you have a similar data
set, quite a lot of data,
you'll get best performance
by fine tuning all the layers.
These are strategies
two and three
on this slide that
I mentioned earlier.
But what about when you have
a very different data set?
So if you have a lot
of data you might just
want to start from scratch or
you might get better performance
if you still initialize.
Here you would test, but
there's no guaranteed way
to know that performance
would be better or worse.
And then, yeah, if you have very
little data or a very different
data set, you
probably want to try
to find a model that's
trained on something close.
There are specific
techniques that researchers
have looked into for
out-of-domain generalization
and this basic idea of
you have one domain,
you train a model on
one domain and you're
trying to learn a new domain,
that's different in some ways.
So this is an active
area of research,
but I wouldn't say there's a
general technique that always
works and it's a bit problem
dependent in that setting,
whereas this is for everything
except the upper right quadrant
here.
It works pretty
well in practice.
So there are actually
techniques for this.
And it's a pretty
active area of research.
And certain models
generalize better.
I think language
models are pretty
good at learning a lot of
different domains, for example.
But yeah, it's definitely
the worst scenario
to be in where you have a
completely different problem
that anyone's ever
worked on before
and you don't have
a lot of data.
It's by far the hardest to
train a model in that setting.
So the question is, do you ever
do anything between training
one final layer and all layers?
Yeah, people have
actually done a lot
of work looking into training
a subset of the layers.
There's also a
technique called LoRA,
which we might go into in
the transformers lecture.
I'm not sure if they'll
make it this year,
but the basic idea
is to fine tune
all the layers in a way
where you're not changing all
the values exactly, but you're
learning basically low rank
differences between
the different layers
where you're fine
tuning the differences
between the original
layers rather than fine
tuning the layers themselves.
So yeah, there's techniques
you could use LoRA.
And it would need
more explanation,
but the basic idea is instead of
fine tuning the actual values,
you're fine tuning these
differences between the value
layers like how a ResNet,
you're learning the difference.
LoRAs are like
that, but you do it
with a very small
number of parameters.
I think the question is,
how do they basically
decide how many layers to pick?
Why did they pick a
large number of layers?
Specifically why are there
two convolution layers
of each size instead of one?
So it's actually really
similar to the example
we showed earlier with VGG where
if you have three of these 3
by 3 convolutions, you're able
to have the same receptive field
as a 7 by 7
convolution, but you're
able to model more non-linear
relationships because you have
these three activation functions
rather than just one activation
on the 7 by 7 filter.
So basically 3 by 3
is more expressive,
but you're still looking
at the same set of values
as long as you have
enough of them.
So a larger set
of smaller filters
is more expressive than a
smaller set of larger filters.
OK, so we'll go on.
Yeah, basically try
to find a large data
set that has similar data.
Get a model that
was trained on that
and then fine tune
it on your own data.
Some good links.
PyTorch image models
has a bunch of models
that are trained on
ImageNet and other data
sets and then also just in the
PyTorch version, a GitHub repo.
You'll find some too.
OK, I'll talk over
very briefly at the end
for hyperparameter selection.
So if you're having
difficulty training your model
and it's not working
right away, I
think the best thing you can do
is to overfit on a small sample.
So this is the default
debugging strategy
in deep learning where you
just have one data point
and you want to see your
training loss basically go to 0.
Your model should be able to
memorize one training example
and if it's not able to do
that have a bug somewhere
in your code or you're not
picking the right kind of model
to model your problem.
So this is a really
good training problem.
And it'll also tell you
what learning rates work
or what ones don't work.
And you'll get a rough idea of
the neighborhood of learning
rates you should explore.
So this is a good way to make
sure your model is correct,
make sure your learning
rate is reasonable
and also to make sure you
don't have any other bugs that
could be impacting your code.
So this is always step one.
If you're having issues
just running some code,
this is how you debug.
The second thing
you would want to do
after you get this is maybe
you try a very coarse grid
of hyperparameters.
So I would first try with
different learning rates
and see how if you trained model
on different learning rates,
what do the training
losses look like.
You want one that has the
most sustained decreasing
in the training loss
over maybe one epoch.
That's a pretty good estimation,
but you can train for longer.
Once you get a good
set of learning rates,
you could then look into
other hyperparameters too.
And specifically,
besides the loss,
you'll also want to look
at the accuracy curves.
So you have your
training accuracy
and your validation accuracy.
If they're still
going up, it means
you want to keep training
pretty reasonable,
but you might have a
scenario where the training
loss is going up, but your
validation loss is going down.
This is overfitting.
So we need to either
increase the regularization
or if we can get more
data, that could also work,
but you need to
do one of the two
in order to improve
your performance further
beyond the peak
right here I guess
would be the best
model you have so far.
If you're seeing very
little of a gap here,
then you can probably train for
longer because generally you
do want to just get to the point
where your validation loss has
been maximized.
So if you could
just keep training,
you could keep training.
So even if there's not
a significant gap here
or anything, if you see
the validation accuracy is
similar to the
training accuracy,
you can probably keep training
until your training accuracy
starts diverging from
your validation accuracy.
And you basically can repeat
this process over and over
again.
One final note is in terms
of for hyperparameter search,
normally people think you have
two hyperparameters or more
that you're searching
over, should you
try every combination
of the hyperparameters
or what is the
best way to do it?
I think in practice, random
search over the hyperparameter
space works a lot better
than a grid search
where you're trying every
set of a predefined set.
And the reason is
mainly because you
can imagine you have one
axis, which is an unimportant
hyperparameter where
depending on the value,
your performance will
be roughly the same
versus an important one.
If you do random values
across all of these,
you'll actually search
the hyperparameter space
of your important
parameter much more
thoroughly, whereas you're
wasting time doing on the grid
search rechecking
multiple values
for an unimportant
hyperparameter.
So in practice,
you should define
the ranges you want to
try and then just randomly
collect hyperparameters with
values from those ranges.
And that's probably
the best way to do it.
And you just keep running
until you get the best model.
OK, that's it.
So we talked about layers in
CNNs activation functions,
CNN architectures, and
weight initialization,
how do you actually predefine
and build these models
and then we talked about how
do you actually train it.
How do you change your data
to be input to the model?
How do you augment it?
Transfer learning is
a really neat trick
for improving performance and
then how do you pick the best
hyperparameters.
So yeah, we covered a
lot in lecture today.
Thank you all so much.
Yeah.