We will be talking today
about image classification,
basically, continuing
our discussion
on the topic of
image classification
from last lecture.
And we'll get a little bit
into some topics that gets us
closer to neural
networks and, ultimately,
convolutional neural
networks and so on.
We will start with
linear classifiers.
Moving to the next slide,
this was the syllabus
that we've talked
about last lecture,
in the previous
lecture, where we
did talk about three major
categories of topics,
deep learning basics,
perceiving and understanding
the visual world,
reconstructing and interacting
with the visual world as
the three major topics,
and some subtopics that we
will be covering in the class.
And at the end, we will
have some discussions
around the human-centered
AI aspects.
And today, the goal is
to cover the first three
items, data-driven approaches,
I will try to tell you
what this means, and linear
classification as well
as the k-nearest
neighbor algorithm.
So like last-- the
previous lecture,
let's start with our core
task of image classification.
Again, it's a core task
in computer vision.
And we actually come
back to this task
quite often
throughout the quarter
because it's a very
good benchmark.
And we have some
examples to tell you
how the algorithms work.
So this is one of the items that
we come back to quite often.
We want to define that image
classification task today
and then introduce two of the
data-driven approaches for image
classification, one of
them, nearest neighbor,
and one of them-- the other
one, linear classifier.
There are some other
approaches which we have
listed in our backup slides.
And you're welcome to look
at them after the class.
But this is what we
will be covering.
So what is image classification?
Given an image and a number
of predefined labels,
predetermined labels, a
set of possible labels
such as in this example, you
see dog, cat, truck, plane,
and so on, the job of the system
is to assign one of those labels
to this image.
So to us, this is actually
a very, very easy task
because our brains,
our cognitive system
is wired to get a holistic
understanding of this image
and assign a label to it.
But when it comes to
coding this and looking
at how a computer can
make sense of this image,
that's completely
a different story.
And we want to see how machines
can make sense of such data.
So images are often defined
by matrices of data,
more broadly, more
generally, tensors of data.
And often, the numbers are--
each of the pixel values
are between 0 and 255,
which is an 8-bit
data structure.
And since this is an image,
a colored image, assuming
that it's with a
resolution of 800
by 600, since it's
an RGB image, it
has three channels of
red, green, and blue, RGB,
and therefore, it's
a tensor of 800
by 600 by 3, as you
can see on this slide.
So as you can
probably guess, this
is the semantic gap between
our perception of this image
and how the machine perceives
and sees the image, right?
And in order to be
able to even understand
how this could be
very challenging,
let's look at some
challenges, some variations
in this type of imaging data.
So let's assume, for example--
as one example, let's assume
that we move the camera.
If the camera is
moved, for example,
panning the camera around,
even if the cat sits completely
and perfectly still, all
of those pixel values,
every single pixel value of 800
by 600 by 3 will be changed.
So all these pixels
will have a new value.
Again, for us humans,
it's the same object.
There is no-- absolutely
no difference.
But from a computer's
perspective,
it's completely
a new data point.
So this is one of
the challenges,
but there are quite
a few others as well.
For example, illumination
is another challenge.
So if you've seen or
if you've taken courses
in graphics or maybe
other vision courses
and/or digital image processing
courses for engineering
applications, you know that the
value of each RGB pixel, the RGB
values, are a function of
the surface material, color,
and their light source.
And that's why same cat, same
object may look differently
in terms of numbers
when it comes
to being pictured in different
illumination conditions.
With that in mind, so whether
the cat is in a dark room
or under the sun,
still, it's the cat.
It's one cat.
But this is creating
challenges for the machine.
Can you maybe name
some other challenges
that may change the
values of the pixels
and create problems for the
machine to recognize objects,
other than illumination
and viewpoint changes
that I mentioned?
So background clutter,
background objects, yes,
which is actually
our next slide.
Yes, background clutter
is another challenge.
Anything else?
Zooming in and out,
yes, so scale basically
of the object in the image.
Yes, what else?
The resolution of
the image that is--
that could be considered as--
that's definitely a challenge.
But often with machine-learning
models or any model
that you want to recognize
action objects and images,
since we normalize
the size of the image,
resolution may not
be that important,
unless there is zooming
effects of the objects.
Occlusion is one of
the major problems.
Again, as humans, it's very
easy to say this is cat.
These are cats.
Even the last one, which is
actually a very challenging,
the one on the right.
You can only see a tail and a
little bit of probably a paw
in the right side.
One could say, yes, that could
be a tiger, or it could be--
I don't know-- a raccoon
with a tiny tale.
But because this is-- because
of the context, because we
know this is inside a
living room on a couch,
most probably, it's a cat.
It's a cat.
So again, for us humans,
it's not that hard.
Beyond that, there are
many other problems.
Deformation.
Cats are very deformable.
So they create challenges for
algorithms to be detected,
recognized.
I mean, not today's algorithms.
Generally, for building
step-by-step algorithms
that can detect objects.
So deformation is one of
the other major challenges.
And beyond that, the
intraclass variation
is one more important challenge.
We know that cats can come
in different sizes, colors,
patterns, or even, they can--
they have different breeds.
And all of those are still cats.
But for the machines,
it's not that
easy to recognize the
intraclass variations.
One other interesting
challenge is the context,
because if you only look at that
part, that image on the right,
or if an algorithm looks at this
without considering the context,
it's very easy to classify this
as a tiger or some other animal.
But because of the
context and because we
know that there is
the effect of shadows
and so on, this could probably
be classified correctly.
But the thing is that the
classifiers that we have today
can do really great job--
good jobs at
classifying the images,
identifying the
objects in images,
thanks to efforts like ImageNet,
and also all of the follow-up
works that created larger
scale benchmarks for training
larger scale models.
And in this class, what we
want to do is to get to a place
that we build models that can
recognize activity-- recognize
objects, and also other
aspects within the image.
For the rest of
this class, we are
going to be working towards
building, step-by-step,
the building blocks that
are needed for building
those large algorithms.
And before doing so, we have to
look at the most basic building
block of classifying an
image, and that is building,
implementing a
function like this.
So if you've taken some
of the computer science
or engineering courses
that often build frameworks
through algorithms, like, for
example, sorting as a computer
algorithm, it's often--
it often comes with
some if-then-else rules
and some for-loops and so on.
So there is a clear
flowchart of tasks and steps,
if-then-else steps that creates
an algorithm for sorting.
But when it comes to
images and understanding
the visual world, that is not
happening, that is a challenge,
there is no way to hard code the
steps for classifying images.
Although there has been
some efforts in this space.
There are papers that they've
tried to come up with algorithms
and steps to recognize objects.
And one of those was
based on edge detectors,
finding the edges in the
image as a first step,
and then after creating
all of these patterns,
look at the important
patterns, for example, corners,
extract some features that
are around the corners,
or counts the number of
specific types of corners,
and based on, from those, try to
map that into the output class.
So while this has been
an interesting effort
and it had some success on
very limited variability type
of images, but this is
very hard to-- first,
it's very hard to scale
these types of algorithms.
Even if it works, it's
very hard to scale
because you have to
create these rules
and everything for
every single object
that you want to recognize.
And second, finding the
logic for each of those
requires a lot of effort
by itself as well.
So because of
these challenges, I
think these types
of algorithms, which
are based on creating logics and
procedures for detecting objects
or classifying images have
not been quite successful.
And machine learning comes
with this data-driven approach.
So with this new paradigm of--
and another paradigm of
looking at this problem
from a data-driven
perspective, we
define a procedure of
a three-step process.
And the first one is
to collect data sets
of images and their labels.
So there are many
different ways of if you
want to recognize a
specific type of object
or specific types
of objects, we can
look for data sets or single
data points over the internet
to create data, many samples
from each of the examples.
We used to be doing
this 10, 20 years ago,
using search engines and image
search engines over the internet
to create these
types of data sets.
Now we have all
of the data sets.
And then the second step
is using machine learning
algorithms to
train a classifier.
Basically, build
a function train
that takes the images
in the training
data and their
associated labels,
and builds a model
that can relate,
associate images
with the labels.
And then the last step
would be evaluating
the classifier on
new images, but which
means implementing
a function called
predict that takes the
model and some test images,
and for those test images that
were not part of the training
images, predicts the labels and
returns those as the output.
So a very simple procedure.
But instead of
building a logic, we
are building a data-driven
approach for it.
As I said, we want to talk
about two popular methods
and classifiers.
One of them is nearest
neighbor classifier.
This is the easiest
form of classification,
and we specifically want
to go over this because we
can learn some of the
concepts around building
these classifiers.
And it's easier to explain
some of the details.
And then we'll move to the
topic of linear classification.
OK to do that, what we do to
build the nearest neighbor
classifier.
As I said, we need to build the
train and predict functions.
The train function
needs to just memorize
all of the data and labels.
So the training
function basically
doesn't do anything other
than keeping everything
in the memory.
And then the
prediction function--
the predict function looks for
the most similar training image.
Basically, it creates a lookup
table of all of the images
and all of their labels.
And during the prediction or
testing time, what it does
is tries to find the closest
one, the most similar image,
and outputs the
label for that image.
Let's look at an example.
So assuming that we have these
five as in our training data,
then--
yes, you see my cursor.
And then this is
the query image,
the input image for prediction.
What we want to do is to see
which of these training data
and training images is the
most similar to this one.
And for that, we need
the distance function.
So this distance
function needs to take
the two images, each pair of
images, each of these images
compared to the query image,
and return a value which
defines the similarity between
these two inputs, these two
images.
There are many different
ways of doing that.
One of the most popular
ones is L1 distance,
which is defined as the sum
over all absolute values
of pixel differences between
the two images, Image I1 and I2.
As an example, if this
is a testing image,
if we want to calculate
the distance of this image
with an image in
the training data,
we do a pixel wise
subtraction and the difference
between the pixel values
and then sum them up,
which defines this new--
this value as the distance
between these two images.
So this is the most
basic distance function,
but it's actually very
useful in many applications.
We'll be coming back to
this L1 and other variations
of distances in the
class quite often.
With this very
simple definition,
we want to see
how we can get it.
Get this implemented.
As I said, the first step is to
just memorize the training data.
So the train function just
keeps the data in the memory.
And then what the
predict function
does, using actually some Python
libraries and NumPy and so on,
we can implement this
in just four lines.
We calculate the distances
between each of the testing
samples and the training
data, take the minimum
for each of the testing
samples, and then output
the label for the
one with mean index.
So this is going to
be the implementation
for the predict function.
Yeah, the pixel values, as I
explained, the simplest form,
this is a tensor of 800 by
600 by 3 and three channels,
and these are RGB values for
each of the pixel locations.
So yes, I should actually
repeat the questions
for online students too.
And the question was the pixel
values, what do they represent?
Yeah, so the next question is
why it's between 0 and 255.
So there are many different
standards for storing images.
The most popular one that
we use in almost all images
that you see online
and here they are RGB.
RGB is a 24-bit
format, sometimes 32
because there's
another channel alpha.
We don't want to get into those.
But the 24-bit format, it means
that for each of the channels,
for each of the three channels
of red, green, and blue,
which creates all of
our color combinations,
we can have 8 bits.
So that's the standard
that is defined.
There are some other
frameworks too,
but this is the
most popular one.
So with that, let me go back to
the code and ask you a question.
So I know some of the
students, most of the students
come with engineering
backgrounds and a little bit
of computer science as well,
but we want to see with,
say, n samples n examples
that we have in the training
data how fast the training
and prediction happens.
I'm hoping that you're familiar
with the big O notation
that we often represents
computational and sometimes
space complexities with.
But here, if you look
at the algorithms,
I'll go with the training data.
In the training
function-- and then
I want you to help me with
the answer for prediction.
For the training
step, the training
is of O1 because we are not
actually doing anything.
We are not even moving any data.
We are just keeping the copy
of the data in the memory.
So no operations, it means
that without operations,
with an operations
of order 1, we
can complete the training step.
What about the
prediction step for each
of the single examples of the
training-- the testing data?
How many operations
should we take?
N, yes.
If we have n training
data, it means
that we have to calculate the
distance of every single testing
image with all of the
images in the training data,
so at least in the
order of n operations.
So this is not really good
because what we often want to do
is-- because training
is not doing anything.
But during testing,
during prediction time,
we are spending
so much time just
to do comparisons
between the data
and the single data points
and the training examples.
This would be
similar to the fact
that each single time that
you ask ChatGPT a question,
it will try to see what the
answer is and compare it
with all of the possible
answers over the internet, which
will take years and then
return your response.
So it wouldn't work
when it wants to scale
for very simple problems.
We used to be using these
types of approaches.
So what we often want is
to build classifiers that
are fast during prediction.
They do it much faster, but it's
OK if they take a lot of time
to do during the
training because that
could be done offline.
So with that in
mind, although there
has been a lot of efforts
making nearest neighbor more--
much faster using
GPUs and so on,
which are beyond the
scope of this class,
if you're interested, you
can take a look at those.
But with that, I want to look
at some of the visualizations
and how this algorithm
in general works.
So given this space
that we have five
classes of red, blue,
green, purple and red--
sorry, yellow, and each dot
represents one training, sample
in that class, if we partition
the space for every single point
you see that we can create
these five partitions--
let's say five or in this case
six different partitions--
that each point, if you
have a testing sample that
is in that specific region,
the color of that region
shows what the nearest neighbor
for that sample will be.
So this is going to be the
nearest neighbor algorithm, one
nearest neighbor
algorithm partitions
the space in this setting.
But do you see a problem
here in this example?
So the yellow one is exactly--
is in the middle of
all of the greens.
And this means that
probably that's an outlier.
That's probably a noise.
And this is the case
for many, many problems
that we have to solve.
And with that, the
reason that there
is this big yellow
region in the middle
is just this single point.
And because we are only
using one nearest neighbor,
this happens.
So to make it a little
bit more robust,
we can increase the number of
nearest neighbors that we take,
which turns the nearest
neighbor algorithm
into a k-nearest neighbor.
And we often select more
than one point or sample.
And we often take
the majority voting
for identifying the label
for any given testing
sample, testing image.
But the problem that
you can see here
is now we have
some white regions.
Those white regions are areas
that we cannot make a decision,
a complete decision because
those areas are areas that we
have equal number of samples
from the neighbors from
the three different classes.
And there is no way
to identify what
the label of that example
in the white region is.
And for you, if you
create these types
of spaces for your
problems, this
means that if you
look at these spaces,
it means that those are good
regions to go and collect
more data for.
So those are unclear spaces.
So it's a good way
of finding regions
that are important for data--
more data collection.
So we can go larger
on the value of the k.
But one of the choices
that we have, one of the.
Factors that plays an important
role is the value of k.
But if you remember,
we had another decision
to make which was the
distance function.
We talked about the
L1 distance again sum
of all of the absolute values
between pairwise differences
of the pixels.
And if I visualize the
L1 distance or sometimes
in some context, we call
it Manhattan distance,
the distance function is kind
of visualized in this way.
If I look at this square
that I have in this space,
all of the points
on that square are--
they have the same
distance from the origin
from the center point.
So this is a good way of
visualizing and seeing
how this L1 distance
function works.
Another popular framework,
another popular distance
function that we
use is L2, which
instead of the absolute
value, calculates the square
of the differences, sums it up.
But because of the square,
we also do a square root.
And visualizing that, we'll get
the circle visualization, where
each of the points on
the circle are-- they
have the same distance from
the center, from the origin.
So this visualization
actually helps
us understand the differences
between these distances too.
And these are the most basic
and easiest distance functions
that we can use.
So there are, again, a lot more.
The reason this
visualization is helpful
is because sometimes if
you rotate the-- so x
and y in these
two visualizations
are basically the features.
If you have two pixel
values, two features,
then we have this 2D space.
And this x and y are
often those features.
So if I rotate these
features, meaning,
if I use other
types of features,
this L1 will have a different
framework, different value,
while it's not any
different for L2.
So that's why this is a big
difference between L1 and L2.
And sometimes if our features
are very specific and meaningful
and we want to preserve
their information,
often L1 is more
important, is better
because it has kind
of, as you can see,
a shape that preserves
and enforces distances
based on the features.
But if those features
are more arbitrary,
then L2 distance
makes more sense.
If I want to calculate
the distance--
so the distance of all of
the points on this shape
from the origin are exactly the
same, if I use the L1 distance,
but for L2 distance, the
points on this circle
have the same distance
from the center
or the origin of this space.
So that's basically the main--
what these two
images are showing.
Any point on this shape,
when using an L1 distance,
have the same distance
from the origin.
And for the circle, any
point on the circle,
if you're using L2
distance, you'll
have the same distance
from the origin.
Yeah, why It's important to--
it's better to use L1 if we
want to preserve the features.
So to answer that question,
if I rotate the feature
axis, the distances
and this distance
function changes completely.
While if I do the same
here, nothing changes.
It's the exact same
value of the features--
distance.
Sorry.
So in this case, L1 is very
sensitive on the feature values,
while L2 is not.
If you select another feature
in the same space that
is having a different creates
a different shape, then
your L function, the distance
function changes as well.
So if I draw the
lines here, again,
the question for online students
is why it changes if you rotate.
If I select another feature
that goes from this side,
then the lines will
look different.
So if you rotate this thing, but
for that shape it's not-- it's
agnostic.
So with these two distance
functions that we talked about,
if I visualize
the space, you can
see with k equals to 1 with one
nearest neighbor with L1 and L2,
these are the space
partitionings.
One of the interesting
things that you can see here
is that with L1 function,
most of the boundaries
are parallel to the two
axes, the two features,
x1 and x2, very much
sensitive to the features.
While there, we
have a little bit
of more smooth
boundary separation.
So there is a tool
online on the lab website
that you can play around with
this, with different distance
functions and
different number of k.
You can see, you can
create a different setup.
So you can play around with it.
But why did we talk about
nearest neighbor to begin with?
First, yes, it's the
easiest problem to solve,
easiest solution, easiest
data-driven approach, and great
to start with.
But one of the main reasons that
we want to iterate and discuss
nearest neighbor
is the fact that we
can look into the topic
of hyperparameters.
Hyperparameters are often
some of the variables
that you have to
make a decision on
to be able to run
your algorithm.
In this case, the value of k,
the number of nearest neighbors
is defined as-- is
a hyperparameter.
Depending on how many number
of nearest neighbors you take,
your outputs will be different.
And then another choice
that you have here
is the distance function.
So the choice of
hyperparameters are often
very much data set-dependent
and sometimes problem-dependent.
And we have to have
a way to identify
those to optimize for them
for each single problem.
And that's what
is often referred
to as hyperparameter tuning in
machine-learning algorithms,
in deep learning
algorithms and so on.
And how to do that?
How to set the hyperparameters?
There are different approaches.
One of them is to choose the
hyperparameters that work
the best for the training data.
So you have a set
of images or data.
In your training data,
you look for the best set
of hyperparameters that
generates the best training
or minimum training loss.
While it works for
the training data,
it's not a good idea at
all because, especially
with nearest neighbor, k equal
to 1 is always the best value.
Because you're memorizing
training data, so k equal to 1
will give you, always,
the 100% accuracy.
So we know that this
is not a great idea.
The second one is choosing
hyperparameter that works
best for held-out testing sets.
While this is a little bit
better than the first one,
there is also a
big problem here.
Can anybody say why
this is a problem.
Exactly, so it's kind of
cheating because you are trying
to find the best hyperparameter
that works on the testing data,
and you don't know how the model
will work on any other data
points, not in the testing set.
So yes, that is exactly right.
It's not a good idea
because we don't know
how the model will generalize.
And for sure never do this.
As we talked about,
it's kind of cheating.
And a better idea is
to always separate,
take some part of the training
data as validation set.
And train your model
on the training data
on the train portion of the
new portion that we call train.
And then try to find or
optimize your hyperparameter
on the validation set.
And after you've found the
best set of hyperparameters,
then use those
hyperparameters to replicate
the results for the testing
set and do the predictions
for the testing set.
So this is a much
better approach,
although it does have some
challenges itself because.
Sometimes the validation
set that you've selected,
it may not be a
good representative
of the entire landscape
because your validation set
is almost always much smaller.
And that's why one of
the-- a better approach
is to use cross-validation
for setting hyperparameters.
Basically, you split
your training data
into a number of folds,
a number of partitions.
Here, in this case, five.
And each of the folds plays
as the validation set once.
And iteratively, you
run this five times
for five-fold cross-validation.
You do this five times and
average the accuracies.
So you set a value of
the hyperparameter.
You run this for all these
five sets, define the accuracy,
calculate the accuracy on the
validation set, average it.
And then you do
this multiple times
to find the best setting
for the hyperparameter.
After you found the
hyperparameter setting,
you apply it to the testing set.
This is a little
bit more reliable
and generates much
better results,
although in larger
scale deep learning,
it is less practiced because
repeating this multiple times
and five times with huge
data sets is very hard.
So we often use intuitions
for setting hyperparameters,
and the single validation
set is sometimes
the approach we go with.
But this is pretty much advised.
Again, outside computer vision,
outside larger scale data sets,
often research
papers require doing
these types of cross-validation
and these types
of statistical frameworks to
make sure your results are
reproducible on a testing set.
Anyways, so there are
different approaches.
Let's finalize
the topic, wrap up
the topic of nearest
neighbor, and look
at some examples, some results.
So let me introduce you
to the CIFAR10 data set.
It's one of the data
sets that you're
going to be using in your
assignments quite often.
It has 10 classes with a number
of training images and testing
images.
The 10 classes,
some of the examples
are shown here with
nearest neighbor
for each of the testing images.
If we run nearest
neighbor and select
the top 10 nearest neighbors,
they are all visualized there.
As you can imagine and guess,
one of the first questions
to answer is how many--
what should be the value for k?
How many nearest
neighbors should we take?
And want to study one
of the quick experiments
with five-fold,
each of those points
is one of the folds in five-fold
for each of the values of k,
shows different values here.
And as you can probably
see here, k equal to 7,
it generates the best
results in terms of accuracy,
which is close to 29%--
to 28% accuracy, which
is actually not too bad
because this is a 10-class
classification problem.
And with a 10-class
classification problem,
often the random guess
gets you a 10% accuracy.
So this is much better
than random guess.
So it's working.
It's doing something, but there
is a lot of room to improve.
So if we go back and
look at the examples,
we can actually see there are
so many mistakes, especially
with the one that is closest.
For example, the fourth row, if
you look at that, it's a frog.
But the first example
seems to be a cat.
Sorry, a dog.
And you can guess why this is
happening because the distance
is being applied on pixels.
And pixel wise, they
look like each other.
They have the same type
of colors in most pixels,
so they are much closer.
This example and
many other examples
show that distances that work
on pixels and pixel values
are not the best choices.
We never practice them.
There are much better
approaches that we'll
be discussing at the end of--
more in the future lectures.
And just to wrap up the topic,
this is another example.
If you look at this original
image, those three images,
while they look very
much different in terms
of color or maybe occlusion,
or the one in the third one
from the left side is
just same pixel-- it's
the same image with one pixel
shifting to the right, I think.
Although from a human
eyes perspective,
there is no-- absolutely
no difference.
But the distance between
that and the original image
is the same as the other two
examples that you see here.
I'll stop for a
couple of questions,
and this is the summary
of what we've discussed.
So the question is, how
do we make a decision.
In those cases, you often go
with randomly selected one
of the tops.
So if you are to collect
more data, if you're--
for example, you're solving
a problem now in genetics
or you're solving a
problem in medical imaging
when you visualize your
examples, your features
or whatever.
And then in this
nearest neighbor space,
you do see pockets of space that
you don't have any good samples
for, or there is
ambiguity, then you often
try to go and find
other samples that
lie in that same
area in that space.
OK, so summarizing
what we've talked
about with k-nearest
neighbor, it
was mostly about
understanding the easiest
algorithm, data-driven
approach, and then talking
a little bit about
hyperparameter tuning
and how distance metrics
and the value of k
play a very important role.
Moving on to the next topic,
which is linear classifiers.
25 minutes time to
cover this, I want
to spend the remaining
time of this lecture
to talk about this
very important topic.
This is the most important
building block for almost.
All of deep learning.
And we need to see how
this approach is different.
So first we want to see how it's
different from nearest neighbor.
So this is a
parametric approach,
meaning that now we are
learning we are finding
some parameters, w,
or some weights that
map the input image into the
output classes, the output
numbers.
In this case, when we
create this function
f that maps input
to the output, often
those outputs are kind
of membership scores
of the image to each of those
10 output classes labels.
So with this setup that we
build, a linear classifier
first maps uses w
uses these parameters
to map each of the inputs x into
a value, which is the output y.
And how this is
done is very simple.
This image is basically an
area of, say, 32 by 32 by 3,
so 3,072 numbers.
And this defines our x,
which is 3,072 by one vector.
And we know that we
have 10 output classes.
So we need 10 different scores.
And the scores are--
the output will be kind
of a vector of 10 by 1.
And this means that we have to
identify to find a weight matrix
w that is a 10 by 3,072 that
maps x into the output scores.
Just to complete
this linear function,
we often use this
bias term as well.
It's an input-independent
value, which actually has
a lot of different use cases.
I can talk about it when I do
some geometric visualizations,
but it sometimes creates a
shift for different class scores
and helps with much better
separation of each class.
So as I said, these
linear functions
are actually building blocks
for building neural networks.
Each of these linear
classifiers, linear functions
when put together,
one after the other,
create these large
neural networks.
Although there are a
lot of other things
that need to be
added here, but this
is one of the most
important components.
If we look at some of the
popular neural networks,
we can see that linear
functions are everywhere
in the architectures.
So, to better understand what
this mapping and this function
is doing, let's go back
to our example of CIFAR10
and our training and
testing samples and so on,
and even make it a
little bit simpler.
Instead of looking at
large images of 32 by 32,
let's look at images of
2 by 2, an input image
that has four pixels.
This means that the input
image is turned into a vector.
As you can see here, we have to
find a w and the values of b.
So the input image is mapped
into some scores as the output.
So this is how the
linear function
from an algebraic
viewpoint looks like.
The output scores here, we
are considering three classes
of cat, dog, and ship.
And as you can
see, this function
maps the image, the vector,
representing the image
into those scores.
So algebraic viewpoint
of linear classification.
Now let's look at some
visual perspectives
of this linear classifier.
As you can see, we often
create each of these images,
as we talked about
for this image.
For each of the classes, we
define some sort of-- we have
a row of this--
row in the matrix w.
So this row is
kind of a template
for that specific class.
If I separate it like
this, so this image
is multiplied by w
and b, and w is--
this is the template
from each of the three
classes of cat, dog, and ship.
And after training or building
the model on the CIFAR data set,
if I look at the visual
perspective, a visual point,
viewpoint of the
linear classifier,
if I look at those
templates that
are learned for each
of the 10 classes,
you can see these templates.
So it's very
interesting that in some
of these cases, for example,
for the example for car,
you do see a front of
a car template-ish,
and although this is all done
with just one linear classifier.
So the visual aspect,
visual viewpoint
of the linear
classifier, and there
is another aspect of
geometric viewpoint.
What this linear classifier
often does is finding those
lines if it's in 2D space,
finding those lines that
separates each class
from the others.
And as you can see here,
red, blue, and green
are defining different classes,
and in higher dimensional space,
instead of those lines,
it's these hyperplanes,
as you can see in this
example on the left.
So you can also see the
use of the bias term
here, because if we didn't have
the bias, all of these lines
should have passed
through the origin
from the center of that space,
which doesn't really make sense.
But with the bias,
we can actually
create more reliable functions
and decision boundaries.
So a linear function
is very useful.
A linear classifier is very
useful for many applications,
as we talked about.
And it's a building block of
more complex neural networks.
But it does have
its own challenges
because it can't classify many
instances of separate data.
For example, in this
case, if class 1
is the first and third
quadrant and the second class
is second and the fourth.
There is no way to
linearly separate these.
Another example is if we
have this type of separation
between class 1
and class 2, that
shows the distance from the
origin being between 1 and 2
as class 1, and then
everything else as class 2.
Similarly, if there
are three modes,
three areas in the space
that are one class, and then
the second class
is everything else.
So in all of these cases,
it's actually very hard
to do the separation.
So what we should do--
so we talked about
linear classifiers
and how they can actually map
the input images into any form
of labels in the output.
But now what remains is how
to choose the value w, that
for each of these
images maps the image
into a score for each
single class as the output.
And in order to do that, we
need to define a loss function,
sometimes referred to
as objective function,
that quantifies how
bad the classifier,
how bad the model is working.
So the level of
unhappiness with respect
to the score on
the training data.
After defining those, we need to
find a way to efficiently change
the values of w to be able
to minimize that unhappiness,
basically, minimize
the loss function.
And this is the
optimization process.
So the topic of next
class, next lecture.
And in order to do that,
again for simplicity
let's look at an easier
and easier example, having
these three classes a linear
function, as you can see here,
and the three classes
of cat, car, and frog.
We need a loss
function that tells how
good our current classifier is.
And in order to do that, we need
to parameterize the problem, xi
and yi defining the input
image, label images,
and the corresponding labels.
And then we need the loss
function and distance
function that maps--
looks at the differences and
how bad the scores are compared
to the ones that are predicted,
the predicted scores fx and w,
and the ground truth values, the
values that are already given,
yi.
We often normalize them based on
the number of samples as well,
but it's not that important.
So this defines
the loss function,
the objective function.
So how we can do
the optimization,
and how can we
really find the w's?
There are different ways
of defining this l--
li.
And I want to talk about
softmax classifier right now.
As an example for
that cat, if you
remember the scores
that were given
were 3.2, 5.1, and
a minus 1.7, these
are the scores that are the
output of the function we
discussed, f, xi and w.
And in order to
turn these scores--
because these
scores are unbounded
and the values are
often not very much
controllable because this
is just a linear function.
In order to turn these into some
scoring functions, the best--
the best possible
way is to turn these
into probabilities,
which defines
the probability of the
class being this class
k for each input image xi.
And in order to do
that, we first--
this is the function that we
use, the softmax function.
We first exponentiate
the values of the scores
to create these numbers.
When we use exp
on these numbers,
the numbers will always be--
the outputs will
always be positive.
And we need to make sure that
the probabilities are always
positive.
And after creating these
numbers, what we can do
is just normalize them.
So exponentiate
and then normalize
based on the sum of
all of the samples.
So then we normalize them
based on sum of all samples.
And this creates a
very, very good set
of values that define
a probability function.
So this is a
distribution function.
They sum to 1.
And if I want to
interpret these,
it's very simple to say it's
this set of w's, parameters,
thinks that this image is
a cat with a probability
of 13% or 0.13.
And obviously, this is making
a mistake in this example
because the w is
not a good setting.
We should optimize
it and change it.
So these probabilities
are the counterparts
of these unnormalized log
probabilities, which are often
referred to as logits.
So if you've taken other
machine-learning courses,
or if you--
I'm sure in other fields,
you've used logistic regression,
this is a similar
type of framework.
This is the exact same framework
as logistic regression.
And since we have
multiple classes here,
it's a multinomial
logistic regression.
How do we define the function l?
I told you that there
are different ways
of defining the function l.
We want to define a
loss function that--
what's objective here?
We want to maximize the
probability of the sample
belonging to the correct class.
So we want to maximize
the value of 0.13.
Now we have other larger
values in that set.
So if you want to maximize this,
this is a maximization problem.
In order to turn it--
because all of the objectives
that we define, we try to
build a minimization objective
function, the first step is
just to negate the values.
We negate it so the
maximization problem turns
into a minimization problem.
And then we also take
the log of the value
just to make the numbers a
little bit more manageable.
So negative log
of that value will
define the objective
function, the loss function
for solving this problem.
Very simple.
That's the objective,
or the loss
function for softmax and
for this logistic regression
function.
And if you've taken, as I said,
other classes like CS-229,
it's often referred to as
maximum likelihood estimation
as well.
It's the same algorithm.
So with that in mind, I want to
say that-- so as we discussed,
it's the negative of the
log of that probability
of the correct class, which
defines the objective function
the loss function.
And that's basically
that simple.
But there are other types of
interpreting this framework
as well.
So one way of redefining
this loss function
is saying that we have some
estimated probabilities,
and we also have a probability
function that defines
the correct probabilities.
What we want to do is to match
these two probability functions.
And in order to do that, we want
to minimize the KL divergence,
Kullback-Leibler divergence.
This is a information
theoretic perspective
of looking at this
loss function.
And again, those are
exactly the same.
This KL divergence
in this setting
simplifies into the same
negative log function
that we defined.
And even going further, this
is exactly the cross entropy
function, because if we define
this, use this entropy of p,
which is entropy of
the correct values,
correct probabilities plus
that same KL divergence, again,
this simplifies into the
same negative log function.
And that's because when
we use one hot encoding
setting for the classes,
the entropy is 0.
So that's one of
the reasons that we
call this function cross
entropy or binary cross
entropy function.
In all of deep learning,
you've probably--
if you've used any of the
neural network frameworks,
you've heard about BCE,
Binary Cross Entropy,
or you will be hearing
about it a lot.
So this is the same framework.
We start very simple, but
we got to the similarities
and differences
between each of those.
So the objective--
sorry, the loss function
was defined as negative
log of this probability,
and the probability was
defined by the softmax, which
we talked about.
And then optimizing for this,
which is the topic of next
session, will give
us the right w's.
But before I end, I want to
ask a couple of questions
with this definition
that you see here.
What is the mean
and maximum value
that you can see for
the loss function li?
Yes, it's 0, which turns
into minus minus infinity.
But we have a negative negation
there, so it would be infinity.
That is correct.
But then we also have to--
yes, that's definitely--
that's right.
And let me actually look
at a second question.
Yes, this one.
So when we initialize all of
the si, so basically, the w's,
in the beginning,
it's almost random.
So the probabilities
of each of the classes
becomes mostly equal.
What is the softmax li,
assuming we have c classes?
And especially if it's c10.
So because the
probabilities are equal,
it means that all of the
probabilities are around 1
over C. And then that will
be defined as log of C.
And we have 10-- if
we have 10 classes,
then the log or ln of 10
is 2.3, which is the exp.
We know about it.