Today we're going to be talking
about image classification
with CNNs.
So you might be wondering,
who am I. I'm a new face.
You haven't seen me
before in this class.
I'm Justin, I'm the
fourth mystery instructor
in this class.
I think my picture's
been on the website,
but it's my first
time here today.
And a little about me.
I did my PhD here at
Stanford from 2012 to 2018,
working with [INAUDIBLE]
on deep learning,
computer vision, pretty much
all tasks in computer vision
around that time.
During my time
here at Stanford, I
was lucky enough to
initiate CS231N with Andre
and [INAUDIBLE] and others and
teach it, quite a few times
2015, '16, '17 and '18 and '19.
At Stanford after that, I spent
time at Facebook AI research
doing all kinds of deep learning
computer vision stuff there.
And I was a faculty member
at University of Michigan.
And there I taught basically the
same class a couple more times.
So I've taught this
class a couple times,
but it's been a while
since I've been here,
and most recently, I've
been doing a startup called
World Labs with [INAUDIBLE].
And that's just a
little bit about me.
Now, about where we
are on this class.
So we're at an interesting
point in the class
right now, where the
class is divided up
into these couple
different segments.
And we've basically
finished the first segment.
The first segment is basically
around deep learning basics.
And this is really cool because
now all the stuff that you've
seen in four lectures is
basically all the fundamentals
of deep learning.
You basically know
this whole pipeline
of what is the basic pieces that
go into building a deep learning
system.
So I thought it's useful here at
the beginning of this inflection
point to just step back and
recap some of the major themes
that we've seen in the
first bit of the course.
So the first is this idea
of image classification
with linear classifiers.
And this was meant
as a toy problem,
to give you a sense of a
problem you might solve
with deep learning, where
usually the first step
in solving a deep
learning problem
is to define your
problem in a way
where it is you take input, some
grid of numbers, some tensors,
you produce as
output some tensors,
and you want to formalize
this problem as some input
output of tensors.
And we do that in the image
classification setting
by saying that we want
to classify images
into a bunch of human
understandable categories,
the inputs are going to be these
grids of pixel values, which
are arranged in three
dimensional tensors.
The outputs are
going to be scores,
giving us the
affinity or the degree
to which we have one
score per category
or you define a set of
categories in advance,
and the network is
supposed to predict
high scores for categories
that the image is likely to be,
low scores for the
categories that the image is
likely to be not.
And then we can define--
we can set up a problem
use a weight matrix,
multiply that against the image
pixels and predict these scores.
And we saw that there's a
couple of different viewpoints,
a couple different ways
that we can interpret
these linear classifiers.
And this basically sets
up a functional form
saying that we can predict
scores for images if only
we have a weight matrix w.
So then the question is, how do
we select a good weight matrix
w?
And for that, we go
to loss functions.
So loss functions
are these things
that tell us given a particular
value of a weight matrix,
given a particular data set, how
well does this weight matrix fit
to solve the problem
on this data set.
And in particular, we saw some
examples of loss functions
that are commonly used for
classification problems,
including the softmax loss and
probably the SVM loss as well.
And then now, OK, so now
we've gotten a little bit
farther along in our problem.
We've set up the problem
of image classification.
We have a model for
solving that problem using
linear classifiers.
We have a way to tell if our
solutions are good using a loss
function, but now
we actually need
to search for a good
solution in that space.
And that's where
optimization comes in.
So now that we-- now
you think of the-- now
you think of defining this
optimization landscape,
where on the x-axis or
on the horizontal plane
are all the different possible
settings of your weight matrix.
And then the loss
function is basically
a height of this plane, where
a high loss function is bad
because losing things is bad.
So you want low loss.
So the purpose of
optimization is
to somehow traverse this space,
slide down this manifold,
and find a point at the
bottom of very low loss.
And now each point in this space
corresponds to a weight matrix.
So by sliding down
that space, we're
going to find a good weight
matrix that solves our problem
and gives us a good
solution to our task.
And in particular,
we saw a couple
of different commonly used
optimization algorithms that
are used in deep learning
pipelines; stochastic gradient
descent, usually with
momentum, RMSProp, Adam.
And one interesting
topical note is
that right now, one of
the biggest deep learning
research conferences is ICLR,
International Conference
on Learning Representations.
And just yesterday,
I cleared 2025,
gave their test of Time
Award to the Adam paper
because the paper
that introduced
this Adam optimizer
was published
at ICLR 10 years ago in 2015.
So a lot of academic
conferences,
they'll tend to give
test of time awards
to some of the most impactful
papers from 10 years ago.
And just yesterday,
the Adam optimizer
that you guys have been
learning-- that you guys saw
in this class got this very
prestigious test of Time Award
at ICLR 2025.
So I thought that was
pretty cool in a nice way
to connect what
you've been learning
stuff that's happening right
now in the machine learning
community.
So then now we
basically-- at this point
we've got our
linear classifiers,
we've got our loss functions.
We can optimize them.
Now, we're almost good to go.
But we ran into a problem is
that the linear classifiers
that we started with are
actually not very powerful.
And we saw this from- we
saw two different ways
of attacking this deficiency
in linear classifiers.
One was from the
visual viewpoint,
where you can interpret a
linear classifier by thinking
about-- by thinking
of that learned weight
matrix as an image where
you learn one image
template for each
of the categories
that you're trying
to-- that you're
trying to classify against.
And if you think
about it that way,
we realize that the weights
of your linear classifier,
each row of that weight
matrix is one template.
So the linear
classifier basically
needs to summarize all of its
knowledge about each category
into just one template.
And that's a difficult--
that's just not
a very powerful classifier.
So then you can-- this shows up
in these visualized templates
of a learned linear
classifier, where
you can see that for
categories like the car,
this car looks like a red blob.
But cars don't have
to be red, right?
What if your car was blue or
purple or green or something
else?
There's just no good way
for a linear classifier
to caption this--
capture this notion of there
might be different appearances
for an object for each category,
or from the geometric viewpoint,
if we imagine these each
point of our data set
as some point in high
dimensional space,
then a linear classifier is
basically going in and carving
up that space with hyperplanes.
So that's really good if
all your categories actually
do lie in linearly separable
regions of your space,
but there's no reason to expect
that to be true in general.
So these are both
two big deficiencies
that we ran into when looking
at these linear classifiers as
applied to image
classification problems.
And that led us--
and that led us
to define this notion of
neural networks, where we're
going to generalize our linear
classifiers to no longer
just have one weight matrix,
but instead stack two weight
matrices on top of each
other with a non-linearity
in between them.
And now this gives us a
much more powerful mechanism
for predicting scores
from our inputs.
Now, basically the
problem is still the same.
We have our input pixels going
through this computation,
spitting out scores.
But now, rather than computing
what we just basically selected
a different functional form
for this score function.
And this gave us--
and now the algebra
is pretty simple.
You just need to go
from f equals wx.
You add an extra w2, add a
little non-linearity in between.
So the algebra doesn't
change very much.
But in doing so,
your classifiers
get much, much more powerful
than they were before.
But now things get a little
bit complicated again
because how does this
play into optimization.
We know that if we
have a loss function,
if we have a model,
then we want to find
values of those weight matrix
that cause the loss to go down.
And to do that, we need
to compute gradients.
We need to be able
to compute gradients
of the loss with respect to all
the parameters of our model.
And that's this notion
of a computational graph.
So these computational graphs
are basically a data structure
to organize the computation
of a neural network, where
each node in the
graph is a little
functional primitive like
a matrix multiply or a ReLU
or some other something
else like that.
And then data flows
forward in this graph
from left to right,
from our inputs
and our weights on
the left, flowing
through all these intermediate
nodes in the graph
to spit out the loss
function on the right.
And then once we
compute the loss,
you traverse this loss-- this
graph backwards from right
to left to compute gradients
of that loss with respect
to all the nodes of the
graph inside the network.
And this is now really
cool, because it basically
means that we can write down
these arbitrarily complicated
neural networks,
these arbitrarily
complicated expressions
for computing
our outputs from our inputs.
But we now have an automate--
a nearly automated algorithm
for computing whatever gradients
we want through arbitrarily
complex neural networks.
And the way that we do that is
this magic of backpropagation.
And backpropagation
is really cool.
I think it's one of
the algorithms that
makes deep learning
work, because it
takes this global problem
of how do we compute
the loss through this
computational graph
and converts it into
a local problem.
And now each of
these nodes doesn't
need to know anything about
the larger context of what
is the graph I'm living
in, what is the problem I'm
trying to solve.
We just need to be able to
define these little nodes
inside of our computational
graph that on the forward pass
know how to compute
outputs from their inputs,
and then on the backwards pass
can receive gradients coming
upstream.
It doesn't have to care where
those gradients come from,
what was causing those
gradients to happen.
And I just need to compute
gradients-- downstream gradients
with respect to my inputs
given my upstream gradients.
And again, this is so
powerful because now it
gives us this mechanism
where we can just
define a bunch of
different types of nodes
that all just have follow this
local API of computing outputs,
computing local gradients.
And if we as long as we follow
that API for all of the nodes,
then we can start to
stitch them together
into these big, complicated
computational graphs that
can do basically
arbitrary computation.
And the gradients
just come for free
when we turn the crank on the
back propagation algorithm.
And this slide that
you guys saw last time
is basically backpropagation
on scalar values.
But we can generalize this
to work on vector value--
on vector valued or matrix or
tensor valued values as well.
But the basic thing
to remember is
that your inputs
are some tensors,
your outputs are some tensors.
And now your upstream
gradient that you get
is the gradient of the loss
with respect to your outputs.
And that always has the
same shape as your outputs.
Because the loss is
a scalar, a gradient
of loss with respect
to a tensor says
for each element
in the tensor, if I
were to wiggle that element a
little bit, then how much does
the loss wiggle.
And because the
loss is a scalar,
we just need to wiggle
each of those-- we just
need to imagine wiggling
each element in our tensor
independently.
And that is the definition
of our gradient.
So then that's very
easy to remember.
Your upstream gradients always
have the exact same shape
as your outputs.
Your downstream gradients, those
are the gradients with respect
to my inputs.
Those also have the
same shape as my inputs.
So then the
backpropagation algorithm
is basically just
the chain rule,
where I need to somehow
compute my downstream gradients
as a function of my
upstream gradients
and whatever function I
was trying to compute.
And you'll get some practice on
later assignments computing--
writing down the
gradient expressions
for different kinds of operators
in your neural networks.
So basically, this
gives us our recipe
for solving pretty much any
problem in deep learning.
This was intended to be quite a
bit more general than just image
classification or just
linear classifiers
or just fully
connected networks.
Now, if you have any problem
that you want to solve,
you just need to
encode it as tensors,
write down some computational
graph that computes your output
tensors from your input
tensors, collect a data
set of input-output
tensors, write down
a loss function for the kind
of problem you want to solve.
And then optimize that loss
function using gradient descent
using backpropagation.
And that's a really
powerful recipe
that basically powers all
deep learning applications,
whether it's image
classification, image
generation, large language
models, pretty much anything
involving a neural
network is trained
using this formula or
some slight variant
on top of this formula.
So that leads us
to the second part
of the class, which is
perceiving and understanding
the visual world.
So here's where we want to get
a little bit more specialized
and start talking about
not the general framework
of deep learning,
but how does this
apply to problems that we want
to solve in computer vision.
Processing images, doing
interesting stuff with images.
And today, we'll take
a step towards that
by talking about a bit more
about convolutional networks.
So convolutional networks
actually are a pretty small lift
on top of this framework
that we've already defined.
So we've already
talked about two.
We have this-- you have
this general paradigm
of computational graphs
of little operators
that can live inside of
our computational graphs.
So we have this
beautiful framework,
but we actually haven't filled
in a lot of the specifics
of that framework.
We've actually only seen
two or three different kinds
of nodes that can live inside
of our computational graphs.
We've seen fully
connected layers which
is basically a matrix multiply.
We've seen activation
functions like our ReLU,
and we've seen our loss
functions themselves.
And now to build up from
what we've seen already
into convolutional
networks, basically all we
need to do is add a couple new
types of nodes that can fit
into our computational graphs.
And in particular, there's
really only two operators
that we need to
talk about to build
much more powerful networks,
which will be the convolution
layer that we'll spend most of
today's lecture talking about.
And then the
pooling layer, which
is another thing that we often
use when processing images.
So that's the roadmap for today.
I want to talk a little bit
about convolutional networks
in general.
Then we'll talk about these
two particular computational
primitives that we can use to
build convolutional networks
in our computational graphs.
So we've already talked
about-- so then here
we want to step
back a little bit
and think about this problem
of image classification again.
So we've already talked about
how image classification is
this super core problem
in computer vision, where
we want to take an input image
and then predict from that input
image what is in this image
as a set of categories--
predict one of k category
labels basically.
And this image
obviously is a cat.
So we want to predict
the cat classifier.
And most of-- and we
basically solved this problem
in some sense already by
building linear classifiers
and by building fully connected
multi-layer perceptron neural
networks.
But these networks are basically
operating in pixel space.
Their inputs, remember
we said the first way
to-- the first step to solving
a deep learning problem
is to formulate it in terms
of input-output tensors.
Well, in this case,
our input tensors
were the raw pixel
values of our images.
So when we write f of x
equals wx that x input,
that's just the literal
values of all of our pixels.
And then we go from
those raw pixel values
to our class scores.
But there's another way
to do it, which was common
back in the dark ages before
neural networks came about
and saved us from all this TDM.
Maybe back in the early 2000,
up until maybe 2010, 2011-ish,
was this idea of
feature representations.
So here, the idea
is you can actually
choose what is going to be your
input to your neural network.
So you could have said, rather
than feeding the raw pixel
values of the image
into our neural network,
instead we could define some
other kind of function, which
is going to extract features,
extract some-- convert
those pixel values of our image
into some other meaningful
representation that we as the
intelligent human designers
of this system,
believe, represent,
or capture some of the important
facets of our input image.
So then when if you're doing
image classification on top
of a feature representation,
your step one
would be to define a
feature representation
that converts your raw image
pixels into this higher level
representation.
And now that feature
representation
will now take the-- will
now be the x that feeds
into your linear classifier.
And there was a ton of
work in computer vision,
really in the 2000 to the late
2010s or to the early 2010-ish
that used this idea of feature
representations for all kinds
of tasks.
And I don't really
think it's useful to go
into super great detail on any
of these particular feature
representations,
because spoiler alert,
they got deprecated
like 10 years ago,
but it's useful to
have a flavor for what
they might have looked like.
So one example of a
feature representation
that people sometimes
used is this notion
of a color histogram.
So here what we could
say is divide the space.
So maybe we think that somehow
the distribution of colors
in our image might be a
useful thing for a classifier
to look at or care about.
Because maybe you're
building a fruit detector,
an apple detector, and you want
to know if it's ripe or not.
Maybe a red apple
from a green apple,
knowing how much red or green is
in the image might be something
that we as humans think
is useful for the network
to know for making
its classifications.
So here we could
build-- we could
try to build a feature
representation that
captures that intuition.
So here what we might
do is take the space
of all possible colors,
discretize that space
into some set of buckets.
And now for every
pixel in our image,
we map that pixel to one of the
discrete buckets in our color
space.
And then basically, our feature
representation becomes something
like a count of how
many pixels in the image
fall into this color bucket.
And now you could-- and now this
is an interesting representation
because it destroys all the
spatial structure of the image.
And it only talks about
the color distributions.
So now if you had red
in the corner versus red
on the other side, they
would-- those two images
would look the same to this
color histogram features,
but they would look very
different from the raw--
on the raw pixel perspective.
So the color histogram
is a one basic
of feature extractor or
feature representation
that you can build on images
that basically looks only
at color and does not look
at spatial structure at all.
Another category of
feature representations
that people used to look at
is the dual to that in which
are these histogram
of oriented gradients.
And I don't think it's useful
to talk too much about exactly
how these are computed.
But the intuition of these is
that they basically throw away
the color information and they
only look at the structure
information.
They basically want to look
for every point in the image
what direction, what
is the local direction
of the edges in the image
around that local region.
So here you can see that this
frog, the leaves of the frog,
it extracts diagonal type of
features because it corresponds
to these diagonal
structures over here
or around the frog's
eyes, you can see it of
captured those spherical--
those circular structures.
So again, it's not super useful
to see how this is computed,
but it's useful
to know that these
are the features that people
would designed for images, maybe
a decade or decade and
a half ago, and people
combined these in
all complicated ways.
So people would often--
you might wonder, oh,
what's the best
feature representation.
The usual answer was just
stack them all together.
So a pretty common
approach would
be to have a bunch of different
feature representations,
extract them all
from your image,
and then concatenate them all
into one big feature vector.
And that's becomes your feature
representation for your image.
And now you could imagine
once we have this feature
representation, we can basically
stick whatever classifier
we want on top of it.
And it's interesting to then
take a step back and contrast
that picture, that viewpoint
of that whole system.
So system A is thinking about
feature extractor plus learned
network or learned
linear classifier
on top of your features.
And then system B is
end-to-end neural networks.
And they actually don't
look that different.
If you take a step back and
think about it in the right way,
both of these systems
are ultimately
inputting the raw
pixels of the image
and outputting some scores or
predictions about the image.
The difference is that--
the difference which
part of the system
is designed by humans,
versus which part is
learned via gradient descent.
In the feature extraction plus
linear classifier paradigm,
the feature extraction
portion of the system
is designed-- that could be
a bunch of really hairy C
code or hairy
Matlab code, and you
don't want to think about
the details of what's
going on inside of that.
And then just the
part that you're
learning via gradient
descent, the part
that you're learning
from your training data,
is just that classifier
on top of the feature
extractor, whereas the neural
network approach is basically
saying gradient
descent is probably
a better programmer than
you, and lots of data
probably knows more about
your problem than you do.
So then the intuition of these
neural network classifiers
is they're still
ultimately going
to be a system that
inputs the raw pixel
values and spits out
your classification
scores at the end.
But the difference
is that all parts
of that system,
from the raw pixels,
all the way to the final
classification scores
will be tuned via
gradient descent
and will be learned from
your training data set.
So the intuition
is that there might
be-- in this feature
extraction paradigm,
there might be some bottlenecks.
You as a human might
get something wrong.
You might have wrong intuition
about what parts of the problem
are important, what
things are not important
or it might be really
hard for you to write down
the perfect feature extractor
that solves your problem,
and this end-to-end learning
approach of ConvNets,
and really of deep
learning more generally,
is just saying that data
and compute can likely
solve that problem better than
you as a human designer can.
And this paradigm
has basically won
over the past decade and a half
for lots and lots of problems
repeatedly.
So that gives an
intuition of-- so then
the question is like for the
particular problem of images,
how should we design
these end-to-end systems.
It's not going to be a fully
connected network all the way.
That would be a
little bit silly.
We do need to still put a little
bit of design into the system.
But the difference about
designing a neural network
versus designing a
feature extractor
is that in designing
a neural network,
you're not designing a
particular function of a feature
extractor.
You're defining a whole
category of functions,
where the category of
functions is defined
by the structure of your
computational graph,
by the sequence of
operators that get run.
But there's a little
bit of-- there's
some flexibility in that
system because you're
leaving the weights of the
system free to be learned
from data.
But the role of the human
designer still matters.
You still need to decide
what is that architecture
of your network.
What is that sequence
of operators that get
stitched into a
computational graph, what
are the sizes of all
the matrices involved
at every stage of processing.
So there still is a lot
of role for the human
to design parts of the problem
in this deep learning era,
but what you're designing
is a little bit different.
So this is basically
where we start
to see the deficiencies
in the tools
that we have so far for
solving this problem.
Because we see that--
we've seen linear layers,
we've seen fully
connected networks.
And the only neural network
architecture that we've seen
is to flatten our pixels of
our image into a big vector,
do matrix multiply, do ReLU,
do more matrix multiply,
do more ReLU.
And that's about it.
That's all we know how
to do at this point.
And one big problem
with that is that it
destroys the spatial
structure of the images.
There's this big problem.
Images are actually not
one dimensional objects.
Images are two dimensional.
They have two
dimensional structure.
That two dimensional structure
matters for the content
of those images.
And when you build a linear
classifier on raw pixels
by stretching it out
into a big vector,
you're basically ignoring that
important factor of your input
data in the design of your
neural network architecture.
So when we think about designing
neural network architectures
for images, in particular, we
want to think what are other--
what are other designs
for our network, what
are other computational
primitives we
can slot into our computational
graphs that better--
that better respect that
two-dimensional structure
of images.
And that leads us to
convolutional networks.
So convolutional
networks are basically
a category of neural
network architectures
that are built of linear layers,
nonlinearities, convolution
layers, pooling layers,
sometimes a couple others
that stitch together
into these neural network
architectures that
input raw pixel values
and then output some prediction
or scores for our images.
And the general
structure of these
is that usually they'll
have some prefix, some body
of the network which is
some interleaved sequence
of convolution layers, pooling
layers and non-linearities that
can be thought of as
extracting some useful feature
representation for the image.
And then on top of
that, they'll usually
be some fully connected layers,
sometimes as few as one,
but sometimes more
than one, which
you can think of as a
multi-layer perceptron
fully connected network
classifier that lives on top of
and ingests the features from
the convolutional portion
of the network.
But crucially, this
whole system is tuned end
to end via gradient descent
by minimizing the loss
on your training data set.
And these networks actually have
quite a bit of long history.
So this image, this particular
ConvNet architecture
that we've drawn on
the screen actually
comes from a paper back in 1998
with Yann LeCun, Leon Bottou
and others who were
at the time building
these convolutional neural
networks all the way back
in 1998 to perform the task
of digit classification.
And it actually
worked pretty well,
but it was really expensive.
They didn't have GPUs,
they didn't have TPUs,
they didn't have the compute
resources that we did today.
But the underlying algorithm,
the underlying network
architecture, basically
looks pretty similar in 1998
to what things were--
to the architectures that people
were using well into the 2010s.
And then zooming forward
from 1998 up until 2012,
that's when the AlexNet
architecture came out.
And this was a big boom,
like giant explosion
of deep learning, especially
in computer vision.
And I think we talked about
this in some earlier lectures.
But the AlexNet
architecture, again
doesn't look that different
from this Yann LeCun,
LeNet architecture from 1988.
It's a bunch of convolutional
layers, fully connected layers.
It's bigger,
there's more layers.
The layers have
more units in them,
but it's still trained end
to end with backpropagation
to minimize some fairly
simple loss functions.
But here, like AlexNet,
was when really things
started to take off.
And at this time, they
were able to train on GPUs.
GPUs were available.
There was more data available
because of internet,
because of ImageNet.
So AlexNet is when things
really started to take off.
So then the era from, I think,
about 2012 to around 2020-ish
was an era where convolutional
networks were basically
dominating almost every
problem in computer vision.
They were solved basically
anything you-- any a problem
that you wanted to do
with an image in that era,
it was almost certainly going to
be a ConvNet that had the best
performance on that problem.
So this included
tasks like detection
on the left, which is the
task of not just classifying
an image, but drawing
a box around all
the objects in the image
and putting a category
label on the box.
Segmentation is the
task of assigning labels
not at the box level
or the image level,
but instead assigning
labels at the pixel level.
So now we want to assign a
category label to every pixel
independently in our image.
And we'll talk more about
architectures for these problems
in future lectures.
But these can be
solved very effectively
using convolutional networks.
People used ConvNets for other
problems involving language
as well.
So the task of image
captioning, where
we want to predict a natural
language caption from an image.
Some of the first widely
successful approaches
to this problem also were built
on convolutional networks.
And then even for
some more recent tasks
of generative modeling.
So text to image--
sorry, captioning is basically
the problem of image to text,
where we input an
image and then want
to output a natural language
sentence describing the image.
We can also think about the
inverse problem of text to image
generation, where we want
to input a natural language
description of something that
we're imagining in our head,
and have the system generate
a new image from scratch that
hopefully matches our
input description and some
of the really-- some of the
first really widely successful--
widely successful
versions of this problem
also were built on
convolutional networks.
So this particular figure is
from the Stable Diffusion paper
that came out back in 2021.
And this has got--
this technology
has gotten a lot better in
the last couple of years.
And we'll talk more about
that in some later lectures.
But it's useful to point
out that this basically--
the first versions of this that
started to work really well
were also built on
convolutional networks.
So basically,
convolutional networks
were so important for this
history of computer vision
that the initial version of
this class that we started
way back in 2015
was actually called
convolutional neural networks
for visual recognition,
because at the time,
convolutional networks was
basically synonymous
with computer vision.
And computer vision
was basically
the biggest field that
was benefiting from deep
learning at that time.
So in setting out to teach
a class about deep learning,
it actually made a lot of
sense to focus entirely
on the problem of convolutional
networks for image problems.
And that's basically
the inception
of this class 10 years ago.
But the field has actually
evolved a lot since then.
Convolutional networks have
actually gotten replaced.
Visual recognition,
there's a lot
of other interesting problems
that we can solve now.
So you'll notice that
the name of the class
changed at some point along
the way and to no longer focus
so specifically on neural--
convolutional networks.
And the reason
for that is that I
said this was the era
from 2012 to 2020.
You might be wondering
what happened
in 2020 other than COVID
that could have displaced
convolutional networks.
It wasn't COVID, it
was transformers.
So transformers are this
alternate neural network
architecture that we'll talk
about in a couple more lectures.
But basically, they started off
in natural language processing
for processing documents,
for processing text strings.
And the transformer architecture
got first published in 2017.
And for a couple of
years after that,
it mainly stayed in the
regime of processing text,
but there was a really
important paper in 2021
that basically applied nearly
the exact same transformer
architecture that had been
getting used to process text,
to process strings,
and instead used it
to process images in
nearly the exact same way.
And since then,
people have found
that for a lot of the
previous problems that we just
talked about that
were previously
solved using
convolutional networks,
you could replace the
CNN with a transformer,
keep everything else the
same and the problem--
and you tend to get better
performance on these problems.
They scale up to more data,
they scale up to more compute.
And this is-- we can get more
data, we can get more compute.
So these are much more commonly
used for more and more computer
vision problems these days.
And we'll talk much more about
transformers in lecture 8,
but I thought it would be
weird to be pitching ConvNets
super hard when actually
they don't get used quite as
much nowadays as they
did maybe five years ago.
But I still think
it's really useful
to talk about
convolutional networks one,
because there is a lot of
historical significance, two,
these algorithms still do get
used quite a lot in practice.
Three, it helps you build
intuitions about what's
important for images
and four, they're
actually not completely dead.
A lot of times we're actually
building hybrid systems.
Sometimes we use convolution,
sometimes we use transformers,
sometimes we mix them
together in various ways.
So it's actually super useful
to still know about this stuff.
So then basically,
the rest of today
we're going to talk more
about convolutional networks.
We said that-- we said that a
convolutional network is just
a computational graph
for processing images.
That's built from a couple
of different primitives.
We've already met the
fully connected layer
and the activation function.
So we basically need to
walk through these two more
layers of the convolution
layer and the pooling layer.
Quick recap of the
fully connected layer.
This is what we've already
talked about in the context
of linear classifiers.
So with our fully
connected layer,
like we said,
basically what we do
is we take our
pixels of our image.
Our image is this three
dimensional tensor 32 by 32
by 3, 32 by 32 are these
two spatial dimensions.
Three, are three channel
dimensions for your RGB colors.
So we take that 32
by 32 by 3 vector.
You stretch it out into
a long vector of 3072,
because that's if you multiply
those in your head, that's
the number you get.
And then you have this basically
this vector of 3072 numbers.
We have a weight
matrix that's 3072
by 10, in this case, because 10
is the number of output classes
that we want.
You do a matrix vector,
multiply between those two.
You end up with a vector
of 10 numbers giving us
our class score.
And in particular, it's
interested-- in trying
to generalize this from
fully connected layers
to convolutional layers, it's
useful to think a little bit
more about the structure of what
this fully connected layer is
doing that fully connected
layer, the output vector,
contains 10 elements,
each one of those elements
is a single number.
Each one of those
numbers is predicted
by computing an inner
product between one
of the rows of your weight
matrix and the entire input
vector.
But each entry you
should basically
think of as a dot
product and a dot product
you should basically think
about it as a template match.
Because the dot
product between two
vectors is high when the two
vectors point the same way,
and it's 0 when the two
vectors are orthogonal.
So anything built
on dot products
is basically a
template matching.
So the way that you should think
about these fully connected
layers is that we have a set of
templates, each of the templates
has the same size as our input.
And then the output is the
template matching score
between each one of our
templates and the entire input.
So then once we think
about it that way,
there's actually a nice
way we can generalize
this from fully connected layers
into convolutional layers.
And that's by saying
we're still going
to have this notion
of template matching.
We're still going
to have this notion
of learning a bank of filters.
But what we're going to change
is that those filters will--
those templates
are no longer going
to have the same
shape as the input.
Instead, now our now
our filters will have
a-- will only look at a
small subset of the input.
So more concretely, rather
than stretching out our image
into a big vector of
3072 numbers, instead,
we're going to maintain the 3D
spatial structure of our image.
It's going to now be a
three-dimensional tensor
of three channels, sometimes
called depth or channels
dimension, 32 width, 32 height.
And now one of our
filters is going
to be a tiny little sub-image
a tiny low resolution image,
in this case a 5
by 5 pixel image.
And importantly,
that small filter
needs to have three channels.
The channels are always
going to span the same
as the number of
channels in the input,
but the spatial size
will be smaller.
And now what we're
going to do is
we're going to
compute dot products.
We think about that small
filter as a little chunk
of image template.
And we're going to slide it
everywhere across the image
and say for every
point in the image, how
much does that sub partial--
sub part of the image
match this template
that we're learning in
our convolutional filter.
So we'll plop that
convolutional filter down
at some chunk of the image.
That 5 by 5 by 3 filter will
line up with some 5 by 5
by 3 chunk of the image at that
spatial location will compute
an inner product
between those two,
and that will give us
one single scalar number,
telling us how much does
that chunk of the image align
with our template.
And now we'll repeat that
process and slide that template
everywhere in our image.
And every place that we plop
down that template, it'll
give us-- we'll again compute
this template matching score
that says, how much does
that piece of the image align
with that one template.
And as we slide that filter
everywhere on the input image,
we're going to collect
all of those scores, all
of those template matching
scores into a plane.
And that plane will now
be a two dimensional--
a two-dimensional plane
that says basically
for every point-- in every
point in the plane now
corresponds to how much did that
corresponding piece of the input
image align with our filter.
But of course, this
is deep learning.
We want a lot of compute.
And how do we get more compute?
We have more filters.
So now we'll add a
second filter and we'll
say rather-- we'll repeat
the whole process again
with another filter.
So we'll have-- we're going
to go-- we have a 5 by 5
by 3 filter that
we colored in blue.
Now let's imagine
a second filter
that's now colored in green.
Our second filter will
still be 5 by 5 by 3.
And we'll repeat the
exact same procedure
of sliding that green filter
everywhere on the image,
compute template matching
scores between the green filter
and little sub
pieces of the image,
and then collect all of those
scores in a second plane,
telling us for every point
in the image, how much did
it respond to the green filter.
And now we can basically iterate
this and add as many filters
as we want.
So then in this
case, we are drawing
six filters, each of them is
going to be 3 by 5 by 5 or 3
by--
3 by 5 by 5.
So then we can actually
collect all of those filters
into a single
four-dimensional tensor.
So that four-dimensional
tensor now has 6
is a leading dimension
because we have six filters.
And then that 3 by 5 by 5
is that image template is
that chunk, is that template
that we're learning.
And now the convolution layer
basically takes as input
our three-dimensional input--
our three-dimensional image
and our four-dimensional bank of
filters, slides, the slides, all
the filters everywhere
on the image
and gives us these
response planes.
So then once we collect
all those response planes
and stack them up in
a third dimension,
then our output has size 6
by 28 by 28, where 28 by 28
should be interpreted
as spatial dimensions,
and that 6 is a
channel dimension.
And of course, we'll also--
just as we do with
linear layers,
we'll often add a learnable
bias vector as well
to our convolutional layers, so
that then in that sense, it's--
in a linear layer,
a bias is one scalar
per row in the linear layer.
Correspondingly, in a
convolutional layer,
we'll have typically
one scalar bias value
for every filter in our
convolutional-- for every one
of our convolutional filters.
So that means that we'll
have a six dimensional bias
vector in this setting.
Yeah, the question
was clarifying
3 is the RGB channels.
Yeah, that's correct.
Question is how do
you get the filters.
That's the miracle of gradient
descent and backpropagation.
So the idea is that we're
defining this operator.
This operator is
going to have an input
image and a set of filters.
But no human is
going to define what
those filters are going to be.
Instead, we're going to
initialize those filters
randomly.
And then they will be learned
via gradient descent on whatever
problem you're trying to solve.
So that's actually a really
important thing to keep in mind.
And that gives these
layers their power
is that we're defining
this fairly computationally
expensive layer,
but we're expecting
that it'll be filled in with
the data from-- with the data
and compute from our training.
Question is, how do
you set the five.
That's a hyperparameter.
So we talked about
hyperparameters
and cross-validation a
couple of lectures ago.
So these would be
architectural hyperparameters
that you would typically set via
cross-validation in some way.
Yeah, good question.
Does it make sense to have
different sizes of filters?
So as we'll see in the
CNN architectures lecture
next lecture--
actually I think you're going
to talk about inception.
Sometimes you
actually do have that.
But that typically
happens at the--
there's kind of a nice
API design problem
when you're designing what is a
primitive in your computational
graph versus what is going to be
an emergent structure built out
of primitives.
So in this case,
we usually define
a single convolutional layer
as having a fixed filter size,
because that makes it
easier to compute and write
efficient GPU kernels.
But if you can effectively have
multiple multiply size filters
by stitching together
a computational graph
that combines convolution layers
with different filter sizes
in a larger network structure.
So it's yes and no is the
answer to your question.
The question is,
what are we learning.
And this is very important to
distinguish between a parameter
versus a hyperparameter.
So a hyperparameter is
something that we set before we
start training the network.
So in this case, one
of the hyperparameters
would be the number of filters
and the size of those filters.
Because those set the
shapes of our tensor.
So then in a
parameter is a value
that we're going
to set and optimize
over the course of
gradient descent.
So in this case, the number of
filters, the number of output
channels, the size
of those filters,
those will be hyperparameters.
We set those once before
we start training.
At the beginning of
training, we'll randomly
initialize the filters and
then the value and-- that
will give us a fixed
shape-- fixed size tensor.
And then the values
inside of that tensor
will float around and change
over the course of optimization.
So that's the--
so then those are
parameters because they
get set via gradient--
via gradient descent.
Yes, the question is what
gradient are we computing.
Whenever you do
backpropagation you're
always computing gradient
of the loss with respect
to things inside the network.
So in this case, we'll be
computing gradient of the loss
with respect to the individual
scalar-- with respect
to our convolutional
filter weights.
So that's basically saying
what is a gradient that's
saying for every
individual scalar
inside of every
one of our filters,
if we wiggle that scalar a
little bit, then how much is
the loss going to change.
So then the gradient of
the loss with respect--
we're always computing gradient
of the loss with respect
to our convolutional filters.
The question is basically like,
what do we do with the bias.
So basically, the
bias would be added
to each of our inner products.
So then we'll always compute
like inner product of one
of our filters against
a chunk of the image
and then add the corresponding
scalar from the bias.
The bias is a vector, but the
number of entries in the vector
is equal to the
number of filters.
So then each entry in the
bias gets basically broadcast
across the entire spatial
dimension in the output.
But each bias only
gets used for--
one bias gets used
for one filter.
So conceptually you basically
one filter you slide everywhere.
That gives us a two-dimensional
plane of activations.
And then if you have
a second filter,
you get a second
plane of activations.
Those are independent operators.
Like step one slide
first filter everywhere.
Step two slide the
second filter everywhere.
Every filter gives rise
to a plane, a plane
that we call an activation map.
And then we stack
all of those up.
And that's the operation
of the convolution layer.
The question is yeah, basically
after every gradient descent--
every time we do
gradient descent,
it's going to
change the filters.
So whenever you imagine a
training a neural network,
it's always this loop of like
while true, get a batch of data,
send your data
through the network,
forward pass, compute
loss, backward pass,
compute gradient
with respect to loss
and now make a gradient
step using your optimizer.
So then it's always going
to be data, forward,
loss, backward step.
And then every
time you do a step,
it's going to make a
change to the filters.
All right.
So I swung the other way
I said more questions
I got too many questions.
But that's good.
We'll equalize in here.
So then we talked about
the convolution layer.
It's actually pretty common
in the convolution layer
to work on it in a batch mode.
So rather than working
on one input image,
we'll actually work on
a batch of input images.
So this is nice because it makes
everything four dimensional.
Now we have a
four-dimensional tensor
of inputs, which is a
set of input images.
We have a
four-dimensional tensor
of filters which is a set
of filters, each of which
is a three dimensional
chunk of an image.
And then the output is
a four dimensional--
is a four-dimensional tensor,
which is a set of outputs.
Each output one output
per image, each image
is output is a
three-dimensional tensor, giving
a stack of feature planes.
You have to start to think
in lots of dimensions
when you start to
build neural networks,
and that's actually fun.
So then here's the
general formulation
of a convolution layer.
Is that in general,
you're going to take
as input a four-dimensional
tensor of n by cn by h
by w, which is a
set of n images.
Each of those n images
has seen cn channels.
For the case of an RGB
image, that'll be 3,
but we might in general have
more than three channels.
This could be arbitrary.
And then h and w is the spatial
size of our input images.
Our convolutional filters will
be a four dimensional tensor
of shape c out by
cn by kw by kh.
C out is the number of filters,
the number of output channels,
cn is-- and then
the rest of that
are three dimensional filters.
So it's a set of
three-dimensional filters.
Each three dimensional filter
has shape cn by kw by kh.
That's the kernel width
and kernel height.
And then we have
c out such filters
that get collected into a
four-dimensional tensor.
And then as output, we're going
to produce a four dimensional
tensor again, where the shape
is n for the number of images
one output per image, c
out-- each of those outputs
is going to consist of c out
feature planes one per filter.
And then each of those planes is
going to be h prime by w prime.
And this is the general
formulation of a conv layer.
And then a convolutional
network is just
a network that is just a
computational graph that
includes a bunch of conv layers.
So in practice, we'll
tend to stack up
a bunch of convolutional
operators one after another.
And in stacking a bunch of
convolutional operators,
that will be a
convolutional network.
So this is a simple ConvNet.
You start with an image
that's 3 by 32 by 32,
then we have a conv layer
that has six filters.
Each filter is 5 by 5 by 3.
Then after we do the first
convolution, that gives us
a new three dimensional set of
activations for that one image,
where we have six channels that
matches the six filters, 28
by 28, because the
spatial size changed
a little bit through
the convolution,
then we have another
convolution that
now has 10 filters, each
of which is 5 by 5 by 6.
So the 10 is going to
give us the output--
the output dimensions and the
next layer of convolution.
And this 6 is going to
be the number of channels
that needs to match up
the channel dimension here
of the input to the convolution.
So you can see
you can just stack
a bunch of these
convolution layers
and perform a lot
of computation.
But there's actually a problem
in exactly this network
architecture design.
And can anybody spot it?
That's sizing.
That's a problem, not
the one I had in mind.
Evolutions are local.
That's another good problem,
not the one I had in mind.
Actually, those two will be able
to fix pretty easily in a couple
slides, but I had a
different problem in mind.
A lot of memory that is a
problem, but not one we can fix.
You just got to
buy a bigger GPU.
Number of filters increases.
I don't think that's
a problem necessarily.
That's OK.
Everything's linear.
Yes, that is a problem.
So we said that convolution
was dot products.
Dot product is a
linear operator.
Composition of two
linear operators
is still a linear operator.
So that means that if we have
two convolution layers stacked
directly on top of each
other, they actually
have the same representational
power as a single convolution
layer, because of the
linearity of the operator.
There's actually a very
simple fix to that.
Add an activation function.
Exactly.
So it's the same--
actually the same bug
that we saw in multi-layer
neural networks
and the same fix.
We need to add a nonlinear
activation function
in between our
convolutional layers
if we want-- this
introduces non-linearity
to the problem, non-linearity
to the network architecture,
and increases the
representational power
of the network that
we're learning.
So in general,
ConvNets are going
to be some stack of convolution
layers, nonlinearities
and other kinds of layers
in our computational graph.
There was a question
earlier about what
do the convolutional
filters learn.
This is basically--
we can view this
by analogy with what we already
did in linear classifiers.
So in linear classifiers,
we have this intuition
where each row could
be visualized--
each row of the
learned weight matrix
could be thought of
as a template that
has the same shape as
the whole input image.
Now, with a
convolutional filter,
you can think of it the same
way, but now each filter,
rather than extending over the
entire spatial size of the input
image, is going to be
just a small sub piece,
a sub chunk of an image.
So we can actually
visualize the first--
we can actually visualize the
first layer convolution filters
of a trained neural network.
So these are the first
layer convolution filters
that are learned by an
AlexNet architecture that
was trained for image
classification on ImageNet.
And here each of
these are basically
little chunks of RGB images.
These are the little
templates that
get slid around the input
image in the first layer
of the AlexNet architecture.
And the fact that this was
AlexNet, the fact that this
was trained on
ImageNet, the fact
that this was classification,
it turns out just
about all convolutional
networks end up
learning filters
that look something
like this on almost all problems
and almost all data sets
and tasks, as long as
they're reasonable tasks.
And the thing we see
is that we often learn
two kinds of filters in here.
One tends to be
looking for colors,
especially opposing colors.
So you'll see this
one is looking
for a contrast
between green and red.
We also see colored blobs
like pink and green blobs.
And the other category
of filter we tend to see
are looking for somehow the
spatial structure of the images.
So like this one is looking
for a vertical edge,
a horizontal edge.
This one is looking for a
vertical edge, some of these
are looking for diagonal edges.
So they tend to look
for colors and edges.
And in these little
local neighborhoods
of our input images.
So we can play this
trick on the first layer
of the convolutional filter and
just visualize them directly
as images.
It gets a little bit trickier
to visualize the higher
layers in the network.
And I'm not going to
explain this figure.
I'm just going to present it
without too much explanation.
But higher layers
of the network tend
to learn larger spatial
structures of our input image.
Here, the visualization is
like each row represents
a filter in a learned
network, and each column
represents some piece
of an input image
that filter was
responding strongly to.
So the visualization
here is a bit
different than the
previous slide.
So these are all basically
chunks of input images
that a filter was responding to.
And here you can see that
this six layer convolution
one of these filters feels like
it's responding maybe to eyes.
This one looks like maybe it's
responding to pieces of text.
responding to wheels or circles
or top halves of circles.
Something like that.
And again, this all gets
driven via gradient descent
via training on your large scale
data sets via gradient descent.
Nobody's sitting down and
designing these filters by hand.
And like I said, visualizing
these higher layer filters
is a bit tricky
and more involved.
Question was if you look at all
the responses to the filters,
can you reconstruct
the original image?
Actually, it turns
out you can do that.
And the trick and the
way that you do that
is also gradient descent.
Gradient descent
is really powerful.
And that's something that we'll
talk about, I think, in a couple
more lectures on some
mechanisms that do that.
Oh, that's a good question.
How do the filters
get differentiated.
That actually comes down to
the random initialization.
So then it's really important
that the way you initialize
your filters is random.
And crucially, that you have
a different initialization
for each filter when you
start training your network,
because that's going
to break the symmetry
between the filters.
Because if all the filters
are exactly the same,
the loss is the same,
then that gradient
is going to broadcast back and
be the same on all the filters.
So if you initialize them the
same, they will stay the same.
But if you initialize
them to be different,
then you'll break
the symmetry and they
can learn different features.
Yeah.
Basically, the human
designer of the network
needs to write down what is
the sequence of operators
and the sequence of channels.
And that's the question of
neural network architecture
design that we'll talk
a little bit more about
in the next lecture.
Third question is, why
is it the deeper layers
visualize larger structures
that actually has a bit
to do with the receptive
fields that we have
a slide on in a little bit.
So maybe we'll get there.
And I think a couple--
some of these questions
will get answered.
So one thing that
already came up
is how do we look at
the spatial dimensions
of these convolutions.
So I wanted to take
a look-- a closer
look at exactly how we
compute the spatial dimensions
of convolutions.
So in this case
here, we've taken
this picture of-- this
picture of a convolution.
We're rotating it 90 degrees and
dropping the channel dimension.
So now the channel dimension
is going into the board.
And then we have our 7
by 7 spatial dimensions.
So here we're
looking at an input
that's 7 by 7 in spatial size.
And we have a 3
by 3 conv kernel.
And then the
question is, how big
is our output going to be here?
Well, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
So our output is
going to be 5 by 5
because we can slide that
filter and plop it down
in 5 different spaces.
And then we can generalize it.
If our input has length w,
our conv filter has length k,
then our output is going
to be w minus k plus 1.
And you can sit down
and convince yourself
that that's the right formula.
But there's a problem that
actually a couple of people
already pointed out is
that your feature maps are
going to shrink in
spatial size as you
go through this convolution.
And that's annoying.
It's actually-- like you
could actually work with that.
And there are some neural
network architectures
that deal with that.
But sometimes we're
lazy and we just
want to keep the same size for
everything, because that's just
basically simpler for human
designers to think about.
And one trick that we do there
is something called padding.
So here it's common to
add additional data,
like virtual data
around the input--
around your true input
data, that you're
going to basically
add extra zeros around
before you compute the
convolution operator.
And now this basically lets us
solve this shrinking feature map
problem.
Because now if we have--
add padding of p, in this case,
we have padding p equals 1.
So we're adding one pixel of
zeros all around everywhere,
then we basically add
2p to our output size.
So in particular, if you have
a 3-- if you have a 3 by 3 conv
and you add padding of
1, then your feature map
is going to stay the same size.
And that's convenient.
Now, if you've taken
signal processing
there actually are
some problems here.
This can lead to weird weirdness
from a signal processing
perspective, but
we'll ignore that
and we'll just look at the
sizes and shapes of the tensors
because that's a little
bit easier to comprehend.
But be aware like why
are we putting zeros.
Is that going to cause problems?
Yes, it is going to cause
problems on the borders,
but it seems to be
in a lot of cases.
OK.
Yeah.
So then like I said, a pretty
common setting is to set p
is to have actually
k be an odd number
and then have p be
k minus 1 over 2
because that's going to
mean that your spatial size
after convolution is the
same as the spatial size
before the convolution.
Then the next interesting
thing to think about
is this notion of
receptive fields.
Someone was asking a
little bit over here
why do the deeper layers
learn larger structures.
That's actually inherent in the
way that convolutions are built.
So in thinking about
a single convolution,
each output is looking at
this local region of an input.
So by design, the output of one
convolution at the first layer
can only be looking at a
piece of the image, which
is the same size as the
convolutional kernel
that you're learning.
But if we build a ConvNet that's
stacking multiple convolutions
on top of each other, then
these receptive fields
get magnified
through the network.
So then in this case,
we're looking at a network
with three convolution layers.
And we see that in the
final layer of activations.
Each entry here depends on
a local region in the layer
before it.
But each one of
those entries depends
in turn on a local region
in the layer before it,
which depends in turn on a local
region in the layer before it.
So when you have
these convolutions,
even though each individual
convolution is looking
at a local neighborhood
in the layer
before it, as you
stack up convolutions
in a bunch of layers,
then the effective size
of the original input that
each of those convolutions
is looking at grows over
the course of the network.
And in particular this--
we call the effective
receptive field.
So the effective receptive
field of a convolution
is basically how many
pixels in the original image
had the opportunity to influence
one activation of the network
later on downstream.
And you'll notice that
the convolution actually--
this effective receptive
field basically
grows linearly with the
number of convolution layers.
And there's a potential problem
here is because ultimately when
we make classification decisions
at the end of our network,
we would like our classification
decisions to basically
aggregate global information
across the entire image.
But you need a lot of
conv layers to do it.
So a trick there is
basically to add some way
to increase effective
receptive fields more quickly.
One way that we can
do this in convolution
is by introducing
something called a stride.
So here what we're
saying is that rather
than placing the filter
everywhere in the image,
we're going to skip some.
So we're going to instead
of moving the field--
moving the receptive
field with one,
we're going to stride
it by 2 instead.
So now in this case, we go back
to our 7 by 7 input, 3 by 3 conv
do a stride 2.
Now, what's the output size.
1, 2, 3.
3 by 3.
And then in general,
if we have our input w
filter size k
padding of p stride
s, then we get this ugly formula
for the size of the output
w minus k.
The bigger kernels shrink the
input plus 2P padding adds back
some of the missing size
divided by the stride.
The stride, divides the
input shape and then
plus 1 because that's how--
because of some fence post math.
OK, so then the
strided convolutions
are interesting because if
you go back to this picture,
now when we do a
strided convolution,
it's effectively
downsampling the image
inside the neural network.
So then when we have
strided convolution,
then each conv
layer is effectively
like dividing the shape of
the feature map, usually by 2.
And then when we
stack these, that
means that now you can
get exponential growth
in the effective
receptive field.
So if you stack a bunch
of conv layers in each
of those conv layers is actually
downsampling by a factor of 2,
then if you run through
a similar exercise,
you'll see that the effective
receptive field is now
growing exponentially in
the depth of the network.
So that means that with
relatively few layers,
we can build up a very large,
effective receptive field that
looks at the entire input image.
So here, let's work
through just one example
to make sure that we all are on
the same page about convolution.
So here, let's think about an
input volume 3 by 32 by 32.
Let's think about a convolution
layer with 10 filters,
each of those filters is 5
by 5 with stride 1 pad two.
What's the size of the output?
I color coded it because
there's a lot of numbers
here to keep track of.
So here, it's 10 by 32 by 32.
This 32 is actually a
different 32 than this 32.
So that's why they're
different colors of blue.
But this 10 is the number
of output channels.
Output channels has to
match the number of filters.
And the spatial size is computed
using that formula that we just
saw.
So then the input spatial
size comes down here plus 2--
plus the padding
comes down here.
Padding adds the spatial size, 5
is the convolutional kernel that
divides the spatial
size, stride of 1.
So that's trivial
and then add one.
And this just so happens
to come out to 32.
So in this case, this
follows the same pattern
that we talked about
a couple slides ago
where it's an odd shaped
convolutional kernel.
In this case five.
The padding is two.
So if the kernel
size is 2k plus 1,
then padding of k means we
maintain the same spatial size.
Number of learnable
parameters here.
Maybe I'll just go through these
because we have a couple more
slides to get through.
So here in this case, the
number of learnable parameters
is 760 because we have each
filter is basically a 3 by 5
by 5.
And we have one for the bias.
So we have 76 learnable
parameters per filter.
We have 10 filters.
So it's 760 multiple--
760 learnable parameters here.
We can also compute the number
of multiply add operations.
How much compute does
this convolution kernel,
how much compute does this
convolution operator take.
So here it's a lot.
Well, is it a lot?
I don't know.
I don't have a lot--
you may or may not
have a lot of intuition for
what is a lot of computation.
But in this case, the way
that I think about computing,
how many flops, how much compute
does a convolution operator
take, we think about
what the output volume
size is 10 by 32 by 32.
And we know that each
entry in that output volume
was computed via dot product,
a dot product in particular
between one of our filters
and a chunk of our input.
So in this case, we know the
total flops because we know
the number of outputs is 10 by
32 by 32, which is about 10,000.
And then each of
those outputs is
computed via dot product of a
3 by 5 by 5 filter and a 3 by 5
by 5 chunk of the image.
So that's 75 elements.
So multiplying those together
means it takes about 768,000
floating point multiply
add operations.
OK, so then here's
the one line--
one slide summary
of convolution.
I'm not going to
walk through this.
This is more for you
to look at later.
But this just summarizes
all the hyperparameters
and the formulas associated
with convolution layers.
If you look in PyTorch, PyTorch
is the deep learning framework
that a lot of people use.
You'll see this
convolution layer
has all these hyperparameters
that we talked about.
There's a couple other
interesting hyperparameters
that we didn't talk about
called groups and dilation.
Dilation isn't really
used so much anymore.
Groups still get used sometimes.
But maybe we'll talk about
those in a later lecture.
You can have other kind of
other kinds of convolutions too.
So we talked about
2D convolution.
We can also do 1D convolution,
where rather than having
a two-dimensional signal
that we slide a filter over,
we now have a one dimensional
signal that we slide a filter
over in with one
degree of freedom,
or a three-dimensional
convolution,
where we have a
three-dimensional signal,
a three-dimensional filter, and
now you can slide that filter
everywhere in 3D space to
convolve with the input signal.
So this idea of a
convolution really
extends beyond just
two dimensional two
dimensional images.
OK.
That's basically all
about convolution.
And the last one is pooling.
Thankfully, pooling
is pretty simple.
So pooling layers are basically
another way to downsample inside
of your neural network.
So we saw that
strided convolution
is one way that we
can downsample inside
of a neural network.
And downsampling is useful
because it lets us build up
receptive fields
more quickly as we
go through the depth
of the network.
But convolution
actually still costs
quite a lot of computation.
So convolution is where most of
the flops, most of the compute
happens in a
convolutional network.
And pooling layers
are basically a way
to downsample that's
very, very cheap.
That doesn't cost
a lot of compute.
And the idea in a
pooling layer is
given our three-dimensional
tensor, where in this case 64
by 112 by 112.
You should think about
that as a spatial--
like a three-dimensional
volume of features
where the spatial
size is 112 by 112,
and we have 64 planes, 64
channels of activation.
So now what we're going to--
and each one of those planes
is a 112 by 112 image.
But then what we're
going to do is
take each one of those
individual feature planes,
pull it out from
our input tensor
and downsample them
independently, and then restack
them to compute the output.
So then this input
64 by 224 by 224,
we're going to pull out each
of those 224 by 224 planes,
independently
downsample it and then
restack them to give a
same number of channels,
but change in the spatial size.
What is the method we
use for downsampling?
Great question.
So the way-- that's
actually hyperparameter
there's a couple
different mechanisms
of downsampling that we use.
One of the common ones-- one
of the most common ones to use
is actually max-- is
called max pooling.
So in Max pooling
what we're going
to do is take our
single depth slice,
divide it up into
non-overlapping regions.
In this case, these are two--
and we often use-- and we
use the same terminology
to talk about these as
we do with convolution.
So this way this
we could say it's
a kernel size 2 by
2 with stride of two
because that then that
divides our inputs
into these non-overlapping
2 by 2 tiles.
Then within each of those
non-overlapping 2 by 2 tiles,
we'll take the max entry.
In this case, it's a 6, 8, 3, 4.
So then you take the max
entry inside each of those
and then that-- and
then that gives us
our spatial compression.
And there's a whole-- you
can imagine a whole set
of hyperparameters here.
You could say, what
is the kernel size.
You could change
the kernel size.
You can change the stride.
You can also change the function
that we use for downsampling.
Max pooling is pretty common.
You'll also see average.
You'll also see anti-aliased
down pooling sometimes.
So these are all just ways that
you can downsample these feature
maps one at a time.
Good question.
Do we make a use of padding.
Typically you do not use padding
inside of pooling layers.
There's nothing mathematically
preventing you from doing so.
But in the case of max
pooling, it would be silly.
It's basically
equivalent to a ReLU.
And so whenever you're
using max pooling,
if you're also using a ReLU
that would be redundant.
So typically, we don't use
padding in pooling layers.
I'm actually not
sure if PyTorch has
a flag for pooling-- for padding
or not in pooling layers.
Yeah.
So the stride would
be another one
of these architectural
hyperparameters.
But usually don't tune
these things too much.
Usually, the intuition
behind pooling layer--
like honestly the
most common is I
want to downsample my I want
to downsample everything
by a factor of 2 is by far
the most common operation.
So then the most common thing
to do would be 2 by 2 stride 2.
Sometimes you'll do
like 4 by 4 stride 2.
But basically, the most
common settings by far
is I want to downsample
my everything
by a factor of exactly two.
Oh, that's a very good question.
Do images all have to
be the same input size.
In all the language that we're
talking about so far, yes.
You're going to run
into big problems
if your input images
are not the same size.
So then things that
you'll typically
do to fix that would be one, you
either resize all your images
to the exact same
size before you batch
them to feed to the network.
Sometimes you'll also
pad your images out
with zeros or some
other value to make
them all the same signs but
now padded rather than warped.
Or you need to basically
run these layers
independently for images
of different aspect ratios.
So that's another thing
that you'll do sometimes
in more sophisticated
training setups,
is that sometimes you'll do
what's known as aspect ratio
bucketing.
So then from your
training data, you'll
bucket them into
different aspect ratios.
And then each
forward or backward
pass the network will
be on a batch of images
of the same resolution
and aspect ratio.
But then each iteration,
you might grab images
with different resolutions
or aspect ratios,
or that's something
that you'll see
in some of the more common,
larger production systems.
Yeah.
So the question is,
where do you put these.
These are usually interspersed
with the convolution layers.
So a pretty common
architecture--
a pretty common
pattern for ConvNets
is to intersperse the
convolution and pooling.
So for example, you'll
see com com pool,
com com pool, com com pool
fully connected, fully connected
is a prototypical
convolutional network.
Yeah, that's an
excellent question.
Does this introduce
non-linearity.
So it depends on the
type of pooling operation
that you're using.
So if you're doing max pooling
that's a non-linearity.
So in some networks, if
you have a max pooling,
you may not use a ReLU
around that convolution
because a max pooling is
a non-linearity itself.
If it's an average pooling
that's also a linear operator.
So then if you do average
pooling it's linear.
So then you probably still
would want a ReLU there.
OK.
So then here's my
quick one-slide summary
of pooling is basically the same
hyperparameters as convolution.
Except you've got this extra
pooling function, which
is what is the mechanism you're
using to do the downsampling.
Then the last thing
I wanted to mention
is this notion of
translation equivariance.
What the hell is that?
So I said at the beginning of
the-- beginning of the lecture
that we wanted
operators that are
respecting the spatial
structure of our images.
And that we had this notion
that flattening our images
into big vectors is somehow not
respecting the spatial structure
of our images.
So there's a really interesting
property that is shared by both
convolution and pooling, which
is one way to formalize this
notion of them respecting the 2D
spatial structure of the images.
And that's this notion of
translation equivariance.
So it sounds like-- it
sounds pretty crazy,
but the idea is we can imagine
two different operators, two
different branches.
Along one branch, we can
imagine taking our image,
doing a convolution
or pooling operator
to get an updated image, and
then translating the result
by shifting that feature map
to the side by, for example.
Then you could imagine changing
the order of these two things
instead.
What we could have done instead
is first translate the image
and then do our convolution
or pool operator
on top of the translated image.
And it just so happens
that in this case,
the order doesn't matter if you
translate and then convolution,
you get the same result as
if you had done convolution
and then translate subject to
some boundary conditions, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
But like in the limit of
infinitely large images
and blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah,
ignoring some of these
technical conditions,
it's really interesting
that you can actually
swap the order of
translation in space
versus performing these
downsampling or convolution
operators.
And that bakes in an
important intuition
about images, which is that
when we're processing images,
the features that we
extract from an image
should only depend on
the content of the image
and should not depend on where
in the image that-- where
the absolute location in the
image that content came from.
So that means that if
I'm looking this way,
it looks like people--
it looks like
people and benches.
If I'm looking this way, it
looks like people in benches.
And the fact that it's over
here on my right and the fact
that it's over
here on my left, I
want to process that data
in the exact same way.
And that's an
important intuition,
an important structure that we
want to of images and of the 2D
data that we're processing.
And this notion of
translation, equivariance
basically is a way to
mathematically describe
how that structure is
baked into these operators.
So this is interesting
that it's a way
that we can build
in our intuition
about how images
ought to be processed
through the design
of our operators,
not through the design of our
feature extraction methods,
as we saw at the beginning.
The question is, why do
you do your translation.
You.
Don't This is not something
you're actually going to do.
This is basically a
mathematical curiosity.
To be clear that you
should not generally
do this inside of
your neural networks.
This is basically like it's
interesting to note that this
happens to be true,
but you would not
do this inside of
your neural networks.
And if you're a
mathematician, you
call this a commutative diagram.
And mathematicians
love those things.
So that's basically
the summary of today.
We talked about
convolutional networks.
We talked about why
they're interesting.
We talked about these
two new operators
of convolution and pooling.
And then next lecture, we'll
see how to stitch those together
into CNN architectures.
And see you next time for that.