This is CS231n.
And I'm Professor Fei-Fei
Li from computer science
department.
I will be co-teaching
this quarter
with Professor Ehsan Adeli
and my graduate student Zane.
So you'll meet them as well
as our wonderful TA team
that you will meet later.
So I just want to get started.
So this is what
excites me, that AI
has become such an
interdisciplinary field,
that what you're going
to learn in this class,
of course, is very technical.
It's about computer
vision and deep learning.
But I really do
hope that you take
it to whichever discipline you
work in and are passionate about
and apply it.
So we hear a lot
about the field of AI.
So how do we position
computer vision
and the scope of this class?
If you consider AI
as this big bubble,
computer vision is very
much an integral part of AI.
Some of you have heard me
saying that not only vision is
part of intelligence, it's a
cornerstone to intelligence.
Unlocking the mystery
of visual intelligence
is unlocking the
mystery of intelligence.
But one of the most important
tools, mathematical tools,
to solving AI is machine
learning or some people
call statistical
machine learning.
And this is exactly what
we will be talking about.
Within the field of
machine learning,
in the past 10 plus years, we
have seen a major revolution
called deep learning.
And I'll explain a little
bit of what deep learning is.
Deep learning is a set
of algorithmic techniques
that is built around
a family of algorithms
called neural networks.
And so if you ask me to pinpoint
the scope of this class,
we'll not be able to cover the
entirety of computer vision.
We'll not be able to cover
the entirety of machine
learning or deep learning.
But we're going to cover the
core intersection of these two
fields.
And of course, just
like the entirety of AI,
computer vision is
becoming more and more
an interdisciplinary field.
A lot of the techniques
we use as well as
the problems we
work with intersect
with many different other
fields, like natural language
processing, speech recognition,
robotics, and AI as a whole
is a field that intersects
with mathematics, neuroscience,
computer science,
psychology, physics, biology,
and many application
areas from medicine
to law to education
and business and so on.
So what you will get for this
lecture, our first lecture,
is I'll give a very
brief history of computer
vision and deep learning.
And then Professor Adeli will go
over the overview of this course
and lay the groundwork of
how this course is set up
and what our expectations are.
So the history of vision did
not begin when you were born
or humanity was born.
The history of vision began
540 million years ago.
You might ask, what happened
540 million years ago?
Why are we pinpointing a
relatively specific date or year
in evolution.
Well, it's because a
lot of fossil studies
have shown us that there is a
mystery period called Cambrian
explosion.
The fossil studies showed about
10 million years in evolution
during that time, which is
a very short period of time
for evolution.
We see the explosion
of animal species
in the fossil study, which means
before the Cambrian explosion,
life on Earth was pretty chill.
It was actually in the water.
There's no animals
on the land yet.
And animals just float around.
So what caused this explosion
in animal speciation?
There were many theories, from
climate to chemical composition
of the ocean water.
But one of the most compelling
theories was the onset of ice.
The first animal,
a trilobite, they
gained photosensitive cells.
So the eyes we
were talking about
were not sophisticated lenses
and retinas and nerve cells.
It was literally a
very simple pinhole.
And that pinhole
collected light.
Once you collected light,
life is completely different.
Without sensors,
life is metabolism.
It's very passive.
It is just metabolism.
And you come and go.
With sensors, you become an
integral part of the environment
that you might want to change.
You might want to
actually survive in it.
Some animals or plants
become your dinner.
And you become
someone else's dinner.
So evolutionary forces
drives intelligence
to evolve because of
the onset of sensors,
because of the onset of
vision, along with haptics
or tactile sensing.
Those are the oldest
sensors for animals.
So that entire course
of 540 million years
of evolution of vision is the
evolution of intelligence.
Vision as one of the
primary senses of animals
drove the development of
nervous system, the development
of intelligence.
Almost all animals on
Earth today we know of
have vision or use vision as
one of the primary senses.
Humans are especially
visual animals.
More than half of
our cortical cells
are involved in
visual processing.
And we have a very complex
and convoluted visual system.
So this is what excites me
to enter the field of vision.
And I hope it excites you.
So now, let's just fast
forward from Cambrian explosion
to actually human civilization.
Humans do innovate.
And not only we see.
We want to build
machines that see.
So here's a couple of
drawings by, of course,
Leonardo da Vinci, who
was just forever curious
about everything.
He studied camera obscura for
how to make steam machines.
In fact, even way before
him, in ancient Greece
and in ancient China,
we have seen documents
about thinkers,
philosophers thinking
about how to project
objects through pinholes
and to create images of objects.
And of course, in
our modern life,
cameras have truly exploded.
But cameras are not enough for
seeing, just like eyes are not
enough for seeing.
These are apparatus.
We need to understand how
visual intelligence happens.
And that's really the
crux of this course.
So let's just talk a little bit
of the history that brought us
to this intersection of deep
learning and computer vision.
So let me go back to the 1950s.
The 1950s-- a set of very
critically important experiments
happened in neuroscience.
And that was the study
of the visual pathways
of mammals, especially
the seminal work
by Hubel and Wiesel.
They used electrodes to put
into live cats anesthetized.
And then they studied
the receptive field
of neurons that are in
the primary visual cortex.
What they have learned,
to their surprise,
are two very important things.
One is that neurons that
are responsible for seeing
in the primary
visual cortex have
their own individual
receptive fields.
Receptive fields means
that for every neuron,
there is a part of
space it actually sees.
It's not all the space.
It's not very big.
It tends to be a very
confined patch of the space.
And within that space, it
sees specialized patterns,
simple patterns, when you're
measuring from the early part
of the visual pathway.
And by and large, in the
primary visual cortex,
which is around here in the back
of the head, not near your eyes,
it's oriented edges or
moving oriented edges.
So every neuron,
some neuron will
be seeing an edge like this.
Some will be seeing an
edge like this or this.
And that's how the computation
in the brain begins.
The second thing they learned
is that visual pathway
is hierarchical.
As you move beyond
the visual pathway,
the neurons feed
into other neurons.
And the neurons in
the higher layers
or deeper layers of
the visual hierarchy
have more complex
receptive fields.
So if you begin
with oriented edges,
you might feed into
a corner receptor.
You might feed into
an object receptor.
I'm overly simplifying.
But that's the concept, is that
neurons feed into each other.
And then they create this
big network of computation.
Of course, most of
you sitting here
are already thinking
the way I've
been describing this will
have a profound impact
on the neural network
modeling of visual algorithms.
Let's keep going.
That's year 1959.
It's very early
studies of seeing.
By the way, about
30 years later--
maybe not quite-- 20
something years later,
Hubel and Wiesel won the
Nobel Prize in medicine
for studying this,
uncovering the principles
of visual processing.
Another milestone in the early
history of computer vision
was the first PhD thesis
of computer vision.
Most people attribute
Larry Roberts in 1963
writing the first PhD
thesis just studying shape.
And this is a very, very
character representation
of the world.
And the idea is that, can
we take a shape like this
and understand that the surfaces
and the corners and features
of this shape?
It's intuitive that humans do.
So an entire PhD thesis
is devoted to this.
And that's the beginning
of computer vision.
And around that time, in
1966, an MIT professor
created a summer
project in MIT and asked
to hire a few undergrads, very
smart ones, to study vision.
And the goal was pretty
much solve computer vision
or solve vision for one summer.
Of course, just like the
rest of the history of AI,
we tend to be overoptimistic
of what we can
do in a short period of time.
So vision did not get
solved in that summer.
In fact, it has blossomed into
an incredible computer science
field.
If you go to our annual
conferences every year now,
it has more than 10,000
people attending.
But 1960s is where, between
Larry Roberts PhD thesis as well
as this kind of project, we
in our field considered that
the beginning of the
field of computer vision.
A seminal book was written
in the 1970s by David Marr,
who unfortunately
died too early.
He wanted to study vision
systematically and start
to consider how visual
processing happens.
Even though this
is not explicitly
stated, but there is
a lot of inspiration
from neuroscience and
cognitive science.
He was thinking about, if
you take an input image,
how do we visually process
and understand the image?
Maybe the first layer is more
like edges, just like we saw.
He calls it primal sketch.
And then there is a 2 and 1/2 D
sketch which separates different
depth of the objects
in the image.
So the ball is the
foreground object.
And then the grass here--
oh, no, not grass.
The ground here
is the background.
So he does these 2
and 1/2 D sketch.
And then, finally, David Marr
believes the grand holy grail
victory of solving vision is
to know the entire full 3D
representation.
And that is actually the
hardest thing of vision.
Let me digress for 20 seconds.
Because if you think about
vision for all animals,
it's an ill posed problem.
Since the early trilobites
who collected light
from underwater, light--
the world through photons
is projected on something
on a surface more or less 2D.
At that time, it was just,
I don't know, some patch
in the animal.
But right now, for
us, it's a retina.
But the actual world is 3D.
So recovering 3D information,
the entire 3D world,
from 2D images is the
fundamental problem nature had
to solve and computer
vision has to solve.
And mathematically, that's
an ill-posed problem.
So what did we later do?
Anybody have a wild guess?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
The trick that nature did is
develop multiple eyes, mostly
two.
Some animals have more than two.
And then you
triangulate information.
But two eyes are not enough.
You actually have to understand
correspondences and all that.
We'll touch on some
of these topics.
But there are other computer
vision classes taht Stanford
offers that also specifically
talk about 3D vision.
But the point is it's
a very hard problem.
And we have to solve it.
Nature has solved it.
Humans have solved it but
not to extreme precision.
In fact, humans are
not that precise.
I roughly know the 3D shapes.
But I don't have geometric
precision of all the shapes.
So that's one thing to
consider and appreciate
how hard this problem is.
Another thing that is very
different for computer vision
and language is
actually something
philosophically subtle.
Language doesn't
exist in nature.
You cannot point to something
and say there is language.
Language is a purely
generated thing.
I don't even know
what word to use.
It comes through our brain.
It's generated.
It's 1D.
It's sequential.
So this actually has profound
implications in the latest
wave of GenAI algorithms.
This is why these
LLMs, which is outside
of the scope of this class,
is so powerful because we
can model language that way.
But vision is not generated.
There is actually
a physical world
out there respecting the laws
of physics and materials and all
that.
So vision has very
different tasks.
So I just want you to appreciate
the difference between language
and vision and actually,
frankly, appreciate nature,
how it solved this problem.
Let's keep going.
1970s, the early pioneers of
computer vision, without data,
without really much
of powerful computers,
without the mathematical
advances we have seen today,
are already beginning to solve
some of the harder problems
of computer vision-- for
example, recognition of objects.
Here in Stanford, one
of the pioneering work
is called generalized cylinders
by Rodney Brooks and Tom
Binford.
And ironically, Rodney Brooks
today is on campus, actually,
over there giving a talk
at the robotics conference.
And he went on to become
one of the greatest
roboticists of our time
and was founder of Roomba
and many other robots.
And then not very far from us
in another part of Palo Alto,
researchers have worked on
these also compositional models
of human body and objects.
And then in the 1980s, digital
photos start to appear.
At least photos start to appear.
And people can digitize
that a little bit.
And then there are some
great work in edge detection.
You look at all this
and probably feel
a sense of disappointment.
I mean, it's kind of trivial
to get some sketches and edges.
And it's not really
going anywhere.
That's how computer
vision, works at that time.
And in fact, you're
not so wrong.
That was around the
time before many of you
were born that we
entered AI winter.
The field entered AI winter
because the enthusiasm
and, hence, funding for AI
research has really dwindled.
A lot of things didn't deliver.
Computer vision didn't deliver.
Expert systems didn't deliver.
Robotics didn't deliver.
But under the hood of this
winter, a lot of research
start to grow from
different fields,
like computer vision,
NLP, robotics.
So let's also look at
another strand of research
that had a profound
implication in computer vision,
is that cognitive
and neuroscience
continue to blossom.
And what is really
important, especially
for the field of computer
vision, is cognitive
and neuroscience is starting
to point to as the North Star
problems we should work on.
For example,
psychologists have told us
there's something special
about seeing nature,
seeing real world.
This is a study by
Irv Biederman, who
shows that the detection
of bicycles on two images
differ depending on if the
images are scrambled or not.
Think about it.
From a phton point of
view, these two bicycles
land in the same
location on your retina.
But somehow the
rest of the image
impacts the viewer,
seeing the target objects.
So there is something
telling us that seeing
the entire forest
or the entire world
impacts the way we see objects.
It also tells us visual
processing is very fast.
Here's another direct measure
of how fast we detect objects.
This is an early 1970s
experiment showing people
a video.
And the test for the subject
is to detect the human
in one of the frames.
I suppose every one of you
have seen that human in one
of the frames.
But think about how
remarkable your eyes are
or your brain is because
you've never seen this video.
I didn't tell you which frame
that the target object would
appear.
I did not tell you
what the target
object will look like, where it
is, its gestures, and all that.
Yet, you have no problem
detecting the humans.
And on top of that,
these frames are
played at 10 Hertz,
which means you're
seeing every frame for
only 100 milliseconds.
And this is how remarkable
our visual system is.
In fact, Simon Thorpe, another
cognitive neuroscientist,
have measured the speed.
If you hook people
up in EEG caps
and show them complex
natural scenes
and ask human subjects
to categorize things
from animals without--
versus things without animals--
hundreds of them.
And then you measure
the brain wave.
It turned out, after 150
milliseconds of seeing a photo,
your brain already has
a differential signal
that categorizes.
You might not be so impressed.
Because compared to today's
GPUs and modern chips,
150 milliseconds is really
orders of magnitude slower.
But you got to admire.
Our wetware, our
brain, our neurons
don't work as fast
as transistors.
150 milliseconds is
actually really fast.
It's only a few
hops in the brain
in terms of neural processing.
So yet, again,
this is telling us
humans are really good at seeing
objects and categorizing them.
In fact, not only we're
so good at seeing objects
and categorizing them, we
even develop specialized brain
areas that have expert
ability in recognizing
faces or places or body parts.
And these are discoveries by MIT
neurophysiologist in the 1990s
and early 21st century.
So all these studies tell
us, well, we should not just
be studying these kind
of character shapes
or the sketches of images.
We really should go after
important fundamental problems
that drives visual intelligence.
And one of those
problems that everything
has been telling us is
object recognition--
is object recognition
in natural setting.
There is a lot of objects
out there in the world.
And studying this
is going to be part
of the unlocking of
visual intelligence.
And that's what we did.
As a field, we
started by looking
at how we can separate
foreground objects
from background objects.
This is called recognition
by grouping in the 1990s.
Keep in mind, we're
still in AI winter.
But research is actually
happening and progressing.
And then there is
studies of features.
And some of you
might still remember
sift features and matching.
And when I enter grad school,
the most exciting thing
was face detection.
I remembered that first
year in my grad school,
this paper was published.
And five years later,
the first digital camera
used this paper's algorithm and
delivered automatic face focus
because of face detection.
So things started to work
and taken into industry.
And then around the
early 21st century,
a very important thing
started to happen,
is internet started to happen.
When internet started to happen,
data started to proliferate.
And the combination of
digital cameras and internet
started to give the
field of computer vision
some data to work with.
So in that early days, we're
working with thousands of images
or tens of thousands of images
to study the visual recognition
problem or the object
recognition problem.
So you've got data sets
like Pascal Visual Object
Challenge or Caltech 101.
I'm going to pause here.
And this is where the first
thread of computer vision
start to progress.
And you might be wondering,
why is she pausing?
Because I'm going to come back
and talk about deep learning.
So while this field of
vision was progressing
through neurophysiology
to computer vision,
to cognitive neuroscience,
to computer vision again,
a separate effort is
going on in parallel.
And that eventually
became deep learning.
It started from these early
studies of neural network,
things like perceptron.
And people like Rumelhart
started to work.
And of course, Jeff
Hinton in his early days,
started to work with a small
number of artificial neurons
and look at how that can
process information and learn.
And you've heard people like the
great minds like Marvin Minsky
and his colleagues working
on different aspects
of this perception.
But Marvin Minsky did say that
perceptrons cannot learn these
XOR logic functions.
And that caused a little bit
of a setback in neural network.
Well, things continued to
progress despite the setback.
And one of the most important
work before the first inflection
point is this neocognitron
work by Fukushima in Japan.
Fukushima hand-designed a neural
network that looks like this.
So it has about
five or six layers.
And then he kind of designed
the different functions
across the layers,
which you will
learn more, that
more or less was
inspired by the visual
pathway that I was describing.
Remember the cat experiment
from simple receptive field
to more complicated
receptive field.
And he was doing that here.
The early layers have
simple functions.
And then the later
lighter layers
have more complex functions.
And the simple ones can
call it convolution.
Or he uses the
convolution function.
And the more complex one, he
was pulling the information
from the convolution layers.
So neocognitron was
really an engineering feat
because every parameter
was hand-designed.
There are hundreds
of parameters.
He has to just meticulously
put them together
so that this small
neural network can
recognize digits or letters.
So the real breakthrough
came around that time in 1986
is a learning rule.
That learning rule is
called backpropagation.
It's going to be one
of our first classes
to show you that
Rumelhart, Jeff Hinton--
they took neural
network architecture
and introduced an error
correcting objective function
so that if you put in
some input and know
what the correct
output is, how do you
take the difference between
what the neural network outputs
versus the actual
correct answer and then
propagate the information
back so that you
can improve the parameters
along the neural network?
And that propagation
from the output
back to the entire
neural network
is called backpropagation.
It follows some of these
basic calculus chain rules.
And that was a watershed moment
for neural network algorithm.
And of course, we're still smack
in the middle of AI winter.
All these work was happening
without public fanfare.
But of course, in the
world of research,
these are very
important milestones.
One of the most earliest
applications of this neural
network with backpropagation
is Yann LeCun's convolutional
neural network, made in the
1990s when he was working
in the Bell Labs.
And what he did is just created
a slightly bigger network,
about seven layers-ish,
and made it good enough
with great engineering
capability to recognize letters.
And it was actually shipped
to some part of the US Postal
Offices and banks to
read digits and letters.
So that was an application
of early neural network.
And then Jeff Hinton
and Yann LeCun
continued to work
on neural network.
It didn't go very far.
Because despite these
improvements and tweaks
of these neural network, things
more or less just stalled.
They collected a big data
set of digits and letters.
And digits and letters
kind of was quasi soft
in terms of recognition.
But if you put the
system through the kind
of digital photos that the
neuroscientists were using
to recognize cats and dogs
and microwaves and chairs
and flowers, it
just didn't work.
And a huge part of this
problem is the lack of data.
And lack of data is not
just an inconvenience.
It's actually a
mathematical problem
because these algorithms are
high capacity algorithms that
actually needs to be
driven by lots of data
in order to learn to generalize.
And there is some deep
mathematical principles
behind these rules of
generalization and model
overfitting.
And data was
underappreciated, was
underlooked because
most people are just
looking at these architectures.
They did not
realize that data is
part of the first class
citizen for machine
learning and deep learning.
So this is part of the work
that my students and I did
in the early 2000s, that we
recognize this importance
of data.
We hypothesized that the
whole field was actually
missing this-- underappreciating
the importance of data.
So we went about and
collected a huge data
set called ImageNet that
has 50 million images
after cleaning a billion images.
And these 15 million images were
sorted across 22,000 categories
of objects.
We actually studied a lot of
the cognitive and psychology
literature to appreciate
that 22,000 images were--
sorry, 22,000 categories
were roughly in the order
of the number of categories
that humans learned to recognize
in the early years
of their life.
And then we open
sourced this data
set and created an ImageNet
challenge called the Large Scale
Visual Recognition Challenge.
We curated a subset of ImageNet
of a million images or a million
plus images and 1,000
object classes and then ran
an international object
recognition challenge for many
years.
And the goal is that we ask
researchers to participate.
And their goal is to
create algorithms.
It doesn't matter which
kind of algorithms.
And they will test you on your
algorithm's ability to recognize
photos and see if you can call
out these 1,000 object classes
as correctly as possible.
And here are the errors.
First year we run
this competition,
the best performing algorithms
error was nearly 30%.
And it's really pretty abysmal
because humans can perform
under like, say, 3% error.
And then 2011, it
wasn't that exciting.
But something happened in 2012.
That was the most exciting year.
That year, Jeff Hinton
and his students
participated in
this challenge using
convolutional neural network.
And they reduced the
error almost by half.
And it truly showed the power
of deep learning algorithms.
And so the participating
algorithm in 2012 ImageNet
challenge was called AlexNet.
And the funny thing is,
if you look at AlexNet,
it's not that different from
Fukushima's neocognitron
32 years ago.
But two major things
happened between these two.
One is that
backpropagation happened.
It's a principled,
mathematically rigorous learning
rule so that you don't
have to ever use hand
to tune parameters.
And that was a major
breakthrough theoretically.
Another breakthrough was data.
The recognition of data and the
understanding of data driving
these high capacity models,
which eventually will have
trillion parameters-- but
at that time was millions
of parameters-- was critical for
setting off the deep learning
for this to work.
And really, many people
consider the year of 2012
and the AlexNet algorithm
that won the ImageNet
the challenge the historical
moment of the birth
or rebirth of modern AI or
the birth of deep learning
revolution.
And of course, the reason
many of you are here
is since then, we are in the
era of deep learning explosion.
If you look at computer vision,
some main annual research
conference, called CVPR--
the number of papers
have exploded.
And our arXiv
paper has exploded.
And many new
algorithms since then
have been invented to
participate in the ImageNet
challenge.
In the following
years, we're going
to study some of
these algorithms.
But the point is
that some of these
algorithms beyond Alex that
have had a profound impact
in the progress of the
field of computer vision
and into the applications
of computer vision.
So a lot of things
have happened.
We're going to
cover some of these.
Not only the field
of computer vision
made a major progress
in creating algorithms
to recognize everyday m like
cats and dogs and chairs--
we also quickly, right
after ImageNet challenge,
the 2012 moment,
we've got algorithms
that can recognize much
more complicated images,
can retrieve images, or can
do multiple object detections,
can do image segmentation.
These are all different
tasks in visual recognition
that you'll find
yourself getting
familiar with
throughout this course
because vision is not just
calling out cats and dogs.
There is so much in the nuanced
ability of visual recognition.
And of course, vision is
not just static images.
So there are work in video
classification, human activity
recognition.
I'm showing you this overview.
You will learn some of these.
You don't have to understand
exactly what's going on here.
But I want you to appreciate
the variety of vision tasks.
Medical imaging, those of you
who come from a medical field,
whether it's radiology
or pathology or even
other aspects of medicine,
is deeply visual.
And this has a profound impact.
Scientific discovery--
even the seminal picture
you probably remember of the
first photography of black hole
uses a lot of computer vision
and computational photography
techniques.
Of course, applications in
sustainability and environment
is $also computer vision
contributed a lot of that.
And we also have made
a lot of progress
in image captioning right after
the image-- that 2012 moment.
This is actually work by
Andrej Karpathy, where he was
my student, his thesis work.
Then we also worked on
relationship understanding.
So not only visual
intelligence is
about seeing what's
on the pixel,
you can also see
what's beyond pixels,
including relationships of
objects and also style transfer.
A Lot of this work,
you will-- actually,
Justin Johnson, who will come
to guest lecture this course,
will tell you all about his
seminal work in style transfer.
And of course, in
generative AI eras,
we get these really incredible
results like face generation.
And this is the very early days
of image generation of Dall-E. I
think this is the early Dall-E.
Of course, now, Midjourney
and everything has gone beyond
these avocado and peach chairs.
But really, we are squarely in
the most exciting modern era
of AI explosion.
The three converging forces
of computation, algorithms,
and data have taken
this field just
to a whole different
level, where we're now
totally out of AI winter.
I would say we're in an
AI global warming period.
And I don't see any
of this slowing down
for both good and bad reasons.
And also, just a word, because
we are in the Silicon Valley,
we're in the very building
of Huang building and NVIDIA
lecture hall-- so we cannot
ignore also the progress
of hardware and
what that played.
So here is just the FLOP per
dollar graph for NVIDIA's GPUs.
And before 2020, the
progress was steady.
But as soon as deep
learning started
to drive these
GPUs and chips, you
can just see the GFLOPS have
just completely taken off.
And by any measure, we are
in this accelerated curve
of lots of compute as
well as lots of AI.
And these are just
different graphs
showing you conference
attendees, startups,
and enterprise applications
in AI all across
not just computer vision.
But also, NLP and others
have just exploded.
So quickly, last but not the
least, it's been exciting.
There has been a
lot of successes.
But there is still a lot to
be done in computer vision.
So this problem is still
not totally solved.
And with great tools comes with
great consequences as well.
So computer vision
can do a lot of good.
But it also can do harm.
For example, human bias--
every single AI algorithm
today, the large ones,
are driven by data.
And data is an artifact
of human activities
on Earth and in history.
And a lot of the
data carry our bias.
And this gets carried
in AI systems.
We have seen a lot of face
recognition algorithms having
the same kind of bias
that humans have.
And we do have to
really recognize that.
We can also use AI to impact
human lives, some for the good.
Think about medical imaging.
But some are questionable.
What if AI is solely
behind deciding your job
or deciding your
financial loans?
So again, is it totally bad?
Is it totally good?
These are very
complicated issues.
This is also why I always get so
excited when students from HMS
or law school or education
school or business school
attend my class
because not all AI
issues are engineering issues.
We have a lot of human factors
and societal issues to solve.
I'm also particularly excited
by AI's medicine and health care
use.
This is something
really dear to my heart.
Professor Adeli
and Zane, who are
also co-instructors of
this course, we three of us
work on AI for aging
population as well as
patients and to try to use
computer vision to deliver care
to people.
So this is a good use.
And also, even in
terms of technology,
human vision is remarkable.
I want you to come out
of not only today's class
but also this entire
course to appreciate,
despite how much
computer vision can do,
there's just so much more
nuance, subtlety, richness,
complexity, and also
emotion in human vision.
Look at these kids
studying whatever
that their curiosity lead them
or the humor in this image.
There's still a lot more that
computer vision cannot do.
So I hope that
continue to entice
you to study computer vision.
At this point, I'm going to give
the podium to Professor Adeli
to go over the
rest of the class.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Awesome.
Thank you, Fei-Fei.
Great to start of the quarter.
And I hope my microphone
is working right now.
OK, good.
I'm seeing some
nodding of heads.
So very excited to
be here with you all.
And I'm hoping that
you will have a fun
and challenging course with an
amazing list of core instructors
that we have and great TAs.
So in this class, we
are going to cover
a wide variety of topics
around computer vision and use
of deep learning in
this space, categorized
into four different topics.
We will start with
deep learning basics.
And let's start actually
with a simple question of,
what is computer vision really?
So at its core, it's
about enabling machines
to see and understand images.
And basically, this is the most
fundamental task in this space--
in this space is
image classification.
You give the model an
image, say, of a cat.
And the model should
output a label cat.
And that's it.
But this deceptively simple
task is the foundation
for much of more
complex applications,
from self-driving to
medical diagnosis and so on.
So how do we teach a
machine to do this?
One of the simplest approaches
is to use linear classification,
as you can see in this slide.
So imagine each of the
images in our data set
is shown with a
dot in that space.
And each axis shows
some sort of feature
which was driven from
the image itself.
Here, we are showing a
2D space for simplicity.
But the task of a
linear classifier
is to find the hyperplane
or the linear function
that separates these
two, say, cats from dogs.
But we all know that
these linear models often
go just only so far.
They struggle when the data
isn't cleanly separable
with a straight line.
So the question is, what's next?
We'll get into the topics of how
to model more complex patterns.
And if we do so, we
often face challenges
of overfitting and
underfitting, which
are the topics we will cover in
the early lectures of the class.
And to strike the
right balance, we
use techniques
like regularization
to control model complexity and
optimization to find the best
fit parameters.
So these are the nuts and bolts
of deep learning and creating
these models, training models,
that not only fits the data
but also generalizes to
unseen and new data as well.
And now comes the fun part--
neural networks.
We've been talking
about them quite a lot.
And what neural networks do,
unlike the linear classifiers,
they stack multiple
layers of operations
to model non-linear
functions to be
able to either classify, to
solve the same problem of image
classification, and so on.
These are the models powering
everything from Google Photos.
And now, everybody's familiar
with ChatGPT, ChatGPT's vision
models, and so on.
In this course, we will go deep
into the details of how they
work, how they are trained.
And we will be looking into
debugging and improving them.
After looking at the
deep learning basics,
we will cover the topics of
perceiving and understanding
the visual world, which
is a complex process that
involves interpreting a vast
array of visual information.
And to do so, we
often first define
tasks that refer to specific
challenges or problems.
We aim to solve--
some of the examples are object
detection, scene understanding,
motion detection, and so on.
And to solve these tasks, we
use different models, which
are computational
and theoretical
frameworks we develop
to mimic or explain
how our visual system
accomplishes these tasks.
One of the examples of
these types of models
is neural networks.
So by aligning
models with tasks,
we can create systems
that can see and interpret
the world around us.
Speaking of tasks, let's
go back to the topic
of image classification,
predicting a single label
for an entire image.
But we know that real
world computer vision
is much richer than this.
And let's walk through
some of the tasks that
go beyond classification.
First, semantic segmentation,
where we are not just
labeling the object
or the entire image
as cat or tree or whatever.
Here, we are looking for
labels for every single pixel
in the image.
So every pixel is a
grass, cat, tree, or sky.
But we don't distinguish
between individual objects.
And next, we have
object detection,
where we now want to not
only say what is in the image
but also pinpoint the location.
And that's why we
create bounding boxes
around the objects and associate
them with specific labels.
And finally, we have
instance segmentation.
We'll go into instance
segmentation, which is
the most granular of them all.
It combines the ideas of
detection and segmentation
together.
And every object instance
gets its own mask.
So these tasks require much
deeper special understanding
and images.
And they push the models
to do more than just
recognizing categories.
The complexity doesn't
stop with static images.
Let's look at some
temporal dimensions.
So there's the task of
video classification,
as Fei-Fei talked about,
where we want to understand
what's happening in video.
Is there someone running,
jumping, or dancing?
There is the topic of
multimodal video understanding,
which is combining vision and
sound and other modalities.
For example, in this
example, the person
is playing a vibraphone
to really understand
what's happening here.
We have to create a
blend of visual features
and audio features to be able
to understand what's happening.
And finally, there is the
topic of visualization
and understanding that we will
be covering in this class, where
we want to interpret what's
being learned by the models
and see an attention frame
or attention map of what
the model is attending to to
do a correct classification
and so on.
And then we have
models beyond tasks.
We look into models.
And the very first topic--
let me introduce to you--
that we'll be covering is
Convolutional Neural Networks
or CNNs.
There are a number
of operations.
We will be going
over the details
in the class, starting from an
image, a number of convolutions,
sampling and fully
connected operations,
and, finally,
creating the output.
And beyond convolutional
neural networks,
we will study recurrent neural
networks for sequential data
and even neural architectures,
such as transformers
and attention-based frameworks.
So next, we will be covering
some large-scale distributed
training topics, which is
kind of new this quarter.
I'm sure you've all heard
about large language models,
large vision models, and so on.
And we will be
briefly discussing
how these models are
actually trained.
We know that data and data
sets are expanding models.
And models are becoming
larger and larger.
And in order to
train such models,
there are some strategies--
for example, data
parallelization,
model parallelization-- that
we will cover in this class.
But beyond that, there
will be so many challenges,
such as synchronization between
these models and workers
and so on, as well as
several other aspects
that we'll be covering in one
of the lectures this quarter.
And we will go also over some
of the trends for training
these large models.
After completing this
topic, what we will do
next is looking into generative
and interactive visual
intelligence, where
we will first start
with self-supervised learning.
Self-supervised learning is
a branch of machine learning
in which models learn to
understand and represent data
by getting some training
signals from the data itself.
We will cover this topic.
It's one of the approaches
that has enabled training
of large scale models using
vast amounts of data that do not
require labels, unlabeled data.
And they have played a key
role in recent breakthroughs
in computer vision in general.
And we will talk a little
bit about generative models.
They go beyond recognition.
They actually generate.
This is an example of the
content of a Stanford campus
photo, which is reimagined in
the style of Van Gogh's Starry
Night.
This is known as style
transfer, a classic application
of neural generative techniques.
Generative models can
now translate language
into images given a prompt.
A model like Dall-E, Dall-E
2 generates an entirely novel
image.
This showcases how
generative vision models
blend understanding,
creativity, and control
in their generations.
And you've probably
heard recently
about the topic of
diffusion models in general.
That's another thing that we'll
be covering in this quarter.
They basically learn to
reverse a gradual noising
process to generate images.
And interestingly,
in assignment 3,
you will actually be
implementing a generative model
that generates emojis
from text inputs,
from prompts-- for example, a
face with a cowboy hat, which
is denoised from pure noise.
Vision language models are
the next topic of interest
we will be covering.
They connect text and images in
a shared representation space.
And given a caption
or image, the model
retrieves or generates
its corresponding pair,
as you can see.
So there are a lot of
advances in this area.
We'll be covering some
of the key examples.
Again, this is a key task
for cross-modal retrieval
or understanding and visual
question answering and so on.
So we'll get to
that in the class 2.
Moving beyond 2D, models can
now reconstruct and generate 3D
representations from images.
And here, you can see some
voxel-based reconstructions,
shape completion, and even 3D
object detection from single
view images.
So 3D vision enables
more especially grounded
understanding, which is
crucial for robotics and AI VR
applications.
And finally, vision
empowers embodied agents
that act in the physical world.
So these models often
must perceive, plan,
and execute whether it's
cleaning up a messy room
or generalizing from
human demonstrations.
So with all of these, we will
be covering different topics
around generative and
interactive visual intelligence.
And finally, we will cover some
human-centered applications
and implications, as Fei-Fei
very nicely explained.
So there is a computer vision.
And generally, AI
have been having a lot
of impact in the past years.
And it's very
important to understand
the human-centered
aspects and applications.
And some of these
impacts are reflected
by these awards that are going
to researchers in this space.
It was first recognized by
the Turing Award 2018, which
is the most prestigious
technical award given
to major contributions
of lasting importance
for computing.
Geoffrey Hinton, Yoshua
Bengio, and Yann LeCun
received the award for
conceptual and engineering
during breakthroughs
that have made
deep neural networks a critical
component of computing.
Beyond that, last year,
in 2024, Geoffrey Hinton
was jointly awarded the
Nobel Prize in physics
alongside John Hopfield for
their foundational contributions
to neural networks.
And finally, I want to very
briefly mention the learning
objectives for this class will
be formalizing computer vision
applications into tasks.
As you can see some
of the details here,
we want to develop and
train vision models, models
that operate on images
and visual data--
images, videos, and so on--
gain an understanding
of where the field is
and where it is headed.
That's why we have some new
topics also covered specifically
in this year.
So the four topics that
I mentioned earlier,
we will be going over the basics
in the very first few weeks.
Bear with us because these
are important topics.
And you need to understand
the details first,
how to build the
models from scratch.
And then we'll get to more
interesting, exciting topics
of the day--
computer vision.
And finally, we'll have one big
lecture on human-centered AI
and computer vision.
I want to just leave
you with what we
will be covering next session.
That's going to be
image classification
and linear classifiers,
which will get us started
with the world of CS231n.
Thank you.