I think at the beginning of the
course, we announced that we would have
a few guest lecturers, people who previously
taught the course, to come and give a single
guest lecture about a topic that they're very
familiar with. And I'm very happy to announce
we have the first one of those lectures
today. So I'll introduce Dr. Ruohan Gao.
He is an Assistant Professor in the Department of
Computer Science at the University of Maryland,
College Park. And he leads the Multisensory
Machine Intelligence Lab there. He was previously
an instructor for CS231N from 2022 to 2023.
And this is while he completed his postdoc with
Fei-Fei Li, Jiajun Wu, and Silvio
Savarese. So without further ado,
I'll leave it to Ruohan to
give the presentation today.
OK, thanks. Hello, everyone. So it's
really exciting to be back to the class
of CS231N. And I'm Ruohan, just like [?
Zen ?] introduced. So as you can tell,
I'm very interested in multimodal stuff. So
not only in vision, but also how we can make
use of other sensory modalities like audio,
tactile, or other modalities, just like us,
humans, to perceive, understand, and
interact with this multisensory world.
But of course, vision is the most important
modalities. That's why we have this course,
deep learning for computer vision. And I'm sure up
to this point that you guys are very familiar with
image classification. Given a 2D image like this,
how to give a label to see whether it's a dog,
it's a cat, or it's a truck, a plane.
That's a 2D-based image classification.
And from the last lecture, I'm sure you have
also learned some other tasks that you can
do on images. Not only you can just assign a
single label to say it's a cat or not. Also,
you can do semantic segmentation to segment the
picture into different portions, components,
and also have some semantic meaning like
where is grass, where is cat, where is tree.
And you can also put a bounding box on
top of the objects you detect in the image
to see where the dog is, where the cat is,
and also do instant segmentation that you not
only want to know the categories, but also
for each category, if there are two dogs,
I want to have a segmentation mask for each
category. That's instance segmentation.
So a lot of tasks, classification, recognition
tasks you can do based on 2D images.
But that's not the only thing that we can use
for computer vision system to do. And also,
our world is not just static like this. So if we
look at this image, hopefully up to this point,
you have learned a lot of tools that you can
train some models to this classify this is a
living room. You also have tools. You have
learned that to put a bounding box to see
that this is a dog, and this is a baby. And
also, you can even have a segmentation mask
to send them out to see where those
objects you detect are in the image.
So today, we're going to focus on video
understanding. So more formally, what is video?
Basically, video is just like this 2D image plus
time. There is an extra time dimension. So now,
we are tackling things not only in this
3D image but also now in 4D. We have this
three times T. T is temporal dimension.
And H and W are the spatial dimension. Now,
we are considering this kind of image and the
videos as a volume of images of video frames.
So an example task is video classification,
just like image classification. So we are
given a video like this. Some person is
running. We want to take this videos as
input. And also we want to train some
model, a deep learning model. We want
to classify whether this person is doing
swimming or running or jumping or what
actions that he is doing just based on
this temporal streams of video frames.
So also, we have from the previous lectures,
I'm sure you have already learned some loss
functions like cross-entropy loss. And you
can train an image classifier. Similarly,
you can use the similar tools. You just train
a video classifier. You just get some features.
And you use the same loss functions
and train a video classifier. So now,
the problem on video understanding is
that how can we get features of videos
that you can apply the loss functions you
have learned from the previous lectures?
And also another kind of difference between image
classification and the video classification,
video understanding is that now the things,
the tasks you want to do might be a little bit
different just from the previous example. For
image classification, usually, you care more
about the scenes, the objects. You want to just
do a classification. What is the object category?
For videos, usually, just like
this example I'm showing here,
you only want to classify actions.
It's often actions where the person,
what activities the person or some animals are
doing in the videos. That's what we care about
usually in video understanding. So the nature of
things to recognize can be a little bit different.
And another problem that we want to be
careful about for video understanding is
that videos are usually very big.
Well, when we talk about images,
it's just like three times H times W.
It's a single matrix of some RGB numbers.
But now, if we consider videos, it's a
sequence of frames. It can be like 30
frames per second. So in movies, sometimes,
we can have even higher resolution and also
temporal resolution video frames. And
so you consider a space to store videos.
For example, if we consider standard
definition videos, it can take about 1.5
gigabytes per minute if we store this video.
If we consider even higher resolution,
like 1920 times 1080. And now,
it takes like 10 gigabytes per
minute. So it takes the gigantic space in
order to store this kind of video data.
And also, there is no way for us to
just fit this kind of data directly
to GPUs. If we just have the input, then
we have a lot of storage to store them,
to store this kind of data. And also, there are
other things you have to store, like the weights,
the activations in your convolution neural
networks. So then, your model will be very huge.
And the solution-- what solutions we can have to
make videos smaller to make them processable? So
one simple solution is that we just make videos
smaller. So although the high definition videos
and also the original videos are long, we can
shrink things both temporally and spatially.
For example, for 3.2-second
videos like this, for example,
we can maybe-- for each second,
maybe we don't need all the frames.
Let's just take five frames because there are
a lot of redundancies in the video frames.
If we take frames per second, and
also we just have a smaller spatial
resolution like 112 times 112.
And now, we can make the videos
slightly smaller. For example, it's five 588
KB for this simple video. But definitely,
we can also do larger resolution if
you have the compute, just like images.
And also, how to train a model on these long
videos? Previous slide, I showed that we are
training this video classifier on 3.2
seconds. But videos can be very long,
can be minutes, can be hours. So one way
that people do is that we train on clips,
just like we train on chunks of this
video frames using a video classifier.
And what we do is that we train models
to classify short clips with some low
fps, frame per second. And we just use a sliding
window. We sample a lot of different clips and use
them as training data. And we train a classifier.
And then during testing, during inference time,
we just run the model on different clips.
We sample a few clips. We made 10 clips. And
then we average the prediction results. And
that is our prediction for this long video.
And then what is a same post, like, video
classification model we can use? So I have
mentioned basically video is just like a sequence
of images, a sequence of video image frames. So
one simple thing that we just treat them as
images. That's the simplest tool we already
have. We just run single frame convolution neural
networks because we already have all the tools.
We have learned that we can train an image
classifier. If we just take our image
classifier to just run on top of these
video frames and treat them as images,
we can indeed get decent predictions.
Especially like a video like this. You
can see that there are not many changes across
videos. The person is running. Maybe there are
some different movements on the body.
But generally, it looks pretty similar.
Maybe you run an image action classifier. And
on every frame, maybe all of the frames will
tell you it's running. And if you average
the prediction results from each image,
each video frame, then you will predict
running for this particular video.
So actually, also, it's usually a very, very
strong baseline for this simple image classifier,
especially for video like this because
there are not too many changes across
videos. So if you are trying to design some
video classifier, you should always run this
first because that's simple things to try. And
maybe you can already get pretty decent results.
So the question is, whether we just run single
frame or we run a chunk of frames? So for this, a
simple single frame, say. And basically, we have a
video of 30 frames. Maybe you just maybe sample a
few frames. And you just use the image classifier
to run on those sampled 10 frames and just treat
them as images. And you just directly average
the results. That's basically the per frame CNN.
So I think you have some very important
question is how to sample the frame?
That's the very key question. Because
we give you a-- I'm talking about we
want to sample some frames and we want
to run a CNN on the frame. So how to get
those frames? So that is actually
also an active area of research.
One simple way is that you do random sampling.
You have a one-hour video. I don't know where the
interesting part, where the important parts
are. We just sample maybe every one minute,
I sample one frame. And then I run an image
classifier. I average the results. But obviously,
maybe this gives us some good results. But maybe
this is not the smartest way to do sampling.
So there are other methods trying to
propose smarter sampling strategy.
Maybe you can sample one frame. You can
then use that decision to decide where
else to sample. I actually also have some
examples later in the later lecture slides.
So this is a very, very simple video
classifier. Just like we just adopt
image classifier, a single frame CNN. And
similarly, just maybe we take one step
further. Instead of directly just run single
frame CNN and average the prediction results,
maybe we can do some fusion across the
features on using the single frame CNNs.
So this is often called late fusion. Basically,
the idea is that we still take some 2D CNNs.
And we have some input, maybe key frames. And for
each frame, we use a 2D CNN. And then we extract
some feature vector. And then we get maybe a
feature map of D times H prime times W prime.
And then because we have T frames. Then basically,
we have T feature maps. And then the simple
thing that we just flatten all the feature
maps to vectors and then concatenate them.
Then we have a giant feature vector that
basically contains all the information,
all the features across all the frames.
And then what we can do, we can use
tools that we have learned like fully
connected networks. We train an MLP
that maps this vector to some neural
dimension. And then we train a classifier
on top of it to map it, to class score C.
So this is called late fusion. Because basically,
you can see that we extract the feature maps. And
we process them very independently. And then at
the very late stage, we concatenate the feature
vectors and run some fully connected
layers to doing the classification.
So this is useful. But one drawback that
you can already probably tell from this
example from my description is that this fully
connected layer, it's going to introduce a lot
of parameters. Because if we concatenate
a lot of-- we flatten them across time.
And these feature vectors, depending
on how long how large T is, then you
can have a giant feature vector. And then
you use this giant feature vector. You want
to map them into some lower dimension. And
then you have a very large, fully connected
layers. And that will introduce a lot of
parameters. So it's not very efficient.
So another way to do this is that
instead of concatenating them,
we don't do concatenation. We don't
just use the giant feature vector,
and then have a fully connected layer to
map them to scores. We can actually just
do a simple pooling. Doing pooling, you don't
increase the length of the feature vector.
Basically, if you have some feature dimension
for a single frame and you pool across time,
for these T frames, you're just
doing a pooling to do a temporal
aggregation. And then based on this clip
feature D, and then instead of D times T,
you just still have a feature
vector of time D if you do pooling.
And then you have a linear layer to map D to some
dimension C that matches the class score. And
then you train the cross-entropy loss on top
of it. And that's also late fusion. But now,
we are using pooling. And the
good side here is that now,
you don't have to have a very large fully
connected layers. But the pooling can also
get rid of information that may be important.
So that's the downside of this operation.
So the reason I'm calling late fusion-- the
important part is late. And when it's late,
maybe there's some information that has already
been lost. So you have using this 2D convolution
networks to process images. For example, as
shown in these red circles here. So what is
very important to recognize this video is
actually the motion of this man's feet,
right. It's moving up and down, up and down.
And you can maybe tell that he's running.
So if we just use a single 2D CNN
to process them independently as a
2D image and extract some feature map and maybe
up to very late stage of the feature maps,
it doesn't contain the information of this
movement of the feet of this man anymore at
this very late stage. So some information of this
feet up and down is showing these red circles,
which should be useful cues. But now,
it's not there in the feature maps.
The intuition is that if you extract
features from the earlier layers,
it's very close to the original video
frames. So there is a larger chance it
will contain this low level information, this
movement from the video frames. And also,
if you concatenate them or pool them, across
time, it will analyze the motion across time.
But because we are processing a lot of
convolution pooling up to a late stage,
you need-- even at the very late stage, it
contains more high level information like
semantic information instead of this low
level motion information. So that's why
it's most likely it's not there. So
that's the downside of late fusion.
So instead of doing late fusion, we actually
we can do early fusion. So to do early fusion,
if we want to make use of the feature vectors
more closer to the actual video frames,
we can just take this input and then we directly
reshape them to 3T times H times W. We just
directly aggregate the information
temporally from the very beginning.
And then we use some 2D convolution, the first
2D convolution layer, just directly map them
to from channel dimensions 3T to D. Basically, we
use the 2D convolution to process this temporal
information in the first layer to map the channel
dimension from 3T to D to process the video frames
of all the information from the frames in the
very beginning of the convolution neural networks.
And the rest of the network
is then in standard 2 CNN. And
the only difference is that now, we destroy
and collapse all the temporal information
using a single layer. And then the rest
is just like image classification. And
then you're doing this classification
using standard cross-entropy loss.
For each frame, we get features like D. And each
single frame will give you a feature D. So you
have T. This feature vectors D. So for pooling,
we are pooling over the features. Basically,
we can do mean pooling to average the features
or be max pooling with max over the features.
Then after that, we still get a feature that's D.
So it's pooling over the features not the frame.
So that's early fusion. So then, the
downside of the early fusion is that
although we explicitly trying to handle
the motion from the early layer. But then,
we are too ambitious. We're trying to
capture everything in a single layer.
We just concatenate all the frames and then
collapse all the [INAUDIBLE] information using a
single convolution network. Maybe it's not
going to achieve what we want it to achieve.
So then, another solution is that instead of doing
late fusion or early fusion, maybe we should do
something in between. That's slow fusion. That's
exactly what this 3D convolution neural network
is doing. So the intuition is that we want to
use this 3D version of convolution and pooling.
We want to slowly fuse the information over the
course of the network. Instead of doing it at a
very late stage or at a very early stage, we
gradually shrink over temporal dimension and
spatial dimension to get this 3D feature maps. So
that's the idea of 3D convolution neural network.
We just use 3D convolution and a 3D pooling
operation. So what is 3D convolution, 3D
pooling? So you have learned the 2D convolution.
Right. For 2D convolution layer. Basically,
you take an image like this-- 32 times 32 times 3
image. And if you use 2D convolution, basically,
you have learned that you can-- for
each kernel, you have this filter.
You can have this convolution kernel that
is maybe 5 times 5 times 3 that runs like
a sliding window approach, just slides across
space and goes all the way in the depth dimension.
So then for each computation, you map that to
a single value in that final activation maps.
And then finally, you obtain this
activation map of 28 times 28 times 1,
in this case. You convolve over all spatial
locations and map this channel dimension,
the depths that-- go all the way over the channel
dimension, and then map from 3 to 1, in this case.
So that's 2D convolution. So the
difference is that for 3D convolution,
now, we just have one extra dimension. So
here, you can think of that-- here, the input
is C times T times H times W. The extra thing is
this T dimension. That is a temporal dimension.
But what I'm showing here, because we can only
show things in 3D, we cannot show things in 4D.
So there's actually one dimension that is not
shown here. That is a C dimension. The channel
dimension is not shown here. So you can think
of that for each grid point in this feature map,
there are many features. There
are C features in that grid point.
And then for this 3D convolution, basically,
if we are talking about a 66 times 6 times
6 convolution, because we have
one extra dimension. Instead of
slide over the spatial dimension just in
the H and W dimension over the images,
now we are sliding over this cube. We are sliding
over this cube of dimension T times H times W.
So it includes both the spatial dimension and the
temporal dimension. And also, it goes all the way
along the channel dimension. So then, gradually,
you can-- just like 2D calculus. The other part
is just like the 2D convolution. It's
just we have this extra dimension.
And then you get this 6 times 6 times
6 3D convolution. And maybe another
layer of 5 times 5. And finally, after you
processed doing these 3D convolution operations,
and you flatten the feature vectors, and
then you use a fully connected layers to
map them to the class scores. So that
is basically the idea of 3D convolution.
So let's walk maybe through some toy examples to
better understand it, to compare the early, late,
and the 3D convolution neural networks. Just to
give you a flavor of how it works. In practice,
actually, definitely, it's better-- can be
much larger and more complicated. But here,
I'm just trying to show that a toy
example to walk through the size of
the feature maps and also the receptive
field to give you a sense about what's
the difference between early fusion and late
fusion and 3D convolution neural networks.
So for late fusion, you can think
of that, for example, in this case,
maybe originally the input is 3 times
20. 20, the temporal dimension. And 64,
64 is a spatial dimension. And you use a
2D convolution. Because we are doing late
fusion. We don't do anything over the temporal
dimension initially. We just keep the 20,
the temporal dimension. We just build
up the receptive field spatially.
Now, we have a convolution 2D layer to
map the channel dimension from 3 to 12,
but just keep the temporal dimension 20.
And then gradually, maybe we use some
pooling layers. Still, we didn't do anything
with the temporal dimension. So it's still 20.
But because of the pooling operation, we build
up the receptive field in the spatial dimension.
And then gradually, we maybe use another
2D layer. And now, the feature map is 24
times 20 times 16 times 16. And we also gradually
increase the spatial receptive field, but it will
still keep the temporal dimension 20. So we
didn't do anything over the temporal dimension.
And finally, just using a single global
average pooling, we pull across the feature
maps 20 times 16 times 16. So we pull over
both time in the spatial dimension. And now,
we get from this 20 times 16 times 16. We get a
1 times 1 times 1 feature point. So basically,
we collapse everything in the
final single layer. And we build
up the temporal receptive field in a
single layer. So that's a late fusion.
So then for early fusion,
what's the difference? So now,
instead of building slowly in
space or at once in time at N,
now, we are building slowly in space and all
at once in time at the very beginning. So the
input is still 3 times 20 times 64 times 64. But
now, we're just using a single conv 2D layer.
Now, we just treat this 3 times 20 as a
single-- the channel dimension. We just
map everything. There's 3 times 30. Just
treat all of them as channel dimension,
and then map them to 12. So basically, we use a
single convolution layer, 2D convolution layer,
to collapse all the temporal
information from the very beginning.
So we build the temporal receptive field
in the first layer. So now, the temporal
receptive field becomes from 1 to 20. And then
the spatial receptive field gradually builds
up. And we use pooling and conv 2D to build
up the spatial dimension just as late fusion.
And finally, we use the global average
pooling. Now, with global average pooling
is only just trying to doing the averaging,
doing the pooling across space. So we build
slowly in space, but all at once at the
very beginning. So that's early fusion.
So then, what is the 3D convolution neural
networks? So for 3D convolution layer, basically
we build slowly both in space and time. So
that's why we call it the slow fusion. So the
input can still be the same 3-- times 20 times 64
times 64. But now, we are using 3D convolutions.
So in the first layer, we just-- to map things
from 3 to 12. But we also just keep the temporal
dimension in this case. And then we build
up a little bit temporal receptive field
and a spatial receptive field. And then
we use a pooling layer. And then 4 times
4 times 4 for pooling layer. And then we pull
a little bit of this temporal feature and also
spatial features. And then we further build up
both the spatial and temporal receptive field.
And we have another conv 3D layer, and
then to further build up the spatial and
temporal receptive field. And finally, we're
using a global average pooling. But now,
we're pooling over these 4 times 16 times 16
feature map, and then to further increase the
temporal and spatial receptive field. So we are
building up gradually in both space and time.
So that's the difference between early fusion,
late fusion, and 3D convolution neural networks.
So you can see that for the early fusion and
3D convolution neural networks. So both of them
builds receptive fields over time. But what's
the actual difference? So let's look at it
more closely here. So if we think of it as a
feature vector for each spatial grid point,
so the common filter, if it's a 2D
convolution, for this grid point,
it will consider all the temporal
dimensions. T is equal to 16.
So it is local in space but extends fully
in time. That's the filter in 2D convolution
neural network. But what is the problem?
Think about it. So if we directly just go
all the way through time dimension in this 2D
convolution, what problem is going to happen?
So the shortcoming of that is that there will
be no temporal shift invariance. It's because
the 2D, the filter, now extends fully in
time. So if we want to learn some global
transition in color of different
time, for example, if we want to--
because it's a video. It's something that
we want to recognize temporal information.
If there are some changes from blue
to orange at different time step,
maybe there is some change that is happening
at time step 4. There's another same change
that is happening at time step 15. But
it's the same change from blue to orange.
If we go all the way through time, the filter
extends fully in time, then if we want to learn
the global transition at different times, then we
have to have a whole separate filter in order to
learn this. So we have to learn a different--
this kernel in order to learn these different
transitions across at different time steps.
So there is no temporal shift invariance.
So how to recognize this kind of blue to orange
transition just anywhere in space and time? Just
like when we are doing image classification, we
want to have some spatial invariance. We want to
be able to recognize the image contains a cat. No
matter where the cat is on the right corner left
corner, we want to share the kernels to be able to
recognize things at a different spatial location.
Here, we want to be able to learn
these different types of motion,
different types of temporal patterns at different
temporal time steps. So that's similar idea. So
then, that's exactly the benefit of 3D
convolution neural networks. Right now,
instead of extends fully in time, in
this T dimension, originally for this
early version T, extends all the way in
the temporal dimension T is equal to 16.
But now if, T is equal to 3. And we can
slide over the temporal dimension. Just
like we learned spatial invariance
using filter and local regions. Now,
this conv filter only spans a local window
in time and slide over in the time dimension.
So then, the benefit is that now, we can have some
temporal shift invariance. Because each filter
slides over time. So we can reuse this filter to
recognize different motion patterns across these
dimensions. So the transition from blue to orange
can now be recognized at every moment in time.
And then, the benefit of this is that we don't
have to have separate filters. Now, we are more
representation efficient. We don't need to learn
separate filters anymore. So that's basically
the main difference between 2D conv early
fusion and the 3D convolution neural network.
And also, in the last lecture,
I think, you have already also
seen some examples of some tools that we can
use to visualize what we have learned in a 2D
convolution neural networks. Similarly, we
can also visualize filters just for this 3D
convolution networks as these video clips. You
can see that-- I'm not sure if you can see it.
The learned filters from the 3D convolution neural
networks, because now the filter extends both in
space and time, so we can see that as a video
clip. And you can see that for these filters,
some of them are just like those filters
you have seen for image classifier.
You can have this color patterns and also
these different edges. But you can also
see that there are some other filters. There
are some temporal transition from one corner
to another or from some one edge pattern
to another. And some doesn't learn motion,
and some maybe focus on just the color patterns.
But some learns motion in different directions.
So we can just visualize these kernels
like this to interpret them. Basically,
two difference-- one is this slow fusion.
In terms of convolution operation, yeah,
indeed, basically 3D convolution.
3D convolution, definitely.
And 2D convolution, they are totally different.
You have another dimension of convolution. You
have this temporal dimension. So the
difference is you have this temporal
dimension in the convolution operation. But
practically, you use 3D convolution neural
networks. It gradually builds this
receptive field over space and time.
So we have talked about this tools, 3D
convolution networks or architectures.
But what data we can use just like
ImageNet? Or what data we can use
to do video to train a video classifier? So
one example dataset, challenge dataset that
people have been tackling is this dataset called
Sports 1 million, which was introduced in 2014.
So for this dataset, you can see what tasks
we can do. We can do very, very fine-grained
sports category classification.
You can see here the blue shows,
the ground shoes. And yellow, it shows
the top five predictions. And the green
shows the correct prediction. And the
red shows the incorrect prediction.
You can see that the action
categories in the dataset is very,
very fine-grain. There are 487 different
types of sports. There can be marathon,
ultra marathon. Actually, I don't
know the difference between them,
but it's very [INAUDIBLE] to different
types of sports categories in this dataset.
And here are some results if we train these
different types of classifiers we have talked
about on this Sports 1 million dataset. So
one very shocking results you can probably
see here is that for this single frame model
that I asked you to try, if you want to develop
some video classification model, is that
it actually has a very good performance.
You can see that the single frame model, if you
just treat it as an image classifier, it actually
gives you 77.7 classification, top five accuracy.
And for the early fusion we talked about,
it actually has a slightly worse performance. And
for late fusion is slightly better. And if we use
3D convolutional neural networks, in this case,
on this dataset, it gets like a 2% to 3% boost.
So the takeaway message here is that,
definitely, you should try the single
frame model. [INAUDIBLE] actually works pretty
well. But the 3D convolution neural networks--
I showed here is the 3D convolution neural
network used in 2014. But over the past 10 years,
we have seen a lot of advancements.
So the numbers are also getting much,
much better, as I'm going to
talk about in the later slides.
For both training and testing, it's
just treating videos as images and
train an image classifier. That's exactly
what a single frame is doing. Basically,
if I understand question correctly,
it's using image classifier. But it's
training on a lot of frames on videos.
It's not a single frame in each video.
And also, because this dataset is a
huge dataset. Because like I mentioned,
videos are very huge. When people sharing
video datasets, we cannot just share them
just like ImageNet. People can download from,
some database because videos are really huge. Like
this dataset has maybe 1 million videos. It's not
very doable to download all of them, to share it.
Actually, this video actually, originally, when
it was released, is shared as a list of URLs,
YouTube URLs. But one thing you can expect
from this YouTube video URLs is that people
modify their videos and delete their
videos. And so that original list maybe
have 1 million videos. But now, I guess,
maybe half of the videos are already gone
or maybe not there. So this dataset is
not very stable because of this reason.
So like I mentioned, 3D convolution neural
networks have been improving gradually since
May 2014. So one early popular version of
this 3D convolution network is this model
called [? C3N ?] network. So basically,
it's actually very simple. Basically,
it's very similar to the VGG architecture
we use for 2D image classification.
But now, we just convert things to three-dimension
convolution neural network. And for example,
for the 3D CNN, you use 3 times 3 times
3 conv and 2 times 2 times 2 pooling.
And except maybe for the first layer, it has
some changes. So the overall architecture is
very similar to VGG architecture. It's
now just we have this extra dimension.
And so that's why it's called the
VGG of 3D CNNs. And the model,
it was trained on this Sports 1 million dataset
said that I just mentioned, and because it
was introduced like in 2014. And at that time,
imagine that you want to train such a model.
It needs a lot of compute because not too many
people have access to a lot of GPUs at that time.
So actually, this model was trained at Facebook.
And they released this model, the pre-trained
weights, they train the 3D model on Sports 1
million, and then they released the feature
pre-trained model as a feature extractor.
So many people actually who cannot afford
to train a video model themselves, they actually
started to use this model as a feature extractor.
So they can just take a video
and extract features from this
using this pre-trained model. So a
3D model, and then maybe train some
other linear classifier. So people start
to use it. That's why it got popular.
So the question basically is about what we're
talking about, [INAUDIBLE] classification about
how many frames we should take as input in
terms to extract the features? So basically,
for all these models we are talking about,
we assume that we are just passing a clip,
a predefined length, like 16 frames or 32 frames
to train a single model that always takes 16
frames or 32 frames as input. And there are other
techniques we can talk about, how we're going to
aggregate this clip level prediction. But for now,
we're just doing clip level feature extraction.
So the downside of this 3D CNN is that it's
very computationally expensive. Basically,
we just directly, in a brute force way,
we just make this VGG style from 2D to
3D. And you can see that for AlexNet. For this
GFLOP, basically, what it means is that it's
like gigaflops. It's trying to measure how
many floating point operations you need for
a single forward pass, basically just trying to
measure whether the network is efficient or not.
So for AlexNet, it takes 0.7 GFLOPS. For
VGG-16, it takes like 13.6 GFLOPS. But for C3D,
you are actually doing this kind of mapping from
2D to 3D. And now, it takes like 39.5 GFLOPS. So
it's 2.9 times VGG, so it's not very efficient.
So that's the downside of this kind of network.
And if we look at the performance on
Sports 1 million, this is just 360 now,
gets about 4% gain in terms of top five
accuracy. So this is just one example
of the 3D convolution network we can do.
But there definitely can be other things
right. We are talking about a lot of tricks
that we can do for 2D image classification.
We can have this residue connections like
you have seen in ResNet. But definitely,
we can also do that just to improve, say, 3D
to adding some residual connections or other
techniques we talked about in 2D convolutions.
And indeed, there are also a lot of work on
trying to improve this, different types of
video architectures, and also papers on that.
But apart from that, let's think maybe a little
bit more on whether we should treat space and
time in a separate way. Because that, indeed,
very different things-- spatial information,
temporal information. So maybe
we should actually explicit,
try to model things that exists
there temporally. That is motion.
So humans actually can do incredible
job processing motion. So maybe
take a guess what actions the
humans are doing here in this
simple video/ You can say it out
if you want. What's this? Sitting.
Yeah, just from these very- few points, you
can actually do a good job just to recognize
what actions that this person is
doing or maybe two persons. Now,
there are not any appearance information.
Just a few points. Just motion.
We can actually have a very good
understanding about some activities
that is going on in these videos. So that's
why how we process appearance and motion
might be very different. Maybe we should have
separate networks to process them. So indeed,
that's kind of motivation for this
work that was introduced in 2014.
And they are trying to propose a two-stream
network to process appearance information and
the motion information separately. So basically,
one way to explicitly measure of motion is to use
this concept called optical flow. So for
optical flow, basically, the idea is that
we want to measure the motion, the changes of
the motion, of the pixels in adjacent frames.
Basically, for the first frame, for every pixel,
how it's going to move in the second
frame. So it calculates the velocity
for points within the frames and provides
an estimation of where the points could be
in the next frame, a sequence. For example,
in this case, like for frame T and p plus 1.
Basically, this flow field, here are two
dimensions, and tells where each pixel will
move in the next frame. So F(x, y) is equal to
(dx, dy). And then the I t plus 1 (x plus dx),
that's where the pixel, E, in the next frame
and is equal to I t (x, y) in the current frame.
So it's a way to measure, explicitly measure
motion of the pixels. So there are many papers
actually on doing research and also how to
actually compute optic flow given a pair of
frames. There are ways to make different types
of assumptions. Some work assume the optic flow,
just assumes brightly stays constant as things
move. And then trying to propose some
techniques to compute this optic flow.
But once you get it, it basically
captures the motion information
for two adjacent frames. And also, these
are two dimensions because it's trying to
capture how pixels move horizontally
and vertically. So you can actually also
visualize it separately. You can visualize
it the horizontal motion, horizontal flow,
dx. And also you can visualize the vertical
flow dy. You can see that it captures some
horizontal motion, the vertical motion. So we
capture this kind of low level motion cues.
So once you have a way to capture this
kind of motion cues as optical flow,
then people trying to propose two-stream networks
to train a motion classifier and appearance
classifier. So this is a famous two-stream network
for action recognition. So basically, it has a one
single frame model that's doing appearance
classification to tell what action it is.
And then you have a separate stream. That's the
temporal stream ConvNet that takes this multiframe
optic flow. For every two adjacent frames,
it computes the optical flow map. And also,
it separately treats the horizontal motion
optical flow and vertical flow. And then stack
them together. And then they process them using
a temporal stream convolution neural network.
And then you make a prediction. And
then they aggregate the prediction
results for both the motion stream
and the appearance stream to get the
final prediction. So that's the
idea of this two-stream network.
And it actually works pretty good. It's on
another dataset called UCF-101. There are
101 action categories in this dataset.
So you can see that-- one surprising
thing you can see that is using only motion
actually works very well, surprisingly well.
You see the performance of 3D convolution network
and spatial only. And that's only the appearance
string. And the temporal only, that's the
motion stream. You can see that the motion
stream actually works much better compared to
the spatial only stream, the appearance stream.
So my hypothesis is that it's less easier
to overfit. Because for the motion,
there are a lot of background information,
which may be not important for the background,
for the action classification.
But for the motion stream,
it actually contains the key
information, the movements,
which are less easier to overfit. Actually,
you can get better results on this dataset.
So, so far, we have been talking about short
term structures in videos. And also earlier,
I think folks asking about how many
frames we should use actually to do
the classification? So definitely,
it's very important to modeling the
long-term temporal structure to
recognize more distant in time.
So we already know actually. I already
have the tools to handle sequences
to use recurrent networks, to process a
sequence of words to doing some caption
tasks and some prediction tasks. So we can also
use similar tools, just recurrent neural networks.
We just have a convolutional neural networks. No
matter whether it's a single frame convolutional
networks to get a 2D feature vector or use a 3D
convolution network to get a feature vector from
a clip. But you have a much longer video. We
can get a feature vector, and then we just use
the RNs or LSTMs we have talked about, to
model the long-term temporal structure.
We just process the local features using this
recurrent networks and make a final prediction
at the last time step if we want to do
a single video level classification,
where we're just doing a many to one output
at the end of the video. And we can also do
one to one mapping like we talked about.
So for each frame, we can make a prediction.
Maybe there are some predictions we want to make
for each video frame. And we can also get this
output from LSTM or recurrent neural network.
And actually, this kind of idea has already been
explored in 2011. Actually, that's way ahead of
its time. Because AlexNet was introduced in 2012.
So, but it's more popularized by this 2015 paper.
So if you want to train this kind of
recurrent architectures for modeling
long-term temporal structure, you can often
only backpropagate through this [INAUDIBLE]. Or
you can fuse the CNNs. You can
pre-train them on some clips,
on image classification. And otherwise, you
have a huge network with recurrent part,
this convolution part. It's very hard to
train them end to end. So you can just use
it [INAUDIBLE] 3D as a feature extractor
and train this recurrent neural networks.
And we have already seen two approaches to model
the temporal structure. How about we can combine
these two approaches, This convolution neural
networks and this recurrent neural network.
Both of them has some advantages. So we
can maybe just combine them in a single
architecture to process this video data.
So indeed, we can take some inspiration from
this multi-layer recurrent neural networks we
have talked about. So each timestep can take
these previous hidden timestep from the same
layer, and also the output from
the same timestep from the previous
layer. That's basically the
idea of this multi-layer RNN.
But similarly, we can just do it for videos.
Now, we introduce this recurrent convolution
neural networks. It's very similar. It's just now,
we build this grid of features, where each one is
a three-dimensional vector. Like two spatial
dimension, and the one is a channel dimension.
So each feature vector, it's like the
fourth dimension C times H times W.
So each depends on two inputs for
each vector. For each feature map,
it depends on the feature map from the
same layer by the previous timestep. But
it also depends on the feature map from
the previous layer but the same timestep.
So you record in 2D convolution network,
where we just map this feature map from
some input feature to an output feature. But
here for this recurrent convolution network,
we can just use as input these two 3D tensors.
One from the same layer and previous timestep,
and one from the previous
layer at the same timestep.
So you recall that the recurrent network, you have
this form of it has some hidden layer feature map,
ht minus 1. It takes the input of this current
timestep, have some function with some parameter
W. And then process the new state feature
vector ht. That's basically the key of RNN.
So now, instead, we just change these
vectors forms of RNN. We just replace
all this matrix multiplication in recurrent
neural networks with 2D convolutions. Now,
we get this recurrent convolution neural
networks. So we have the feature map.
You do 2D convolution instead have this
matrix multiplication. We get another
feature map. And also for features from
the previous layer, the same timestep,
also do this. And then after doing this
2D convolution, we add them together,
use another tanh layer, and then we get the
feature map for the current hidden layer.
So that's basically the idea of recurrent
convolution neural network. Basically, we
can combine convolution operations and recurrent
operations. And we can also actually do this
for any kind of recurrent neural network
variants like GRUs and LSTMs, maybe you
have already learned from previous class.
And so now, we can successfully combine
the benefits of the two. We have this both
spatial and temporal fusion inside this recurrent
convolution neural network. But this model was not
used too much because there's one large downside
of recurrent networks, which you may have already
learned that RNNs are very slow for processing
non-sequence. And videos are usually very, very,
long, and you have to be process them in parallel.
But RNNs are very hard to be parallelized.
But there's another important model we have
learned, I think in the previous lectures,
what we can do. We can also use operations
like the self-attention to process videos. For
self-attention, you have this queries, keys,
and values. And you can use self-attention
layer as a standalone operation to process
images. Here, we can also do it for videos.
And one very large advantage of self-attention
is highly parallelizable. And all the alignment
and these attention scores for all the inputs can
be done completely in parallel. So indeed, people
are trying to use self-attention also in videos.
So they just pause self-attention directly to 3D.
Maybe you have some 3D convolution
neural network. You get some feature
map like C times T times H times W. And
then similarly, you can get some query
feature maps. You can use some 1 times
1 times 1 3D convolutions to change the
channel dimension to map them to query feature
map that is C prime times T times H times W.
Similarly for keys, you get this feature map
for values, get this feature maps. And then you
want to get some attention weights. Basically,
you're doing some transpose of this feature map
from queries. And the vectorized multiplication
get a attention score for each query and key
feature pair. And then you can get this attention
map and then use it to condition the values.
And you can get another value, a feature map.
And then you can map them. Use another 1 times
1 times 1 convolution to map them back
to the same dimension C so that it can
be concatenated with the original feature input.
So that is a residual connection. So in total,
you can see that it's very similar
to the self-attention operations.
But now, we move things to 3D. And this
is one block that is very independent.
It can stand on its own. So you see in
this paper, it's called nonlocal neural
network. It introduces block, and call
it a nonlocal block. You can use it as
a building block for processing
videos, to do video understanding.
For example, you can just add this
on nonlocal blocks into existing
3D convolution neural network architectures.
And to have some 3D CNN on a nonlocal block,
and another block of 3D CNN add on a nonlocal
block. And each nonlocal block, basically,
is very powerful to fuse across both space and
time, and finally, into this classification.
So the one thing we haven't talked about is
what is this 3D convolution neural network?
So what we should use here? So a
very interesting idea that people
have explored in the past that can is,
can we reuse the 2D convolution neural
Network many successful architectures we have
talked about or have learned, directly to 3D.
We just do some inflation of this 2D networks. So
then, we can get a 3D convolution neural networks.
So for this work, it's called I3D architecture.
The idea is that they just take a 2D CNN
architecture. They replace each 2D conv pool, the
layer that originates of dimension Kh times Kw.
But now, we replace with a 3D version, that is a
Kt times Kh times Kw, just inflated basically. And
they use it on top of the inception block. And
then after they're doing this inflation, then
you have an architecture for processing videos,
directly just reuse the existing architectures.
And now, we can transfer the architecture
that works pretty well in 2D to work
also in 3D. But taking one step
further, people also have been
trying things that not only we can transfer the
architectures. But actually, we also can transfer
the weights. Because we have already pre-trained
a lot of architectures models on image datasets.
Maybe we can actually reuse the weights
we have learned there. There are maybe
some good prior information. So one thing
you can do is that you can just initialize
the inflated CNN with weights trained on images.
For example, you have maybe for one-- originally,
you have this 2D conv kernel. You just copy the
kernel by Kt times. And you divide it by Kt.
And originally takes one single image as input.
Now, you take this video of 3 times Kt times H
times w as input because we have divided them
by Kt. And you just use this inflated version
and copy the weights by Kt times. And then you
will get the same output if you just input a
single frame or a video of constant frames.
So now, we have a way to recycle this existing 2D
image based on this architecture and weights from
2D image understanding. And actually, it works
pretty well. So if you look at the performance,
you inflate them. Compared to this two-stream
convolutional network, it actually has better
performance. And you can also inflate
actually not only the appearance frame.
You can also inflate a motion stream. So
it actually gets some further improvements.
Basically, this is just like a technique you
can do to reuse this kind of independent from
the 3D convolutional networks. You can build
this non-local blocks, this part. And what I'm
trying to say is that we have a lot of 2D
convolution neural networks, the weights.
Successful people have shown that they are
very successful. And if we want to reuse them,
people have shown that they can actually
copy the weights and reuse their weights,
directly use them to operate on videos. So
that basically, that's the high level idea.
And after doing this initialization, you can
still fine tune on the video data. But you have
the pre-trained weights from images. So then,
we can give you some good initialization
for training the video models. So this
idea of this I3D network basically is trying
to copy the weights and doing the inflation.
So this is also just one example of this
video understanding net model. And there
are also many other video transfer model
proposed for video understanding. That is,
for example, this work, space-time
attention is trying to do more factorized
attention to attend both space and time.
And also, there are some other methods trying to
be more efficient in terms of this transformer
architecture. Or this mask autoencoder you have
heard about doing more efficient, scalable video,
video level pre-training to doing video
understanding. So I'm not going to talk them
here in the class. But if you are interested,
you can check out their papers. Because there
are also many progress has been made to
have better media understanding models.
And if you look at the performance of
progress that way, I think we started
from a single-frame model 62.2 on this--
this is another dataset, Kinetics-400.
It's a large video dataset. And then, you can
see that for this video model encoder, now,
it already gets to 90% accuracy. So there are some
other-- new transformer model has been proposed.
So we are doing very well on classifying the
videos. And similar to the image classification
in the last class, we can also use similar
tricks for visualizing video models. So we can
take in this two-stream network as an example.
We can randomly initialize a appearance image
and the flow image doing-- we are doing a
forward pass, and then compute the score.
And then we can back propagate with
respect to the score of a particular
class and using gradient ascent to maximize the
classification score. Just like what we're doing
the visualization for the image-based
model. So then, it's this way that we
can visualize doing some visualization,
interpretation of what has been learned.
So the left is the optimized image for appearance
string. Maybe it's hard to guess what is maybe
happening in the visual stream. On the right,
it's optimized image for the flow stream. One
has some temporal constraints to prevent the
temporal stream to change too fast. So you
can capture slow motion. And the other captures
right motion. So you can guess what the action is.
And maybe in this case, it's pretty clear. So what
action is this. So this is a weightlifting. You
can see that-- the middle one is doing some
bar shaking. And the right one is doing some
pushing overhead, the motion. So it's
indeed actually-- you can see that this
video model is actually-- which models
are learning something about this motion,
So so far, I have been talking about how we
can classify these short clips-- the swimming,
running. But another very important thing
is that how we can-- other task is that
this is called temporal action localization
is that not only we want to just doing clip
level or a classification. Sometimes, we want to
localize, just we want to do object detection.
Now, we want to localize where in the video
the action is happening. Maybe sometimes the
person is running. Sometimes, it's jumping.
So there is another task. This is another
class called temporal action localization.
You can also use similar ideas from faster
R-CNN. You can just generate some temporal
proposals and then doing the classification.
And also, you can also do both. This is
a spatial temporal detection. Basically,
you want to localize not only in space but also
in time. Where the action is happening in space.
Where the action is happening temporally. So this
is another task called spatial temporal detection.
So so far, I have been talking
about the temporal stream and
the architectures we can use to do
3D CNN, two-stream neural networks,
spatial-temporal self-attention. And we have
already talked about some tools to do that.
But yeah, maybe in the final 10 minutes,
let's just revisit. I hope to finish
in time. Let's revisit the
example that we started today,
where I showed you a video. But that's
still maybe not the full picture.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[BABY LAUGHING]
[DOG BARKING]
[END PLAYBACK]
So we are looking at video.
I think video understanding,
there is another very important dimension that
we have never covered until now. That is this,
there is sound. There is audio. There
is other modalities in videos. If we
miss that ingredient, you lose a lot of
fun. There's emotions you can perceive.
There's another interactions you can do
if you combine this visual and motion.
So if we have this audio in mind
and we have this vision stream,
then people also have proposed many
other interesting tasks. And also,
we have explored other tasks to doing video
understanding. Here's another example that
in videos that maybe there are some
multiple objects, multiple speakers.
And you can actually-- one task, example
task that I also personally have explored
in the past with a visually-guided audio
source separation. And you can actually
understand trying to process things visually and
acoustically. You can use the visual information
to guide the source separation. You want to
separate the sound components. Originally,
maybe there's a mixture. You want to
use the visual information to separate
into some sound components. This is called
visually-guided audio source separation.
So just to give you an example for this task.
For example, here is a speech mixture. Maybe
sometimes, you want to hear the sounds for
each person individually. And then we can use
their visual information, audio information
to process them together, to separate their
sounds. So here is what we can do. We can
separate the voice for the left speakers.
So only we can do this for people, for
speech. When we have to process audio and
speech and the visual stream. But we can
also do this for other types of sounds,
like music instruments. Here's another
example. We can even do musical instruments
separation by analyzing the motion,
the object-centric information with
the audio stream and doing the separation.
So this is another example for this task.
And also, once we introduce this
new modality of audio, we just want
to do video understanding classification.
Audio can also be useful cues. So indeed,
there are other work, audio-visual
video understanding work proposed
from transformer attention-based models, not
only we want to map images, videos to patches.
But also, map those audio spectrum to patches
and use some transformer architectures to
doing the classification. Or even, we
can do some mask autoencoder style. We
want to predict the patches for the images and
also spectrograms doing video understanding.
And also, another aspect people have
been exploring is how to do efficient
video understanding. So I will just quickly give
some examples. So here, throughout this class,
I think I'm mainly focusing on clip level
classification. Just giving a clip, how to doing
this classification. And after we classify a lot
of clips and we want to aggregate the information
to get a video level predictions. That's
action recognition in long videos.
So for efficient video understanding,
why we would want to do efficient video
understanding? Because videos are very
long. We cannot afford to process every
clip one by one. So that we're trying to
increase the efficiency for a single clip
just to building like this X3D is trying to
build better 3D convolution neural network.
But also, that we're trying to-- like this SD
sampler, trying to predict which clips are the
most useful. And then you can only combine the
predictions. Only run your clip classifier on
those important clips. And also, they are doing
policy learning, trying to predict which modality
we should use in order to doing this action
classification we can select, or whether we want
to use video, or how many video clips, or whether
we want to use audio or other sensory data.
So here's one example that we can also
use audio, as a preview mechanism,
to predict where are the important
moments. And then we use that
as a guiding clue to process the clips and
to average the results. So that's about the
efficient video understanding. So
that's also one area of research.
And also, nowadays, there are people moving
to VR and AR, the smart glasses. And also now,
in the future, I'm guessing there are a
lot of egocentric video streams. That's
another aspect of video understanding. So
not only you have this egocentric videos,
but you also have this multi-microphone,
microphone array, multi-channel audios.
So how to doing better under video understanding
from this egocentric multimodal egocentric
video streams is also a hot topic. Maybe
we have explored that we can use processes
video streams, the audio, multichannel audio,
and visual information to predict who is speaking
to whom and who is listening to whom. Imagine,
in the future, you wear these smart glasses.
You want to use it to help you to understand
these different types of social interactions.
So that's an egocentric video understanding.
So my final slide, definitely, LLMs right now,
there are also a lot of ongoing work
trying to build video level foundation
models. How to collect the video understanding to
LLMs? So indeed, there are works trying to just
map the videos to tokenize them and map them to
the LLM embedding space and maybe prompt the video
foundation model-- where the person is--
what the person is doing in the video.
And then you output some text to describe
the videos. So there are many work trying
to collect video understanding, LLMs.
So that's also a hot topic right now.