All right, welcome back,
everyone, to lecture eight.
Today, we're going to talk about
attention and transformers.
And I think this is
a really fun one.
So as a quick
recap, last time, we
were talking about
recurrent neural networks.
And recurrent neural networks
were this new neural network
architecture meant for
processing sequences.
And in particular, we saw how
neural networks, by processing
sequences, let us attack a whole
new different kinds of problems
than we could with
convolutional networks before.
So in particular,
usually, we had
been thinking about these
one-to-one problems, where
you input one thing like an
image and then output one thing
like a classification
for what's in that image.
But once you have the
ability to move beyond images
and move towards
sequences of data,
it let us tackle a lot
of new kinds of problems,
like one to many problems,
image captioning.
Maybe we want to input an image,
output a textual description
of that image, which is going
to be a sequence of words, maybe
many to one, where we do input
a sequence of frames and output
a classification
for those frames,
and a bunch of other
problems along this vein.
So now, we're seeing that moving
into these more sophisticated
neural network
architectures, both
is more interesting,
architecturally,
but also lets us
tackle new problems
than we could with more
traditional feedforward neural
networks.
So today, we're going
to build on that
and talk about two new
things in today's lecture.
The first thing is
going to be attention,
which is going to be a
brand new neural network
primitive that fundamentally
operates on sets of vectors.
And then the second thing
we're going to talk about
is the transformer.
And the transformer is a
different neural network
architecture that has
self-attention at its core.
And the spoiler alert is that
transformers are basically
the architecture that we
use for almost all problems
in deep learning today.
So any of the largest
applications that you're
seeing out there
in the wild today,
whether it's classifying images,
generating images, generating
text, classifying text,
working with audio, basically,
any kind of large neural
network today that is large,
state of the art, trained
in a lot of data, deployed
by a big company,
almost all of them
are going to be
transformers today.
So that's really exciting
that we to get you up
to speed on the latest
and greatest architectures
that people are using now.
But even though transformers
are this state of the art
architecture that everyone is
using for everything today,
they have a relatively
long history.
And they initially--
it's interesting
watching these fields develop.
Because looking back on it, when
the moment that transformers
came out, it feels
like it ought to have
been this big moment,
this big thing when
there was a big sea change,
this new architecture,
this new thing.
But it actually
didn't feel that way.
Because even though there was
one moment where the transformer
architecture was born,
these ideas around
self-attention, around using
attention in various ways,
those had actually been around
in the field for several years
at that time.
And in particular, these ideas
around attention self-attention,
they actually developed out
of recurrent neural networks.
So we're going to start there
to talk about and motivate
these problems.
So this is going
to be a little bit
mirroring the historical
development of these ideas.
So for that reason, we're
actually going to-- in order
to introduce transformers,
we're actually
going to roll back
and recap a little bit
about this idea of
recurrent neural networks
that we saw in the last lecture.
So as a motivating problem,
let's think about this sequence
to sequence problem
of translation.
So we want to
input one sequence,
which is going to be a
sequence of words in English.
Then we want to output
another sequence,
which is going to be
a sequence of words
in a different language, Italian
And we can't make assumptions
that there's any correspondence
between those words.
The number of words in
the English sentence
might be different from
the number of words
in the Italian sentence.
And the order of those words
might be totally different.
So this is a perfect application
of the kind of sequence
processing algorithms
that we-- sequence
processing architectures
that we saw
in recurrent neural networks.
And indeed, this idea of
processing these sequence
to sequence problems with
recurrent neural networks, this
goes all the way back to 2014,
even a bit earlier than that.
But people have been
processing sequences
with recurrent neural networks
for more than a decade
at this point.
So the basic architecture
for processing sequence
to sequence problems with
recurrent neural networks
is that, typically, you'll
start with one encoder.
Your encoder is a
recurrent neural network.
The recurrent neural
network recall
is this function that
gets applied recursively
on two inputs.
One is your xt, your input
at the current time step.
And the other is
your ht minus 1,
which is your hidden state
at the previous time step.
And your recurrent
neural network unit
will then spit out
a next hidden unit--
a next hidden state
at the next time step.
And then we can apply that same
recurrent neural network unit
over in time to
process a sequence
of potentially variable length.
So in this case, we're using
a recurrent neural network
encoder that inputs the
input sequence in English.
Input sequence-- you got to
use relatively short sentences
to fit on slides and still
have all the boxes show up.
So we're using a kind of
short, silly sentence,
"We see the sky."
And this each word
in that sentence
gets processed via one tick of
the recurrent neural network.
And then the idea of this
encoder recurrent neural network
is it wants to process all of
the words in the input sequence
and somehow summarize the
content of that input sentence
so that we can translate it into
a different-- into our output
target language.
So the more concrete
way that this happens
is that after processing all
the words in the input sequence,
we are going to summarize the
entire content of that input
sequence into a single vector
called the context vector.
And there's a couple
of different ways
that people would
typically do these
in recurrent neural networks.
I don't think the details
are too interesting.
So you can just think that
context vector is basically
the last hidden state of
the encoder recurrent neural
network.
And now, the idea
is that because
of the recurrent structure
of recurrent neural networks,
the last hidden state
incorporates information
of the entire input sequence.
So we can think of
that last hidden state
as summarizing, or encoding
all of the information
in the entire input sequence.
So then that is
one vector that is
going to summarize that entire
input sequence to do whatever
we want with it.
And in this case, what
we want to do with
it is translate
that input sequence
into an output sequence
in a different language.
So to do that, we're going to
use a second recurrent neural
network, called the
decoder, which usually
has the same architecture but,
potentially, a different weight
matrix, different set
of learned parameters.
And this decoder,
gu, is going to be
a different recurrent neural
network with different learnable
weights, u, but has
the same basic idea.
Now, if our recurrent
neural network unit
is going to take three
inputs at every time step,
it's going to take
yt minus 1, which
is the token in the output
sequence at the previous time
step.
It's going to take st minus 1,
which is the previous hidden
state in the output
sequence, and C,
which is that context vector
summarizing the entire input
sequence.
And then we unroll
that output sequence
just as we saw in the last
lecture and produce words one
at a time in the
output sequence.
And I don't speak
Italian, so I'm not
going to try I'm not going
to try to pronounce these.
But there's some Italian words
on the screen that you can see.
And I'm assuming that, that
indeed translates to "We see
the sky."
Hopefully, that's correct.
But the idea is
we're going to tick
this recurrent neural
network one tick at a time.
It's going to output
words one at a time.
And this is basically a summary
of what we saw last lecture.
So this should this
should, basically,
not be too surprising in
light of the previous lecture.
But there's a
potential problem here.
And there's a
communication bottleneck
here between the input sequence
and the output sequence.
The only way in which the
input sequence is communicating
with the output sequence is
via that context vector C.
And that C is going
to be a fixed length
vector because the
size of that vector
is fixed when we set the size
of our recurrent neural network.
And maybe that's fine.
So C might be a fixed length
vector of like 128 floats,
1,024 floats.
But the size of that input
vector is not going to change,
as our input and output
sequence sizes grow or shrink.
And that's a potential problem.
So if we're doing short
sequences, like we see the sky,
maybe it seems pretty plausible
that we can summarize everything
we need to know about that
sequence in that fixed
vector of 120--
the 1,024 floats.
But what if we're not trying
to translate four words?
What if we're
trying to translate
a whole paragraph,
or a whole book,
or an entire corpus of data?
Then in that case, we're going
to run into a bottleneck, where,
at some point, as we
scale that input sequence,
it's just not going to be
sensible to ask the network
to summarize the
entire input sequence
into a single fixed
length vector.
So that's going to be a problem.
So the solution
here is, actually,
let's not bottleneck the network
through one fixed length vector.
Instead, let's change
the architecture
of our recurrent neural network.
Intuitively, what we want to
do is not force a bottleneck
in a fixed length vector between
the input and the output.
Instead, as we process
the output sequence,
we're going to give the model
the ability to look back
at the input sequence.
And now, every time it
produces an output vector,
we want to give the network
the opportunity to look back
at the entire input sequence.
And if we do this, there's
going to be no bottleneck.
It will scale to much
longer sequences.
And hopefully, the
model architecture
will work much better.
So that's the
motivating idea that
led to attention and
transformers and all
this great stuff
that we see today.
It all came-- one way
of telling the story
is that it all came from trying
to solve this bottleneck problem
in recurrent neural networks.
So let's see how we can actually
implement this intuition
and endow a recurrent neural
network with the ability
to look back at the input
sequence on every time step.
So here, we're going to
start with the same thing.
Our encoder neural network
is going to remain the same,
no changes there.
We still need to set
some initial hidden state
for the output sequence.
And so we need to set some
initial decoder state, s0,
in some way.
But now, once we have
that decoder hidden state,
what we're going to do is look
back at the input sequence.
So the way that
we're going to do
that is by computing some
alignment scores by comparing
that, basically,
compute a scalar
value for each step in the
input sequence that says,
how much does that
initial decoder state
s0, how much does that
decoder state match each token
of the input sequence?
So in this case, there were four
tokens in the input sequence.
So we want to compute four
alignment scores, each of which
is just a single
number that says,
what is the similarity
between the input sequence,
the token of the input sequence,
and this initial decoder state
s0?
Now, there's a lot
of ways that we could
implement alignment scores.
But a simple way is just
use a simple linear layer
that we're calling f sub att.
And so that linear layer
is going to input--
is going to concatenate the
decoder hidden state, s,
with one of the
encoder hidden states,
h, concatenate those
two into a vector,
and then apply a linear
transform that squashes that
down into a scalar.
And that's just
a linear operator
that can be put into
a computational graph
and learned jointly via gradient
descent, just in the way
that we learn all other
parameters of a network.
So now at this point, we've
got this scalar alignment score
for each step in
the input sequence.
And now, we want to
apply a softmax function.
These scalar alignment
scores are totally unbounded.
They're arbitrary real values
from minus infinity to infinity.
We want to put some
structure on this
to prevent things
from blowing up.
So one way that we do this
is apply a softmax function.
So we've got four
scalar values telling us
the alignment of that
decoder hidden state
with each of the
encoder hidden states.
Now, we apply a softmax
over those four values
to give us a distribution
over those four values.
So remember, the
softmax function
that we saw a few
lectures ago is going
to take a vector
of arbitrary scores
and convert it into a
probability distribution.
Which means it'll
have the property
that each entry in the
output softmax probabilities
will be between 0 and 1,
and they will sum to 1.
So we can think
of-- so whenever we
have whenever we run a
vector through a softmax,
we can think of the
thing we get out
as a probability
distribution, or rather,
a discrete probability
distribution
over those input scores.
So in this case--
so at this point, after we
take those alignment scores
and run them through a softmax,
what we've essentially done
is predicted a
distribution over the input
tokens, given that
decoder hidden state.
So now, what we want to do
is take that distribution
over the input
tokens and use them
to compute a vector summarizing
the information in the encoder.
So the way that we do that is we
take our attention scores, which
recall, are these numbers
a11, a12, a13, a14,
they're all between 0 and 1.
They sum to 1.
We're going to take a
linear combination now
of the encoder hidden
states, h1, h2, h3, h4
and take a linear combination
of those encoder hidden states
weighted by our
attention scores.
And this will give
us a context vector
that we're calling c1
here in purple, which
is going to summarize the
information in the encoder
sequence in some way that's
modulated by those attention
weights.
And now, at this point, so
then this c1 is basically
some linear combination of the
input encoder states, h1 to h4.
Things look basically
the same, as they
did in the non-attention case.
So we have our context vector.
We concatenate it with our first
token of the output sequence,
y0, pass that to our
recurrent unit to get both--
to get our next hidden state
of the decoder recurrent neural
network, as well as the first
output token from the decoder
recurrent neural network.
So basically, the structure
of that decoder RNN
did not really change.
All we did is rather than set,
we computed the context vector
in a different way using this
attention linear combination
mechanism.
But now, crucially,
so the intuition here
is that this context
vector basically
attends, or looks at different
parts of the input sequence that
is modulated by whatever the
output RNN wants to look at,
at this moment in time.
So for example,
part of the input--
as part of the input sequence
has this token, these two words
we see.
So then in trying to produce
that one word in Italian that
corresponds to we see,
the network probably
wants to go back and look at
those two words in the input
sequence in order to know
what output word to produce.
So we might expect--
we might want to have some-- we
might expect that, intuitively,
when trying to produce
the word, "vediamo,"
then the network will want to
look back at the words we see
and put higher attention
weights on those.
And it doesn't really
care about the sky
because those words are
not necessary for producing
that vediamo output.
And that's the
kind of intuition.
We're giving the
network, the ability
to look back at the
relevant parts of the input
sequence for the word that
it's trying to predict
at this moment in time.
And the other thing
to keep in mind
is that this is
all differentiable.
We don't need to
supervise the network.
We don't need to tell it which
words in the input sequence
were required for each
word in the output.
Instead, this is just a big
computational graph composed
of differentiable operations.
All of this can be learned
end-to-end via gradient descent.
So at the end of
the day, we're still
going to have this cross-entropy
softmax loss, where
the network is trying to
predict the tokens of the output
sequence.
And in the process
of trying to predict
the right tokens in
the output sequence,
it's going to learn
for itself how
to attend to different
parts of the input sequence.
So that's really critical.
If we had to go in and
supervise and tell the network
the alignment
between the two, it
would be very difficult
to get training data
for this kind of thing.
The question is, how do
we initialize the decoder?
We're actually using the
word-- you got to be careful,
we're using the
word "initialize"
a little bit overloaded here.
So one question is, the decoder
is itself a neural network that
has weights.
When we start
training that network,
we need to initialize
those weights in some way.
So then we will
typically initialize
the weights of the decoder
randomly and then optimize them
via gradient descent, just as we
do with any other neural network
weights.
But there's a second
notion of initialize.
Which is that when the
network is processing
a sequence, whatever its current
value of the weights are,
we need some way to set that
initial hidden state at the time
we start processing
an output sequence.
And in that case, we need
some rule, or some way
to set that initial hidden state
of the decoder output sequence.
There's a couple of different
mechanisms for this.
Sometimes, you
might initialize it
as the last hidden
state of the encoder
is one thing you'll
sometimes do.
You might have a linear
transform that projects--
has some learned projection
from the last decoder state
to the first--
from the last encoder state
to the first decoder state.
Or sometimes, people
even initialize
the first hidden state of
the decoder to be all zeros.
Any of those will work, as
long as you train the network
to expect that kind of input.
So the question is,
negations and XORs,
will this cause a problem?
Maybe.
This is a hard problem.
But then you need a lot
of data, a lot of flops
to try to hope the network
can disentangle this.
But basically, recurrent unit
takes three things as input.
It takes in the decoder.
It takes the previous hidden
state, the previous decoder
hidden state.
It takes the current
context vector.
And it takes the current
token in the output sequence.
And then from that, we
produce the next hidden state.
And then from the
next hidden state,
then we go and predict
the output token.
So that's actually
the same setup
as in the non-attention case.
I guess there's an
implicit connection
from-- there's a connection from
s0 to s1 that we're not drawing.
Well, so there should have been
another arrow from s0 to s1.
I think I just dropped the s0
arrow, so sorry about that.
Well, we're basically
letting the network
decide for itself to look
back at any part of the input
sequence that it thinks might be
relevant for the task at hand.
But the reason why we think
that this mechanism is plausible
and might be helpful
for the network
is because we know that
in a language task,
there often is some
kind of correspondence
between words in the output
and words in the input.
And we want to let the
network look back and pick out
which are the relevant bits
of the input for producing
this bit of the output.
But again, we're not
directly supervising it.
We're not telling it how to
use these attention scores.
But the intuition
is that we think
that's a plausible thing
that it might choose to do,
given this mechanism.
OK, so that's one
tick of the output.
And now, basically,
we do it again.
We do this whole process
again for every time
we tick the decoder RNN.
Remember, the problem
we were trying to solve
is that, previously, the
decoder was bottlenecking
through a single vector.
Now, we're going to compute--
instead of bottlenecking
through a single vector,
we're going to repeat this
whole process again and compute
a new context vector for the
second time step of the decoder
and let it go back and look
at the whole input sequence
yet again.
So now, basically,
given our s1, which
is our computed first
hidden state in the decoder,
we're going to go back.
You take s1, go back
and compute comparison,
and use our attention
mechanism to compute
similarity scores between s1
and all of the hidden states
in the encoder.
That will compute our
similarity scores,
using that exact same FATT, that
same linear projection that we
used at the first time step,
compute these alignment scores,
again, cram them through softmax
to get a new distribution
over the input sequence for
the second decoder time step,
and now compute a new
linear combination
of the encoder hidden
states, now weighted
by this new distribution that
we computed at the second time
step.
And this will basically give
us a new context vector, c2,
that now is a different
summarization of the input
sequence that's now computed
as a new linear combination
of the input encoder
hidden states.
And then the whole
thing iterates.
We have a new context vector.
We use that to run another
tick of our decoder RNN unit
that will now does include
that mysterious missing
arrow that wasn't there
on the previous time step.
So then given our
new context vector,
given the next token
of the output sequence,
and given the s1 hidden
state of the decoder,
we compute a new decoder
state, s2, and then from that,
compute another token
of the output sequence.
And again.
Remember, in this case,
it's producing il,
which maybe is "the"
according to the slide.
I hope that's true.
And then in this
case, there's maybe
a one-to-one correspondence
between the word
the network is trying to produce
for this sequence and one
of the words in the output-- and
one of the words in the input.
So we might expect
that the network should
put relatively high
attention weight
on just one of the words
in the input sequence
and relatively low attention
weight on all the other words,
in the input sequence.
But again, we don't
supervise this.
The network is
deciding for itself
how to make use of
this mechanism, all
driven by gradient descent
on our training task.
And this whole
thing is we're just
going to repeat that whole
process for every tick
of the decoder RNN.
So now, this basically
solved our problem.
We are no longer bottlenecking
the input sequence
through a single
fixed length vector.
Instead, we have
this new mechanism,
where at every time
step of the decoder,
the network looks back at
the entire input sequence,
re-summarizes the input sequence
to generate a new context
vector on the fly for this
one time step of the decoder,
and then uses that to
produce the outputs.
So this is a pretty
cool mechanism.
And this is called attention
because the network
is attending, or looking at
different parts of the input
sequence at every
moment in its output.
So we talked about
these attention weights.
And we said that
they were driven--
the network was
learning for itself,
how to set these attention
weights based on its training
data, based on
its training task.
And another really cool
thing about attention
is it also gives us a
way to introspect and see
what the network is
looking at, as it's
trying to solve this problem.
So we never told it
what the alignment
was between the input sequence
and the output sequence.
But by looking at
the attention weights
that the network predicts when
trying to solve this task,
we get a sense of what the
network was looking at,
while trying to
solve the problem.
So that gives us
a way to interpret
the processing of the
neural network in some way.
And so one thing that we can
do is then go and look at,
in the process of producing
a particular-- processing
a particular sequence,
what were the attention
weights that the
network predicted
when trying to do this task?
And we can visualize these
in a two-dimensional grid.
So here, we're looking
at an example of English
to French translation.
And across the top, we
have our input sequence.
The agreement on the
European Economic Area
was signed in August 1992.
And then running down the
rows is the output sequence,
which is in French, which I
will not attempt to pronounce.
But you can see that, basically,
through this attention
mechanism, for every--
remember, the way this
attention mechanism worked
is that each time the network
produced one of these words
in the output sequence,
it predicted a probability
distribution over the
entire input sequence.
So we visualize that
in that first row.
So if you look at the
first row of this matrix,
we're visualizing that predicted
probability distribution
over the entire input
English sentence.
And we see that when trying to
predict that first word, "le"
of the French sentence, then it
puts a lot of probability mass
on the English word "the" and
basically no probability mass
on any of the other words.
Then, when predicting the second
word of the output sequence,
remember, it goes back and
predicts a new distribution
over the entire input sequence.
And that's going to be the
second row in this matrix.
So you can see that
a chord, it puts
a lot of probability
mass on agreement
and then no probability
mass anywhere else.
So then that gives us some
sense that the network actually
did figure out the
alignment between the input
words and the output words when
doing this translation task.
And there's some interesting
patterns here that pop up.
When we look-- when we
see diagonal structures
in this attention
matrix, that means
that there was a one-to-one
correspondence between words
in order between the input
sequence and the output
sequence.
So in particular, we
see that the agreement
on "the," the first four
words of the input sequence,
correspond to this diagonal
structure in the attention
matrix.
So that means that the
network has decided for itself
that these first four
words of the input sequence
align, or match up, or
correspond to the first four
words of the input
sequence, and the same thing
for the last several words.
So again, we see this
diagonal structure
at the end of the sequence,
which means that August 1992,
or in August 1992 corresponds
to these last couple
words in the French sequence.
And again, there's this
one-to-one correspondence
between words in the output
and words in the input.
But we see some other
interesting stuff in the middle
here.
So in the middle, we see
European economic area.
But in the French,
we see words that
look kind of like those in
a slightly different order.
Good question, how does
it figure out the grammar?
That's the mystery
of deep learning.
But basically, we told that-- we
didn't tell the network anything
about grammar.
We told the network--
we supervised it
with a lot of
input, output pairs.
We told it, here's an
input sequence in English.
Here's an output
sequence in French.
Here's a mechanism
for processing this
and learn via gradient
descent to set
the weights of this
architecture in order
to produce this output
from this input.
We'd never told it
anything about grammar.
But it kind of-- because
we, as human designers,
have this intuition that
maybe it makes sense
that there ought to be some
correspondence between some
of the words, so we bake in
a mechanism that we think,
as human designers, might
be helpful for solving
this problem.
And the network
figures out for itself,
in the process of doing
the end-to-end task, how
to make use of that mechanism to
solve the problem we set for it.
And it's pretty
amazing that it works.
But in this case, it figured out
some of the grammar for itself.
So it sees that we see
this non-diagonal, sort
of backward diagonal in
the attention matrix here.
And that means that
the network figured out
for itself, this different word
order between words in English
and words in French.
Or in the middle, you see
there's a little two by two grid
here.
And that corresponds to a
situation, where there might not
have been a one-to-one
correspondence
between the English words
and the French words.
There might have been two
French words that corresponded
to two English words and
they didn't perfectly
disentangle perfectly.
I mean, the network just all
figures out this for itself
over the process of
training on a lot of data
and putting a lot of
compute through this.
And that's pretty cool.
OK, so there's actually--
and this actually was the
initial usage of attention
in machine learning.
It actually came from these
machine translation problems.
So this was from a
paper back in 2015,
'Neural Machine Translation'
by jointly alerting to align
and translate.
And this paper actually just won
the runner up test of Time Award
at ICLR 2025.
So that's pretty cool.
This has been a really
impactful paper over time.
But it turns out
that there's actually
a more general idea here and
a more general operator hiding
here.
We approach this problem
from the perspective
of trying to fix our
recurrent neural networks.
But it turns out the
mechanism that we
used to fix the recurrent
neural networks actually
is something general
and interesting
and really powerful
in its own right.
So now, we want to try to
pull that out, pull out
this idea of attention, and
divorce the idea of attention
from the recurrent
neural networks.
And it turns out
that attention will
be a very useful and
powerful computational
primitive for neural
networks in its own right,
even if then we can cut away the
recurrent neural network part
and just be left with
attention as the core
primitive in our architecture.
And that's where
we're going towards.
So now, what we want to do is
take this idea of attention,
as we saw it, in
recurrent neural networks,
and try to generalize
it and try to carve out
this independent operator
that can be used on its own.
So let's think about what this
attention mechanism was doing.
Basically, what this
attention mechanism did
is there were a bunch
of query vectors.
These are-- well,
maybe it makes sense
to talk about these
in the other order.
So there's data vectors,
which are like data
that we want to summarize.
These are the encoder
states of the encoder RNN.
So we have this input sequence.
And we've summarized that
into a sequence of vectors.
And the sequence
of vectors is data
that we think is
relevant for the problem
that we're trying to solve.
And now in the process of
trying to make use of that data,
we want to produce
a bunch of outputs.
And for each output,
we have a query vector.
A query vector is
a vector that we're
trying to use to solve an--
to produce some piece of output.
And in this case,
the query vectors
are the hidden states
of the decoder RNN.
And we have this property,
that for each query vector,
we want to go back, look
at the data vectors,
and summarize the information
in the data vectors
into a context vector for each--
well, OK, from the
purpose of attention,
this gets a little bit weird.
So the output of the
attention operator
are the context vectors that we
just talked about for the RNN.
So if we're thinking
about just, what
does that attention
operator do, the output
of the attention operator
were the context vectors
that we feed into the RNN.
So then what is the
attention operator doing?
The attention operator is
taking a query vector going back
to the input data vectors,
summarizing the data
vectors in some new way to
produce an output vector.
And that's what the
attention operator is doing.
Does that make sense as a
generalization of this attention
mechanism that we just saw?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I'll repeat it
again because it's tricky.
There's a lot of stuff flying
around here, a lot of boxes.
And we're changing
the words that we're
using to define the boxes.
So I get it, there's
a lot happening.
So what the attention
operator is doing
is there's a bunch of
data vectors, which
are the encoder hidden states.
Then we have a bunch
of query vectors,
which are the things we're
trying to produce output for.
Now, in the process of
processing a query vector,
we're going to go
back to the data
vectors, summarize the data
vectors in a new custom
way for each query vector, and
that will produce an output
vector, which is the
context to be fed
into the next tick of the RNN.
So our query vectors
are these guys in green.
For each query vector, we
go back to the data vectors,
summarize the data
vectors, and then produce
a new output vector, which
is one of the contexts
that we then feed into
the rest of the network.
So this is tricky
because we're trying
to go into this architecture and
carefully cut out the attention
part and cut it
out from the RNN.
So then we're going to try
to walk through this again
from the perspective of
just the attention operator.
So from the perspective of
just the attention operator,
we're going to
start with just one
query vector at first, which is
one of the states in our RNN.
We also have a bunch
of data vectors,
which are the encoder
hidden states in the RNN.
Now, the computation
that we want to perform
is, first, compute similarities
between that query vector
and all of the data vectors.
This is the exact same
thing that we just
saw, just written
in a different way.
So we use this FATT function to
compute the similarity scores
to compute similarities between
each data vector and our one
query vector.
Then once we have
those similarities,
we're going to squash
them through a softmax
to get attention weights.
And this will be a distribution
over the data vectors
that has been computed on the
fly for this one query vector.
Then we want to do is
produce an output vector.
This output vector is a linear
combination of our data vectors,
where those linear combination
weights are the attention scores
that we just computed.
So this is the output
of the attention layer.
And then in the context of
the larger RNN that we saw,
the output of the attention
layer, or the attention operator
will become an input to the
next tick of the decoder RNN.
But we're trying to
deprecate the RNN,
so we don't want
to talk about that.
We just want to talk
about the attention
and focus on the computation
happening inside the attention
layer.
So this is basically the
operator that we saw in the RNN.
We have this one--
we did this process
over and over
again of taking a
query vector, using
it to compute similarity scores,
getting attention weights,
getting an output vector.
Then we got a new query vector.
Where did that query
vector come from?
Attention operator doesn't care.
Get a new query vector, go back,
summarize the data vectors,
get a new output vector.
And that's the core of
the attention operator.
So now, let's try
to generalize this
and make it even more powerful
computational primitive.
Yeah, so in principle,
this FATT doesn't
have to be-- it could
be any function.
It could be any function
of two vectors that
outputs a scalar in principle.
But in practice,
we're actually going
to make it simpler in
a couple of slides.
But in principle, yeah, you
could just slot in any function
that you wanted there.
OK, so the first generalization
that we're going to do
is, actually, the
opposite of what
you just suggested and make that
similarity function simpler.
So we said in
principle, it can be
any function that
takes two vectors
and gives a similarity score.
What's the simplest possible
function that inputs two vectors
and gives us a scalar
similarity score?
It's a dot product.
So we want to try to
make things simpler
and also generalize
at the same time.
And it turns out
that a dot product
is good enough of
a similarity score
to be used for this purpose.
So the first thing
we're going to do
is, actually, just only use dot
products to compute similarity.
But it turns out,
there's a slight problem
with dot products.
And this one's subtle
because there's
a weird interaction between the
dot product and the softmax.
And that has to do
with what happens
when the dimension of those
vectors scales up or down.
So if you have--
the motivating
example is that if you
scale the dimension
of that vector, say,
we had a constant
vector of all 1's
of like dimension 10 versus
a constant vector of all 1's
of dimension 100, then
as we go to the higher
dimensional vector,
then when we compute
the sum inside that
softmax, then we're
going to be dividing
by a larger number.
So we'll end up with more
squashed probability scores,
as we go to higher
dimensional vectors.
That can lead to
vanishing gradients,
as we just saw in
the previous lecture
and prevent learning
of this whole thing.
So as a slight hack to prevent
that and make this architecture
more generalizable
scalable up and down
to different dimension
vectors, what we're going to do
is actually not use
the pure dot product
but scale the dot product
down by the square root
of the dimension of those
vectors that we're looking at.
And this is just a way to
prevent vanishing gradients
and give nicer gradient flow
through the softmax for a wider
range of dimensions of vectors.
And this turns out
to be very important
because, as we make these
networks bigger and bigger
and bigger over time, we want to
get higher dimensional vectors
because that gives us more
compute, more capacity.
So we always want to think
about how our architectures will
scale, as we make the parts
of those architectures
get bigger and
bigger and bigger.
So this scaled dot
product is actually
really important for preventing
vanishing gradients here.
Yeah, question was, we're
limited to data and query
vectors of the same size,
but we'll actually fix that.
So our first generalization
was to use, actually,
scaled dot product similarity
as our similarity measure.
So now, if we go back and look
at the shapes of these things,
we have one query
vector of dimension Dq.
We have data
vectors of dimension
Nx by Dq as well because it's a
dot product they need to match.
But there's actually--
a next generalization
that we're going to do is
have multiple query vectors.
Maybe we don't want to process
just one query vector at a time,
we want to have the ability
to process a whole set
of query vectors all at once.
And this happens in the RNN.
We did end up with a
bunch of query vectors.
And it's useful for
the attention operator
to be able to process, not
one query vector at a time,
but basically process a set of
query vectors all in parallel,
and perform the exact same
computation in parallel
for a whole set
of query vectors.
So in this case, we've now
generalized it to have N.
So Q is now a matrix
of shape Nq by Dq.
So we have Nq query vectors.
Each of those query
vectors has dimension Dq.
We have our data vectors is
a matrix of size Nx by Dq.
And now, the computation
changes a little bit
because now, when we compute
these alignment scores, when
we compute these
similarities, basically,
we want to compute all pairs
of similarities between all
of the input data vectors and
all of the input query vectors.
And each one of
those similarities
is a dot product, or
a scaled dot product.
So what's a very efficient
and easy and natural
way for us to compute
dot products between two
sets of input vectors?
That turns out to be
a matrix multiply.
Because remember, when
you do a matrix, multiply,
each entry in the output matrix
is the inner product of one
of the columns of
one of your matrices
and the rows of
your other matrix.
And that's what-- so then each
entry in the output of a matrix
multiply is exactly the dot
product between the rows
and the columns in the output.
So by computing
a matrix multiply
between our query vectors
Q and our data vectors X
and you need to get
a transpose in there
to make the rows and columns
match up in the right way,
this basically gives us--
lets us compute all the
similarities between all
the data vectors
and all the query
vectors all in one
simple matrix multiply.
Now, we still need to compute
these attention weights.
Remember, the
attention weights, we
want to compute for
each query vector.
We want to compute a
distribution over the data
vectors.
Well, we already have these--
now, our similarity
scores are not just
a single vector
of scores, they're
now a matrix of scores
giving all the similarities.
But we still want to compute
a distribution over the data
vectors for each query
vector independently.
So now, we need to
compute the softmax
over just one of the axes
of that matrix of similarity
scores.
So this is basically the
exact same computation
that we just saw.
We're just doing it in parallel
for a set of query vectors
all at once.
Now, we need to compute
the output vectors.
And remember, the
output vectors were
going to be a weighted
combination of the data vectors,
where those weights are
the values in the softmax.
And it turns out that
this is also something
that matrix multiply does.
Another way to think
about matrix multiply
is that when you take a matrix
multiply of two matrices,
a different way to view a
matrix multiply is that it takes
a linear combination
of, oh man, am
I going to get the rows and
the columns in the right way?
But I think you get
the linear combination
of the columns of one
of your input matrices,
weighted by the values in
the other input matrix.
So this is another
interpretation
of matrix multiplication.
So then if you work
through the indices
and draw some little
pictures for yourself
to prove to yourself
what's going on,
it also turns out that
in order to compute--
now, what we want to do is
compute many linear combinations
of the data vectors, where
each linear combination will
be given by the probabilities in
one of the rows of the attention
matrix.
So we can compute all at once
with another matrix multiply
between the attention matrix
A and for data vectors X.
And again, you need to get the
transposes in the right order
to make this work out.
But basically, this is the exact
same operation that we just saw,
but we're now doing it for a set
of query vectors all at once.
And it turns out that we can
do it all at once with just
a couple of matrix multiplies.
A next way that
we'll generalize this
is notice that in this
equation, the data
vectors X are actually entering
in two different places
in this computation.
The first place that
we're using the data
vectors X is to
compute similarities
with the query vectors in
this similarities computation.
So in that notion,
what we're trying to do
is say, oh, for a
data vector, how much
do you line up with
each query vector
as measured by an inner product?
But then we're also using
the data vectors, again,
to compute the output vectors.
So the output vectors are
now a linear combination
of the data vectors weighted
by our attention weights.
And it maybe seems a little
bit weird to reuse the data
vectors in those two
different contexts.
So now, what we want to do
is separate those two usages
of the data vectors and
let the network figure out
for itself, two different
ways to use the data
vectors in those two contexts.
So to do that, we'll introduce
this idea of keys and queries.
So now, what we're
going to do is,
we had a set of data vectors,
but what we're going to do is,
for each data vector, we're
going to project each data
vector into two vectors.
One is a key vector.
One is a value vector.
And the idea of the key
vectors are the key vectors
are going to be compared
with the query vectors
to compute the alignment scores.
And the value vectors
are what we're
going to compute linear
combinations of in order
to compute the output
from the layer.
And this also-- so then the
way that we implement this
is we add two learnable weight
matrices, the key matrix
and the value matrix,
which are going
to be linear projections
that project the input--
or that project the data vectors
into key vectors and value
vectors.
So now, the data
vectors, remember,
we have N data vectors,
each of dimension Dx.
So now, the key matrix is
a linear transformation
that projects from
Dx into Dq because we
know that we're going to
compare the key vectors
with the query vectors.
So they need to have the same
dimension as the query vectors.
So that will project each--
so then applying
matrix multiply of K
equals XWk will project each
data vector into a key vector
of dimension Dq.
Then we'll separately
have another weight matrix
that projects from
Dx to Dv, which
is the dimension of the
value vectors, which
in principle could be different
than the query vector dimension.
And then we'll separately
project each data vector
into a value vector, again, with
a matrix multiply operator here.
And the intuition here is that
it's like in a search engine,
you want to separate what you're
looking for from the answer you
want in response to that query.
So you go to Google, or
these days, ChatGPT and you
type in like, what is the
best school in the world?
That's your query.
And then the value
you get-- well,
that's the query that
needs to be combined
with the keys in the back end.
But then the value,
the data you want
to get back from that
query, is actually
different from the
query you typed in.
So we want to separate this idea
of you put your query in, what
is the best school in the world?
That query needs to go match
on all the different strings
on the internet.
And then the value
you want to get back
from that query
is Stanford, which
is a different value, which
is different from the query
that you put in.
So that's the intuition.
Another intuition
between separating
the keys and the queries and the
values in this way, the query
is what I'm looking for.
The key is-- in the back end, we
have some record of all the data
back there in the data vectors.
But when we query,
we want to match up
against part of the--
potentially, just part
of the data vector.
And then the thing we want to
get back from the data vector
is the value.
So we're separating the
usage of the data vectors
into those two different
notions of keys and values.
Then we can visualize
this in a different way.
So now, we're finally
throwing away the RNN
and we're looking at attention
just as an operator on its own.
So we can step through
this operation again.
We've got our query
vectors coming in.
We've got our data
Now, what we're going to do
is from the data vectors,
we're going to project each data
vector into a key and a value.
Then we're going to compare
each key with each query
to get our similarity scores.
So this is a similarity-- this
is a matrix of scalars, giving
the similarities between
each key and each query.
Then once we have this
matrix of similarity scores,
we want to compute a
distribution over each--
a distribution over the
data vectors for each query.
So that means we
need to run softmax
over this matrix of
alignment scores,
where we compute the
softmax over each row.
Then what we do is, we want
to reweight the value vectors
by the attention
scores in the softmax.
Oh, actually, no,
sorry, we want each--
we want each column to be--
we want each column to be
a distribution.
Because we want, for each query,
a distribution over the keys.
Which means we want
softmax over the columns
because we want it to be
aligned to the columns.
So then what we do is
we've got this query one.
We've predicted
this distribution
over all of the keys
from this computation.
Then we're going to take a
linear combination of the values
weighted by these
attention weights
and compute a linear
combination of the value vectors
to produce our first
output vector, Y1.
And then the same thing
happens over here.
Our second query got
compared with all the keys.
We computed a distribution
over those alignment scores
to get a distribution
over the keys
for the second query, which
then get linearly combined--
then we use those to linearly
combine the values to produce
our output vector.
So now, this is now the
attention operator standing
on its own, divorced from
the recurrent neural network.
The question is, how do
you divide the data vector
into keys and values?
The beautiful part is we
don't have to say how.
We just give the neural
network the capacity
to split it by
itself by giving it
this mechanism to project
separately into keys and values.
But we're not going to
tell it how to do it.
These are just going
to be-- the key matrix
and the value matrix
are just going
to be learnable parameters
of the model that
will be learned via gradient
descent along with everything
else.
So just as we did
not tell it how
to align the English and the
French sentences, all of that
was learned via
gradient descent,
the model will learn for itself,
how to separately project
into keys and values
in a way that's
sensible for the problem--
that's helpful for the
problem it's trying to solve.
So the keys and values,
you might think of it
as some kind of filter.
So the data vector might
have a lot of stuff in there.
But for the task
at hand, we might
want to filter the data
vector in various ways
and only try to match our
queries against part of it.
And we only care about
retrieving information
of a different part of it.
So you could think
of those as, yeah,
filtering the
information in the data
vector in two different ways.
OK, so this is basically
our attention operator.
And now, there's no RNN here.
This is just a
neural network layer
that you could have
standing on its own.
It receives two inputs,
the query vectors
in the data vectors.
It has two weights of
learnable parameters,
which are the key matrix
and the value matrix.
It inputs two
sequences of vectors,
outputs a sequence of vectors.
So this is a neural network
layer in its own right
that you could start to plug
into your neural network
architectures in various places.
This is sometimes called
a cross-attention layer
because it has two sets
of inputs coming in.
The idea is, we have both data
vectors and query vectors.
They're potentially coming
from two different sources.
And this is sometimes useful.
So that I have a set of queries.
For each query, I want to
go and summarize information
from my data, which is
potentially different,
or a different number,
or totally different
from my query vectors.
So this is sometimes called
a cross-attention layer
because we're
cross-attending between two
different sets of things.
But there's another
version of this
that happens maybe
even more commonly is
a self-attention layer.
So here, what we're
going to do is,
we only have one set of things.
We only have one
sequence of inputs.
We have one set of vectors,
one sequence of vectors
that we're processing.
And then so now, we no
longer have this separation
between data vectors
and query vectors.
We just have one
set of input vectors
that we would like to process.
So in a self-attention
layer, we're
going to have one-- we're going
to have a set of input vectors,
and we're going to produce
a set of output vectors.
So we want to input a set
of vectors x, output a set
of vectors y that are the same
number as the input vectors.
But now, the mechanism
of this is, basically,
the same attention
mechanism that we just saw.
But now, rather than
projecting-- but then
we're still going to use
this notion of filtering.
But now, rather than
projecting our data vectors
into keys and queries, as
we previously did, now,
what we're going to do is take
each one of our input vectors
and project it to
three different things.
From each of our
input vectors, we're
going to project it to a query,
to a key, and to a value.
And so the equations
change just a little bit,
but the picture over
here doesn't actually
change very much.
For each of our input
vectors, we separately
project it to a query,
to a key, and to a value.
And now, we have the
exact same computation.
Now, we've got queries, we've
got keys, we've got values.
From the perspective of
everything happening up here,
it's all the same.
It just so happened
that we computed
the keys and the queries
and the values all
from different linear
projections of those same input
vectors.
But all the computation
is otherwise shared.
Yeah, question is, what
are D in and D out?
How are they sized?
So these are going to be
architectural hyperparameters
of the layer.
Just when we have a learnable
linear layer in a model,
a linear layer basically
projects from D in to a D out,
those are going to be
architectural hyperparameters
of the layer.
Same thing with a self-attention
layer, the D in and the D
out are going to be
architectural hyperparameters
of the layer.
And in principle, they
could be different.
There's enough there's enough
flexibility in this architecture
so that, in principle, D in
and D out could be different.
Although I don't think
I've almost ever seen that.
In practice, they're
almost always the same.
So I've been like a little bit
extra general in the notation
here.
OK, so I don't know
that we necessarily
need to walk through this.
Oh actually, there is
one important thing.
So I said that we are
separately projecting the inputs
into queries, keys, and values.
So that happens via three
matrix multiplies with our three
learnable weight matrices.
Now, we have three learnable
weight matrices, one for keys,
one for values, one for queries.
And we separately project
the input vectors X
into keys, queries, and values.
But in practice, we
can, actually, typically
compute just one matrix
multiply all at once for those
because it's typically
more efficient on hardware
to do fewer large matrix
multiplies than it is to do more
smaller matrix multiplies.
So a pretty common trick
in practice is to fuse--
is to concatenate these three
matrices along the dimensions
and compute all of these
keys, queries, and values
for all the input
vectors all at once
with one big matrix multiply.
If you've read
transformers before,
they sometimes separate
between encoder and decoder
transformers, or encoder
decoder attention.
So in that case, this would
be the decoder only attention
if you've read
transformer papers before.
And which corresponds
to the way that it's
used in the decoder of the
RNN in the initial example
at the beginning of class.
But this mechanism is
actually just the most--
the most commonly used
flavor of attention
nowadays is this sort
of so-called decoder
only attention.
So we are quite divorcing
ourselves away from the RNN now.
So this flavor of
it doesn't really
make sense to be used
in the RNN that we
saw at the beginning of class.
So we've basically been doing
a little bit of sleight of hand
here, where we introduced
this architecture
for the purpose of RNN in this
very concrete case of machine
translation,
sequence to sequence.
But we've now
generalized it to become
a totally different operator
that can be used all on its own.
And in this particular
generalization
into self-attention, it
actually no longer can
be used in that decoder in RNN.
But it's a very
useful primitive that
gets used in a lot of
other places, it turns out.
OK, the question is, what's
the benefit or difference
between the self-attention
versus the cross-attention?
They would get used
in different contexts.
So in some situations,
you naturally
have two different kinds of
data that you want to compare,
which we saw, for example, in
the machine translation setting.
We have an input sentence.
We have an output sentence.
We believe that there's
some natural structure
in the problem, that there's
two different sets of things
that we want to compare.
That also might happen
in, say, image captioning.
Say, we have an
input image, we want
to produce an output
sentence, there's
two different kinds of
things we want to compare--
pieces of the image
and tokens in the words
that we're generating.
So for some problems, there's
just this natural structure,
where you have two different
kinds of things floating around.
But for other problems, there
aren't two kinds of things.
There's just one thing.
So say, you're doing
image classification,
then there's only an image.
We just want to
process the image.
So in that case, we just want
to compare parts of an image
with itself.
And that's where you would
use a self-attention layer.
So they just get used for
different kinds of problems.
But we want to--
but crucially, we
want to reuse, basically,
the same machinery
and the same
computational primitives
to be used in those
different kinds of problems.
And that's really beneficial.
There's a couple interesting
things about attention
that I want to get through.
So one is like, let's
consider what happens
if you permute the inputs.
We had a set of
input vectors, what
happens if you shuffle
them and process them
in a different order?
Now actually, a lot of
interesting stuff happens.
So the keys, the
queries, and the values
will all end up the
same because they
are computed as linear
projections of the input.
So we'll end up getting the
same keys, queries, and values.
They'll just be in a different
order, shuffled in the same way
that the inputs were.
And now, because our
similarity scores were just
dot products, we'll also end up
with the same similarity scores,
just, again, shuffled
in accordance
with the way we
shuffle the input.
Same thing with the softmax.
Softmax doesn't actually care
about the order of its inputs.
So the softmax is now operating
on the same vector but shuffled.
So each column of
our attention weights
will end up the same as
they did before, just
shuffled, and then same thing
with linear combinations.
So our outputs Y will actually
still be the same outputs
as we had before.
They'll just all be shuffled.
So that means that there's a
really interesting structure
here called permutation
equivariance.
Remember, we saw this a couple
lectures ago with convolution.
Now, we see a different
equivariance property
of these self-attention layers.
Which is that if we
shuffle the inputs,
then the output-- then
we get the same outputs,
just shuffled in the same way
that the inputs were shuffled.
And this kind of
means, in this case,
that self-attention
doesn't actually
care about the
order of the inputs.
If we change the
order of the inputs,
we'll get the same outputs
just shuffled in the same way.
The computation of
the layer does not
depend on the order in
which we present the inputs.
So that means that we can think
of self-attention actually not
as operating on
sequences of vectors.
They happen to be packed into
an ordered sequence of a matrix.
But we really think
of it, instead,
as operating on an
unordered set of vectors
because the outputs that
we get don't actually
depend on what order we packed
those vectors into our input
matrix.
So we really think
about this as a kind
of different neural network
primitive that fundamentally
operates on sets of vectors,
rather than sequences
of vectors.
But this is,
sometimes, a problem.
Sometimes, it is useful to
tell the neural network what
the order of the seq-- what
the order of the entries is.
So as a quick fix to
that, we'll sometimes
concatenate an
additional piece of data
onto each of the input vectors,
called a positional embedding,
that is basically
some piece of data
that tells the neural network,
this one's at index one,
this one's at index two,
this one's index three, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
And there's a bunch of
different mechanisms for that.
The question is, is it going
to train to the same result?
I'm not really talking
about the training here.
I'm talking about if you fix
the weight matrices and just
consider the computation
of the layer,
then if I were to
shuffle the inputs,
then I receive the same
outputs but they'll
be shuffled in the same way
that the inputs were shuffled.
So the question of what vectors
do I compute at the output
does not depend on the order
of the vectors in the input.
But the order of the vectors
I get from the output
does depend on the
order that they
were presented in the input.
So there's another
couple of tricks
we can do with
self-attention, but I'll
go through these a
little bit faster.
So sometimes, in a full
self-attention layer,
we allowed every
piece of the input
to look at every other
piece of the input.
But for some problems,
we might want
to impose some structure
on this computation
and say that certain
pieces of the input
are only allowed to look
at certain other pieces
of the input, rather
than looking at--
rather than everything being
allowed to look at everything.
And we can implement
this via notion
called masked self-attention.
So what we're going to
do is after we compute
these alignment
scores E, we're going
to go in and override
the alignment scores
with negative
infinities in places
where we want to
block the attention.
And now, if you have
a negative infinity
in your alignment scores,
then after you do a softmax,
it's going to end up as a 0 if
you walk through the softmax
computation.
So that means that
if there's a 0--
whenever there's a
negative infinity
in the alignment scores,
we end up with a 0
in the softmax score-- in
the scores after the softmax.
Which means that
output Y will not
depend on the value vector
computed at that index.
So this is a mechanism to let us
control which inputs are allowed
to interact with each other in
the process of the computation.
And we might want to do this
now for language modeling
because now, we've
generalized this operator
to the point, where we
don't need an RNN at all.
We can just use this
for the same problem
that we used to use in RNN for.
So now, we can use it to
process sequence of words,
like attention is very and
then output is very cool.
So then in this case, we're
doing the same language modeling
task that we saw last
lecture with RNNs.
But we can now
just do it natively
with this self-attention block.
But in this case, we want to
make the first output "is"
only depend on the first word.
The second output "very" only
allowed to depend on the first
two words.
We don't want to let the network
look ahead in the sequence
and cheat.
So here is where we
would use masking.
Another thing that we'll
sometimes do with self-attention
is called multi-headed
self-attention,
where you run n copies each
separate independent copies
of self-attention in parallel.
Why do you want to do this?
Because it's more
computation, it's more flops,
it's more parameters.
Deep learning, we always
want more and bigger.
And this is another way that
you can make this layer more
and bigger and more powerful.
So what we're going to
do is take our inputs X,
route them to H
independent copies
of separate
self-attention layers.
Those will each produce
their own outputs
Y, which will then stack up
along the output and then fuse--
and then have another
linear projection
at the output to fuse
the output data from each
of the independent
self-attention layers.
And now in this
case, this is called
multi-headed self-attention.
And this is basically the format
that we always see in practice.
So this is-- whenever you see
self-attention used these days,
it's almost always this
multi-headed self-attention
version.
And in practice, it
turns out that you
can compute this all with
matrix multiplies as well.
So you don't have
to run a for loop.
You can compute each of these
H copies of self-attention
all in parallel if you're clever
and use batch matrix multiplies
all in the right places.
So in fact, this whole
self-attention operator
seems like a lot
of stuff going on,
but it's really, basically,
just four matrix multiplies.
We have one matrix multiply,
where we take our inputs
and project them to
queries, keys, and values.
We have another matrix multiply,
where we compute Qk similarity.
For each Q, we compute the
similarity against all the K's.
And that's one big batched
matrix multiply now
in the multi-headed case.
We have another one
called V weighting, where
we want to take linear
combinations of all
the values weighted by
the softmax entries.
And that can be done in another
big batched matrix multiply.
And then finally, we
have an output projection
to mix information across
our different heads
of our self-attention.
So even though there's
a lot of equations,
there's a lot of
vectors flying around,
this whole
self-attention operator
is basically just four big
batch matrix multiplies.
And that's great because
matrix multiplies are
a really scalable,
powerful primitive
that we can distribute,
we can optimize,
and we can make this thing
highly parallel, highly
scalable, highly efficient.
Yeah, question is
that the x1, x2, x3,
they're exactly the same.
Yeah, but we're
just going to have,
basically, separate copies
of the self-attention layer.
They will all be random.
They'll all have different
weights, critically.
And those weights will
be initialized randomly,
different at initialization.
So it'll end up
learning to process them
in slightly different ways.
So this is just a way to give
extra capacity to the layer.
Oh, yeah, the only
thing different between
different heads is the weights.
So while the architecture
is exactly the same,
the computation is
exactly the same,
but they'll have
different weights.
And those weights will be
initialized to different things
at initialization.
But other than that, it's
all exactly the same.
OK, there's some stuff
there that we can skip.
But now, basically, we've gotten
to one really interesting place,
where we have, basically,
three different ways to process
sequences that we've
seen in this class.
The first is recurrent
neural networks.
We saw that recurrent neural
networks basically operate on 1D
ordered sequences.
And they're really cool.
They're really powerful.
People like them
for a long time.
But they're fundamentally
not very parallelizable.
Because of this
concurrent structure,
where each hidden state depends
on the previous hidden state,
then they're just a
fundamentally sequential
algorithm.
There's no way to parallelize
this across the sequence.
And that makes them
very difficult to scale,
very difficult to make very big.
Another primitive that
we've seen is convolution.
And convolution
basically operates
on multidimensional grids.
We've seen it in two-dimensional
grids in the case of images.
You can also run them on 1D
grids, 3D grids, 4D grids.
And convolution,
basically, is something
that mixes information locally
in N dimensional grids.
This is great.
It's very parallelizable.
Because by this notion of
sliding a kernel around a grid,
each position that we might
want to place the kernel
can, in principle, be
computed in parallel.
So this is a very
parallelizable primitive.
But it has a hard time building
up large receptive fields.
If we want to summarize
an entire very long input
sequence, or an entire very
large image with convolution,
we either need to have very
large convolutional kernels,
or stack up many, many,
many convolutional layers.
So that still introduces some
fundamental sequentiality
in the way that we need to
process large pieces of data.
And now, self-attention,
basically,
is a separate kind
of primitive that
operates on sets of vectors.
It naturally generalizes
to long sequences.
There are no bottlenecks
in the way that there are
in recurrent neural networks.
There's also no
necessity of stacking up
many, many layers of them
to let all the vectors look
at each other.
In one layer of
self-attention, every vector
looks at every other vector.
So with just one layer,
you can summarize-- you
can do a lot of computation.
And it's also highly
parallelizable.
As we saw, the whole operation
is just four big matrix
multiplies.
And matrix multiplies
are a great primitive
that we can distribute.
We can run on GPUs.
We can run in very
scalable, distributed ways.
The only downside of attention
is that it's expensive.
It ends up having
n squared compute
for a sequence of
length n and n squared,
or later n, or n memory
for a sequence of length n.
And if your n ends up being like
100,000, 1 million, 10 million,
n squared becomes
very expensive.
But you can solve that
by buying more GPUs.
So that's basically the
solution that people
have come up with here.
So basically,
attention has become
this super awesome
primitive that
is super powerful for processing
very arbitrary pieces of data.
And you might be wondering,
which of these you should use?
Attention is all you need.
It turns out that
of the three, you
can get a long way
using only attention.
Now, the question is,
is parallelizable,
what's the advantage of that?
The advantage of that is that
in the history of computing,
it gets hard to make
processors faster.
We've run up against this
limit as a fundamental limit
in hardware.
That it's become very difficult
to make individual processes
faster.
But what we can do very easily
is get a lot of processors.
So the way that we are able
to marshal more computation
over the last two
decades is finding
algorithms that do
not require running
on one really fast processor.
But instead, if we can have
an algorithm that can make use
of 10 processors, or 100
processors, or 1,000 processors,
or a million processors, I want
to blanket the entire Stanford
campus with processors and have
all of them working together
in concert to process
this big thing.
If we can find
algorithms that do that,
that's how we can scale up
and get really big, powerful
computations.
So the benefit of
parallelizability
is that if you have
algorithms that can trivially
make use of more and
more and more processors
in parallel, then we can
scale up those algorithms
without having to wait for
our individual processors
to become faster, which
they may never will.
Yeah, is there a trade-off
with the n squared?
I think the n squared is
actually a good thing.
So it seems bad.
You're taught in
computer science
that parameters
inside that n is bad.
But in the case of neural
networks, for compute,
it could actually be a good
thing because more compute means
the network is doing
more computation,
it has more ability to think,
more ability to process.
So actually, the more
compute the network
does on the input sequence,
actually, maybe the better
answer it could arrive to.
So it means that
it's more expensive,
but that's not
necessarily a bad thing.
So basically, the
transformer is now
a neural network architecture
that puts self-attention
at the core of everything.
So our input is going to be a
set of vectors X. Then we're
going to run all those vectors
through self-attention, which
is, as we just said, this
amazing primitive that lets all
the vectors talk to each other.
After that, we'll wrap
that self-attention
in a residual connection
for all the same reasons
that we wanted to use residual
connections in ResNets just
a couple of lectures ago.
Then we will take the output
of that residual connection,
pass it through a
layer normalization.
Because as we saw in
ResNets and in CNNs,
adding normalization
inside your architectures
makes them train more stably.
But then now, there's
something interesting.
Because the self-attention,
basically, what it does
is compares all the
vectors with each other.
And that's a very
useful primitive.
That's a very
powerful thing to do.
But we also want to give
this network the ability
to perform processing on vectors
independently one-by-one.
So then there's a
second primitive
inside the transformer, which is
the multi-layer perceptron, MLP,
also called FFN.
But basically, this is a
little two layer neural network
that operates independent--
that is run independently
on each one of our
vectors inside.
So then this works in concert
with the self-attention,
where self-attention lets all
the vectors talk to each other
and compare with each
other and the FFN
or MLP lets us perform
computation on each vector
independently.
We'll also wrap the MLP
in a residual connection,
put a layer normalization, and
put a box around the whole thing
and call it a neural
network block.
So this is our
transformer block.
And a transformer is just a
sequence of transformer blocks.
And these things have gotten
much, much bigger over time.
The architectures haven't
changed too much since 2017
when this was introduced.
The original transformer was
something like 12 blocks,
200 million parameters
and now, where
people are training transformers
with hundreds of blocks
and trillions of parameters.
So this same
architecture has scaled
across many orders of
magnitude in compute and size
and parameters over
the past eight years.
They can be used both
for language modeling
as we already seen.
They also can be
used for images.
And here, the application
is fairly straightforward.
Given an image, we
basically divide the image
up into patches, project
each of those patches
separately into a vector.
Those vectors then get passed
as inputs to our transformer.
And then the output gives us
one output from the transformer
for every patch in the input.
Now, if you want to do something
like a classification score,
or do a classification
problem, then you
do a pooling operation on
all the vectors coming out
of the transformer and
have a linear layer that
predicts your class scores.
So then this same
architecture of a transformer
can be applied
both to a language
and to images and to a lot
of other things as well.
I mentioned, there have
been a couple minor tweaks
to transformers since they
were first introduced.
But we're running out
of time so I'll just
leave those as extra reading.
So the summary of where we get
to at the end of this lecture
is, basically, two things that
I promised at the beginning.
One is that we
introduced attention,
which is this new
primitive that lets
us operate on sets of vectors.
It's highly parallelizable.
It's basically just a
couple of matrix multiplies.
So it's highly scalable, highly
parallelizable, highly flexible.
It can be applied in a lot
of different situations.
And the transformer, which
is now a neural network
architecture that
uses self-attention
as its main
computational primitive.
And the transformer is basically
the neural network architecture
that every application in deep
learning is using these days.
So that's super powerful, super
interesting, super exciting.
The transformers have been
with us for eight years now.
And I don't see them
really dying anytime soon.
So that's pretty exciting.
So that's basically it
for today's lecture.
And then next time,
we'll come back
and talk about some new tasks--
detection, segmentation,
visualization,
and see how we can use
these architectures to do
new cool things.